<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Poems sacred and satyricale</title>
            <author>Richards, Nathanael, ca. 1600-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34569</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14514035</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14514035</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102470</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57222)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102470)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1067:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Poems sacred and satyricale</title>
                  <author>Richards, Nathanael, ca. 1600-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 178 p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T. Paine for H. Blunden ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:102470:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102470:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Christian soldier, in armor and bearing sword and shield, receiving a laurel wreath or crown from a hand emerging from the clouds (Consolation), with the Flesh and the Devil on either side and the World beneath his feet</figDesc>
                  <p>Consolation</p>
                  <p>The Christian Souldier.</p>
                  <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Devil Reſiſted.</p>
                  <p>the Fleſh morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</p>
                  <p>y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> World Crucified.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Crocodilian World whoſe Shining gloſs</l>
                     <l>Is guilded Emptyneſs, and painted droſs:</l>
                     <l>Thy Fawns, or frowns I matter not, not I;</l>
                     <l>Crucifie th' I muſt Thy Siſter Fleſh muſt die.</l>
                     <l>And Soul deſtroying Devil whoſe malice tis,</l>
                     <l>T'accuſe th' Brethren that ſeek to bliſs:</l>
                     <l>Thy Roaring rage is nought; Stand off or I</l>
                     <l>Will make thee th' Worlds Captain, captively.</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102470:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102470:2"/>
            <p>POEMS SACRED AND SATYRICALL, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prayers Paradice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The World.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Fleſh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Ieſuite.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Devill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mans Miſery.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sinnes Infirmity.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sinnes Impudence.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Penitent Sinner.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Soules-ſea-fight.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The ſingle &amp; Married-life.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Teares Tryumph.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mercies Miracle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hope.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Charity.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Midnights Meditation</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Virtues Pyramid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chaſtity and Luſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Divine Dreame.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Divine Eccho</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deaths Maſqueing-Night.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By NATHANAEL RICHARDS.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>T. Paine,</hi> for <hi>H. Blunden</hi> at the <hi>Caſtle</hi> in <hi>Cornehill.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:102470:3"/>
            <head>THE <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THOR.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi> o man ſo high but er'e he die may fall,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>ll <hi>Fleſh</hi> is fraile, all ſubject unto thrall,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T</hi>her's no content on <hi>Earth,</hi> none certaine bred,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>H</hi>ealthfull to day we live; to <hi>morow</hi> dead.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>rt, nor <hi>Promotion,</hi> meuds not each <hi>Man's</hi> ſtate,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>or are the Greateſt, truly fortunate.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>dvanc'ments but a <hi>Breath,</hi> delight a <hi>Toy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>ach <hi>glitt'ring Pompe</hi> each ſoule-ſeducing joy</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>ike <hi>Hell-bred poyſon,</hi> workes the ſoules annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>eject all lewd, all vaine affecting pleaſure,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>J</hi>ntend thy future good, <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> treaſure.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>C</hi>onteſt with ſinne, ſtill ſtrive, the conqueſt weare</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>H</hi>e that will conquer, patiently muſt beare.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>t ſuch rare <hi>Combats,</hi> aide from Heav'n is ſent</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>eſpecting Man, ſinnes danger to prevent,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>D</hi>eare is the Love of God, in him delight,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi>eeke Heavenly joyes, thoſe comforts infinite.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102470:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THY AND NOBLY DISPO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SED THOMAS SOAME Eſquire, Alderman, and one of the Burgeſſes of Parliament for the Honorable City of</hi> LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough a <hi>Sranger</hi> to your <hi>Perſon,</hi> I am no Stranger in my thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Heart</hi> (to the All-glorious Majesty of Heaven) for ſuch as you: You whoſe <hi>knowne worth,</hi> &amp; inward <hi>Candor,</hi> nor frownes, nor Flatterie, could ever force from its true Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for the generall good. Monſter Ingratitude cannot ſay I flatter; Witneſſe this Cities approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unanimous conſent, free choice of you that are, (the All-guiding hand of Heaven be praiſed) free
<pb facs="tcp:102470:4"/>from the aſperſion, Spots and staines of this Worlds <hi>Vicious</hi> and <hi>Ambitious</hi> Greatneſſe. Let it not then ſeeme ſtrange, that I (incouraged by your <hi>Noble Vertues</hi>) have here made bold, (out of an honeſt heart) Right worthy Sir, unto your ſelfe to <hi>Dedicate</hi> this <hi>Booke.</hi> It is a knowne <hi>Maxime</hi> to approved Iudgements, that <hi>Illicita non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibere conſenſus erroris eſt,</hi> which being the full ſcope of this my endeavour, intended only for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of <hi>Vertue,</hi> deteſtation of <hi>Vice,</hi> and like the <hi>Sea-mans Compaſſe</hi> to direct ſoules from the dangerous <hi>Paſſage</hi> indirect. The <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rybdes</hi> Shelfes and Rocks of this uncleane and moſt uncertaine Ocean of the World. This being my intent, (as caveats againſt ſinne not to be cavilled againſt, but by guilty Perſons.) Accept then (ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Sir) this my good will, take it from him, who (leaving you and yours, all your faire Actions and occaſions preſent to the <hi>All-pure God</hi> which never leaves his) remaines</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Ever devoted to your Worthy Virtues
NATHANAEL RICHARDS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:102470:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>POEMS SACRED AND SATYRICALL.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Prayers Paradiſe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL-Potent Scatt'rer of Man's o'r rancke ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Thou that doſt raiſe the humble, the proud hate</l>
                  <l>Soule-ſaving God, joy to the beſt of men,</l>
                  <l>Great terrour to the damned, guide my Pen,</l>
                  <l>Head, hand, heart, all, apply my ſoule to win</l>
                  <l>Soules to thy glory; let the ſence of ſin,</l>
                  <l>(Companion ſtill to miſery) affright,</l>
                  <l>Times ſcoffing Idiots from the lewd delight</l>
                  <l>Of ſoule confounding ſinne, make us to pray</l>
                  <l>With ardency of ſoule, great God of day,</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:102470:5"/>
                  <l>Faſhion our wills to thine, let each proud eye,</l>
                  <l>Humbled with teares, admire thy Majeſtie.</l>
                  <l>The ſpirit of Prayer muſt amend us all,</l>
                  <l>(So writes the Churches <hi>Atlas,</hi> holy <hi>Paul,</hi>)</l>
                  <l>We ſhipwrack elſe; ſoules that will Heav'n inherit,</l>
                  <l>Muſt pray, and pray with confidence of Spirit;</l>
                  <l>Pray for our King, pray for the bleſt event,</l>
                  <l>Of this our <hi>Englands</hi> preſent Parliament:</l>
                  <l>Have we not cauſe; do's not this Nation know,</l>
                  <l>Warre and the Plague ſo threats our overthrow;</l>
                  <l>We ſoone were loſt, did not ſweet mercy yet,</l>
                  <l>Protect our Peace? let us not then forget</l>
                  <l>To faſt and pray, (Lord) make us all inclin'd</l>
                  <l>To praiſe thy Name, Eternally to mind</l>
                  <l>Thy mighty favours, unto this Realme more</l>
                  <l>Then all the World, for Peace and plenties ſtore;</l>
                  <l>While neighbouring Nations periſh by the ſword,</l>
                  <l>Fierce Fire and Famine, wanting the ſacred word</l>
                  <l>To ſolace ſoules; this Nation lives at peace,</l>
                  <l>And might continue did our murmuring ceaſe.</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102470:5"/>
                  <l>We heare the word preach't, have our recreations,</l>
                  <l>Walking abroad, our peacefull preſervations,</l>
                  <l>Our ſtreets have ſeene no Rider and his horſe</l>
                  <l>O're whelm'd in bloud, nor have we ſeene what's worſe</l>
                  <l>Big-belli'd women ript, the inſants braines</l>
                  <l>Daſht in their Fathers faces; nor whole lanes</l>
                  <l>Of Armies in the field wheltering in bloud,</l>
                  <l>Nor thouſands famiſh't in our ſtreets forfood.</l>
                  <l>Our bleſſed time of Peace did never ſpie</l>
                  <l>Cities a fire, poore people's diſmall crie:</l>
                  <l>Age torne by th'haire o'th'head, Virgins defil'd,</l>
                  <l>Dainty Dames raviſh't, and the tender child</l>
                  <l>Stab'd in the Mothers Armes; God grant ſuch ſights</l>
                  <l>May never fill our Land, with like affrights:</l>
                  <l>Importune Heav'n, on God alone rely,</l>
                  <l>True prayer to God, is what? <hi>Nuncius Coeli;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mercies ſweet meſſenger, that ſweetly beares</l>
                  <l>To Heav'ns bright Majeſty mans trickling teares</l>
                  <l>Wrapt up in ſighes, hearts-griefe, ſorrowes ſad face</l>
                  <l>Wrinkled with cares for ſinne, which conquers grace;</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:102470:6"/>
                  <l>What humble ſoule mounts heav'ns celeſtiall Ayre</l>
                  <l>In up-flying fervent purity of Prayer,</l>
                  <l>But God ſends downe a pardon; Age and Youth,</l>
                  <l>Through ardent prayer, prove the ſons of truth.</l>
                  <l>Fear'ſt thou ſtearne War, Fire, Sword, Times, deare yeares dearth?</l>
                  <l>Pray fervently, ceaſe not till Heav'n and Earth</l>
                  <l>Eccho the Spirit of thy Supplications,</l>
                  <l>Teares of contrition, holy meditations:</l>
                  <l>So ſhall no Devills ruling in the Ayre,</l>
                  <l>Nor difficult paſſage ſtop zealous Prayer.</l>
                  <l>"The want of prayer, proves the ſoules decay,</l>
                  <l>"Men ceaſe to proſper, when they ceaſe to pray.</l>
                  <l>We all are ſinners: ſinne raiſes ſuch a ſtorme</l>
                  <l>In our baſe blood, reaſon can ne're reforme.</l>
                  <l>Vrge reaſon to us, it will doe no good,</l>
                  <l>Fervent Prayer onely maſters fleſh and blood.</l>
                  <l>Tis <hi>Clavis coeli,</hi> which unlockes Gods treaſure,</l>
                  <l>"Fervent prayer opens and ſhuts Heav'n at pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>The Elements, <hi>Fire, Water, Earth,</hi> and <hi>Ayre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are all at the command of fervent Prayer.</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102470:6"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elijah</hi> prayed that ſier might deſcend</l>
                  <l>From Heaven, and heav'n alone did him befriend.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elijah</hi> pray'd, it rain'd not for the ſpace</l>
                  <l>Of three yeares and ſixe moneths on the earths face.</l>
                  <l>Fervent prayer never did true ſolace lacke;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> he prayed, and the Red-ſea fled backe,</l>
                  <l>The prayers of the faithfull never fail'd;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aarons</hi> fervent prayers prevail'd</l>
                  <l>Gainſt <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abirams</hi> ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Earth open'd, ſwallow'd them, with all their kinne.</l>
                  <l>Earneſt prayer truely is (Heav'ns truth to ſay)</l>
                  <l>From man to God, from God to man the way.</l>
                  <l>"Prayer maugre all Earths Villanous entices,</l>
                  <l>"Makes man at peace with God, at war with vices.</l>
                  <l>O Text of Truth never to be denide,</l>
                  <l>Celeſtiall prayer quells Luciferiall Pride.</l>
                  <l>Cooles raging luſt, tames the Malicious,</l>
                  <l>Envie, Wrath, Gluttony, cures the Covetous,</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns in that prayer when (circl'd round with vice)</l>
                  <l>Man conquers ſinne, that's Prayers paradice.</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:102470:7"/>
                  <l>Firme Prayer ſteeres ſoules to each ſoule-ſaving motion,</l>
                  <l>Sighes, Teares, repentance, and to all devotion,</l>
                  <l>As the true skill of a Pilote is unknowne</l>
                  <l>But in a Tempeſt; (or a Captaine prone</l>
                  <l>To noble deeds) his valour is unſeene</l>
                  <l>But in a battell (where the field hath beene</l>
                  <l>His mount of Honour) ſo the rare worth</l>
                  <l>Of a true Chriſtian, can be ne'r ſet forth,</l>
                  <l>Nor ever of th'All-viewing eye diſcern'd,</l>
                  <l>Till like the Hebrewes Gen'rall he has learn'd</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns pleaſing ſcience, the Celeſtiall Art</l>
                  <l>Of fervent Prayer; that's the true Chriſtians pare.</l>
                  <l>When the Hearts tooke with a delight to pray,</l>
                  <l>Soules clearely ſee, ſinde a compendious way</l>
                  <l>To know Heav'n ſavingly, to curbe offence,</l>
                  <l>And burne in raviſhing joy, truth's Excellence.</l>
                  <l>Such ſweet content, all mortalls Mundane wit,</l>
                  <l>(Humane delights,) can never equall i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>"The fixing of our hearts on heav'n by prayer,</l>
                  <l>"Heales ſinnes deepe feſtering wounds, kills killing care,</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:102470:7"/>
                  <l>Cures the diſtracted minde, proves ſoules defence,</l>
                  <l>Mercies ſubduer, ſacred conference.</l>
                  <l>O thou <hi>Ens Enrium,</hi> ſempeternall light,</l>
                  <l>Give me the ſpirit to pray, to pray aright;</l>
                  <l>Leſt Tempeſt-toſt with cares, thinking to ſhunne</l>
                  <l>Sinnes guife, on ruints Rocke my ſoule's undone:</l>
                  <l>"Pray then, O pray; he that prayes willingly,</l>
                  <l>"Be rich or poore, can ne'r live wickedly.</l>
                  <l>Prayer is the wing by which the ſoule do's flie</l>
                  <l>To Heav'n; and meditation is the eye</l>
                  <l>Wherewith we ſee God: by prayer we talke,</l>
                  <l>And by our Charity with God we walke.</l>
                  <l>Soules that will mount, gaine a Celiſtiall Crowne,</l>
                  <l>Muſt pray with ardency, looke up, not downe,</l>
                  <l>Like times too many mumblers that doe fall</l>
                  <l>To pray, on the halfe knee, or none at all,</l>
                  <l>Nor deſperately like ſuch, as thinke no ſinne</l>
                  <l>To come to Church, till Sermon time beginne;</l>
                  <l>Entring (O moſt abhorr'd) ſo ſneakingly,</l>
                  <l>So rude in rev'rence, pray ſo peakingly,</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:102470:8"/>
                  <l>As doth amaze religious fortitude,</l>
                  <l>To ſee lewd Mortalls baſe ingratitude</l>
                  <l>To their Redeemer; he that dreads heav'ns Rod,</l>
                  <l>Prayes ardently t'appeaſe the wrath of God.</l>
                  <l>Elſe like the ſickles edge, or Razor keene,</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns wrath works worldlings quick diſpatch unſeene,</l>
                  <l>Sharpe Vengeance undiſcernd full ſwift do's fall,</l>
                  <l>Leaves not a life uncut; but mowes downe all,</l>
                  <l>All grumbling Nations for their ſinnes exceſſe,</l>
                  <l>Pride to the poore, and rude unthankfulneſſe,</l>
                  <l>All Sects, all Schiſmes, that dare by booke maintaine,</l>
                  <l>And for their owne baſe ends, their godleſſe gaine,</l>
                  <l>"Make Scripture fight with Scripture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fatall ill,</l>
                  <l>"Sanctity ſave Kingdomes from ſuch curſed skill.</l>
                  <l>O the deepe folly that on man attends<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our fleſh and bloud are to our ſelves ſalfe friends.</l>
                  <l>We aske, and pray, but both amiſſe, and why?</l>
                  <l>We neither aske nor pray with fervency,</l>
                  <l>Our mindes at randome runne, this way, and that,</l>
                  <l>Vpon a world of vanities; Idle chat,</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102470:8"/>
                  <l>Faſhions, and fooleries; heav'n pardon ſinne:</l>
                  <l>We oft are out in Prayer, ſeldome in.</l>
                  <l>Sinne like a whirlewind circles feeble prayer,</l>
                  <l>Snatches it up, then whirles it into ayre,</l>
                  <l>Infections ayre, whoſe fatall poyſon ſpreads,</l>
                  <l>Powers downe hot vengance, miſery on our heads,</l>
                  <l>Croſſes, continuall cares, perpetuall paine,</l>
                  <l>Weake Prayer makes bitter ſtill the fruit of gaine,</l>
                  <l>Converts the key of kindnes into luſt,</l>
                  <l>Careleſſe prayer makes the life of love unjuſt,</l>
                  <l>Dulls noble wiſedome, over-rules all reaſon,</l>
                  <l>To the forgetfull ſoules Eternall Treaſon.</l>
                  <l>"We pray to heav'n, yet mind not heav'nly things,</l>
                  <l>"O foule ingratitude to the King of Kings.</l>
                  <l>"Mans mingling prayer with Earths cold cogitation,</l>
                  <l>"Merits ſwift vengeance; cloath'd in blacke damnation.</l>
                  <l>Think on thy God then, in thy dayes of youth,</l>
                  <l>Search in the Morning of thy yeares for truth;</l>
                  <l>Early betimes, before the evill day</l>
                  <l>Of ſinne, and Satan, that does ev'ry way</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:102470:9"/>
                  <l>Stops mans Coleſtiall journey, ſcatters ſnares</l>
                  <l>In every place; we are not ſafe at Prayers:</l>
                  <l>No ſooner man to heaven divine thoughts reaſe,</l>
                  <l>But ſtraight the Devill whiſpers in his eare,</l>
                  <l>Thinke on the world, thy wealth, thy poore eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Meanes muſt be had; thinke on thy neighbours hate:</l>
                  <l>Thinke on revenge, thinke on thy change, thy croſſes,</l>
                  <l>Thy law-ſuites, ſhips at ſea, thy land, thy loſſes;</l>
                  <l>Away with Prayer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; puzzell not thy braine,</l>
                  <l>Mind thou what's preſent, what's to come reſraine.</l>
                  <l>Thus ſpeakes the ſubtile Fiend, of purpoſe bent,</l>
                  <l>To put us out of practiſe to repent.</l>
                  <l>Like a falſe Sexton, he ſets backe the Clocke</l>
                  <l>To delay time, makes that our ſtumbling blocke;</l>
                  <l>Makes Time our Bawd, with flat'rie to betray,</l>
                  <l>And put us quite, out of the mind to pray:</l>
                  <l>With glorious outſide, and deceitfull riches,</l>
                  <l>Satan fooles mortalls, wiſeſt men bewitches.</l>
                  <l>Note but the whore-like minde of mans condition,</l>
                  <l>(So generally in all) when they petition</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102470:9"/>
                  <l>Their earthly King; (Lord) what a ſtirre we keepe,</l>
                  <l>The buſie braine's in labour, cannot ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>Nor take it's naturall reſt, the carefull minde</l>
                  <l>Is totally tooke up, wholly inclin'd</l>
                  <l>To give each word his weight; for to relieve</l>
                  <l>Our wants, to ſue for pardon, or repreive,</l>
                  <l>Profit or gaine; then head, hand, heart and all,</l>
                  <l>Knees that ne'r bend at Hean's high will, can fall</l>
                  <l>Proſtrate in all obſequiouſnes for place,</l>
                  <l>Lofty preferment, and a Princes Grace,</l>
                  <l>Then tongue and heart both jumpe in one agree,</l>
                  <l>Minde nothing but his Earthly Majeſtie;</l>
                  <l>Beg, kneele, implore, we fervently importune</l>
                  <l>Pardon for ſome foule fact, ſome brittle fortune.</l>
                  <l>This we can doe, we can with hot purſuite</l>
                  <l>To compaſſe our vaine ends, ne'r ceaſe ſinnes ſuite;</l>
                  <l>The trot, the amble, and the full cariere,</l>
                  <l>No ſpeede is wanting, nor no paines too deare</l>
                  <l>To purchaſe ſinnes Exchequer, riches ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Ambitious aymes, Times glory, Beauties whore,</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:102470:10"/>
                  <l>This too too many can, and in that way,</l>
                  <l>Eager like hungry hounds, ſoone ſent ſinnes prey;</l>
                  <l>But to the King of thoſe Eternall ſires</l>
                  <l>That ſpangle Heav'n, lukewarme in their deſires,</l>
                  <l>"Impudent in all Vice, in baſeneſſe bold,</l>
                  <l>"Chriſtians halfe coddl'd, neither hot nor cold,</l>
                  <l>"O Hell of hells; Man to'th' Celeſtiall Race</l>
                  <l>"Do's ſeldome runne, but with a Iade-like pace,</l>
                  <l>Never conſidering how the mind that's wrapt</l>
                  <l>In wilfull wickedneſſe, is ever apt.</l>
                  <l>To pine at Princes, ſnarle at pious lawes,</l>
                  <l>Scold people on to fight Religions cauſe.</l>
                  <l>When truth and all true Chriſtians know Religion</l>
                  <l>Conſiſts in true obedience, not Rebellion;</l>
                  <l>"Men that give way to ill, t'increaſe their good,</l>
                  <l>"Bring famine on a land, fierce fire and blood.</l>
                  <l>"All villages in a Kingdome, Sinne do's delude,</l>
                  <l>"Leaves it a prey to'th' law-leſſe Multitude.</l>
                  <l>In true obedience then, with humble knee,</l>
                  <l>Eye, head, hand, heart, pray to Eternity.</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:102470:10"/>
                  <l>Throw from thy minde all worldly cares, temptations,</l>
                  <l>All wandring, idle, vaine imaginations.</l>
                  <l>Abandon flaring pride, cloſe fiſted bribes,</l>
                  <l>And like the Father of twelve potent Tribes,</l>
                  <l>Tugge with Aimighty God, ſtill ſtrive to winne</l>
                  <l>Pardon for each foule fact, times uggly ſinne.</l>
                  <l>"Like Arts rare engin's Excellent's defence,</l>
                  <l>"Gainſt fires in Cities which (to cleare offence)</l>
                  <l>Raiſes from Earth ſo ſweet a watery ſhowre,</l>
                  <l>As ſlacks the furious flame, extincts her powre:</l>
                  <l>So let the Art of fervent prayer raiſe</l>
                  <l>Our watery teares to Heav'n, to Heavn'n that paies</l>
                  <l>In the deſcent, mans penitent deſires,</l>
                  <l>With plenitude of grace, to quench ſinnes fires.</l>
                  <l>God made the eare to heare the happineſſe</l>
                  <l>We have from him, the tongue ſtill to expreſſe</l>
                  <l>The glory of his name; the eye to ſee</l>
                  <l>The workes of his divine Integrity.</l>
                  <l>Eye, head, hand, heart, God the whole man did frame,</l>
                  <l>All to rejoyce in his All-Sacred name.</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102470:11"/>
                  <l>Happie the ſoule that prayes with ſincere ſorrow,</l>
                  <l>Repent to day, deferre not till to morrow.</l>
                  <l>And when you pray, thinke unto whom you pray;</l>
                  <l>T'is to the Worlds great builder, Lord of day,</l>
                  <l>'Mercies bright Majeſtie, th'Almighty ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>Iuſt grand decider of each poore mans wrong,</l>
                  <l>That tumbles downe the mighty, only can</l>
                  <l>Make the moſt Potent Prince, the pooreſt man;</l>
                  <l>The peace of Kingdomes in a breath disjoynt,</l>
                  <l>Spit all Earth's Children on warrs Rapiers point;</l>
                  <l>Turne fruitfull fields to yron, burne the graſſe,</l>
                  <l>And for our ſinnes, convert the Heav'ns to braſſe;</l>
                  <l>Swell ſurging ſeas, the dreadfull deepes with waves,</l>
                  <l>Stormes, famine, fire and ſword, to dig our graves,</l>
                  <l>How dare proud mortalls then ne'r take to minde</l>
                  <l>Heav's ſacred eye-fight? ſhall darke deedes ſo blinde</l>
                  <l>Mans Machivilian miſchiefe, as to thinke</l>
                  <l>Rais'd on Ambitions top, he cannot ſinke?</l>
                  <l>He muſt, he muſt; bad ſtates-menne'r ſo big</l>
                  <l>Fall of themſelves in time, breake like a twig.</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:102470:11"/>
                  <l>As one naile drives another out of place,</l>
                  <l>So time cleares truth, drives flat'rie to diſgrace:</l>
                  <l>Flatt'rers are fearefull Fiends, bright honours ſting,</l>
                  <l>Serpents, the worſt of Traitors to a King;</l>
                  <l>Court-Eare-wiggs, nimbly wrigling in the Eares</l>
                  <l>Of greatneſſe, mighty profits, madneſſe, feares,</l>
                  <l>So painted o're, ſhaddow'd for ſound advice,</l>
                  <l>"A good King cannot knowes vertue from vice,</l>
                  <l>Till Heav'n (that brings the darkeſt deedes to light)</l>
                  <l>Produce in time the truth, twixt wrong and right.</l>
                  <l>Man whoſoe're thou art, take this advice,</l>
                  <l>'Tis Angels counſell, Prayers Paradiſe.</l>
                  <l>"Walke after Gods way in the day of light,</l>
                  <l>"Or end thy journey in the darkeſt night,</l>
                  <l>Ther's but one univerfall remedy</l>
                  <l>For all our ills, each ſoules extremity,</l>
                  <l>And that is fervent prayer, all muſt reſort</l>
                  <l>To Prayer, or periſh; there is no ſafe port</l>
                  <l>(In this worlds <hi>Mare Mortuum</hi>) for man</l>
                  <l>To put into, but prayes; prayer only can</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:102470:12"/>
                  <l>Powr'd out in fervency of ſoule prevent</l>
                  <l>Plagues, famine, bloud, and death, warr's dire event,</l>
                  <l>Bred by ſeditious ſubjects, whoſe deſires</l>
                  <l>Are ſtill the fuell unto popular fires.</l>
                  <l>Prayer ſhall confound, dead all the divelliſh deedes</l>
                  <l>Of forraigne foes, all home-corrupted ſeedes:</l>
                  <l>Diſſembling Hypocrites, by hells aide appointed</l>
                  <l>To ſtiffe truth, and grieve the Lords annointed.</l>
                  <l>Prayer like to haſtie powder ſir'd ſhall choake,</l>
                  <l>Flame viperous Rebels to a ſudden ſmoake.</l>
                  <l>Pray then, through fervent prayer imitate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> wreſtle with bleſſed fate,</l>
                  <l>Subdue thy ſinnes, 'gainſt ſinfull fleſh and bloud,</l>
                  <l>"Importune heaven, and heaven will doe thee good.</l>
                  <l>"Gods promiſe is, if fervently we pray,</l>
                  <l>"And uſe our beſt indeavours ev'ry day</l>
                  <l>"To fly from ſinne, reſolving to betake us</l>
                  <l>"To holy meanes, he never will forſake us.</l>
                  <l>"Never did any doe their faire endeavour</l>
                  <l>"To pray to God, that ever loſt his labour,</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:102470:12"/>
                  <l>"Nay more, if God but ſee thy inclination</l>
                  <l>"To pray, he will prevent thy ſupplication,</l>
                  <l>Anſwer thy full deſire, e're thou canſt crave,</l>
                  <l>Grant that, thy heart did never hope to have:</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe good heaven 'tis true; ther's no deniall,</l>
                  <l>For I have found th'experimentall triall,</l>
                  <l>And were for ever like a ſoule in hell</l>
                  <l>Worthy to burne; ſhould I forget to tell,</l>
                  <l>In midſt of dangers, how I call'd on thee,</l>
                  <l>Mercifull God; and thou did'ſt ſet me free.</l>
                  <l>At home, abroad, at Sea, upon the land,</l>
                  <l>Here, there, and ev'ry where, thou Lord did'ſt ſtand</l>
                  <l>My ſure protector 'gainſt griefes infinite,</l>
                  <l>Times flatt'ring ruine, and the worlds deſpite,</l>
                  <l>Sickneſſe, ſad diſcontent, when I and care,</l>
                  <l>Shooke hands with ſorrowes Minion deepe deſpaire.</l>
                  <l>That very hower, in heavineſſe lockt up</l>
                  <l>Beyond all hope of health; then mercies Cup</l>
                  <l>I freely taſted; bleſſed be thy name,</l>
                  <l>To me my Gracious God, prove ſtill the ſame,</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102470:13"/>
                  <l>Circle me round thou All-Bternall health,</l>
                  <l>Gainſt all enticements, <hi>Honour, Beauty, Wealth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe fatall ſlies of ſinne; which though beſt men</l>
                  <l>Do ne're ſo much flap off, ſlie on agen:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arme, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me</hi> good heaven, <hi>Times Microcoſme</hi> in me,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Through Faith, Hope, Love,</hi> enable me to be</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Truths Champion; Troopes of Furies</hi> to withſtand,</l>
                  <l>And ſtave <hi>Hells Tempter off,</hi> dead ſinnes command.</l>
                  <l>"Times expert faithfull ſouldier is a Iewell,</l>
                  <l>"Fit for a King, to fight a Kingdomes Duell.</l>
                  <l>"Valour and honeſty are Princely twinnes,</l>
                  <l>"Ther's nothing makes a Coward, but his ſinnes.</l>
                  <l>Lord, let a watchfull <hi>Centinell</hi> within</l>
                  <l>My weake mortality, ſo keepe out ſinne,</l>
                  <l>That when ſo e're we meet, <hi>Morne, Noone,</hi> or <hi>Night,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I with my good ſword Faith, may in thy ſight,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heavens Saint-like</hi> Souldier prove, ſubdue and winne</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At truths</hi> cloſe conſtant fight, conqueſt o're ſinne.</l>
                  <l>Heare me my God, mount thoughts with admiration,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the higheſt ſtep of contemplation.</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:102470:13"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Irradiate (Lord)</hi> my mind, paſt ſinnes controle</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conari Sancta; Angelize my</hi> ſo ule.</l>
                  <l>Give what thou doſt command great God, and then,</l>
                  <l>Command even what thou wilt; Amen, Amen.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>EArneſt</hi> prayer, and the committing of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Will never lodge together in one Inne.</l>
                  <l>For ſure if prayer cannot make thee ceaſe</l>
                  <l>From ſinne; ſinnes ſure to rob thy ſoule of peace,</l>
                  <l>And make thee leave off praying; God's all Eye,</l>
                  <l>Let our petitions then with fervency</l>
                  <l>Flie unto him, whoſe Majeſty is ſuch,</l>
                  <l>It comprehends all power; do but touch,</l>
                  <l>Trie, and then truſt, petition but his name</l>
                  <l>In ardency of ſoule, you le find a flame</l>
                  <l>All-heav'nly holy, thrill through thy vitall blood</l>
                  <l>To quell corruption, turne all ill to good.</l>
                  <l>O that the Soules of Mortall's to the life</l>
                  <l>Would Act this part, ſubdue ſinnes ſtormy ſtrife</l>
                  <l>Through fervent prayer; and in that ſwift courſe runne,</l>
                  <l>Firme as the golden taper of the ſunne</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102470:14"/>
                  <l>Which hourely ſailes the Circuit of the Skie,</l>
                  <l>That, were excelling heav'nly harmonie.</l>
                  <l>'Twould make this Globe on Earth whereon we tread,</l>
                  <l>Times glorious Theater; the rich ſtage ſpread</l>
                  <l>And hung all-round with ſilver ſhining ſtarres</l>
                  <l>Prickt fall of holy thoughts; in them no jarres</l>
                  <l>Of times diſcording muſicke dare appeare,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Muſick-roome</hi> of concord being there;</l>
                  <l>There Truths faire Actor, where ſo e're he turnes</l>
                  <l>His penitent Eye, with holy raptures burnes,</l>
                  <l>Sees the All-ſole Spectator, <hi>Three in one</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Seated in gloryes Gallery; where none</l>
                  <l>But his <hi>Omniſcient</hi> bleſt beatitude,</l>
                  <l>Sits the ſole Iudge of ſoules Ingratitude,</l>
                  <l>Actors, and <hi>Action;</hi> mans good part, and his ill,</l>
                  <l>Th'unworthy <hi>Actors,</hi> dull, imperfect skill</l>
                  <l>Bred by diſtemper, groſſe neglect in ſtuddy,</l>
                  <l>Careleſſe Rehearſalls, and a skull ſo muddy,</l>
                  <l>As never minds th'infinite paines and Art,</l>
                  <l>Penn'd, to advance and fit him with a part</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:102470:14"/>
                  <l>That might immortalize; inflame deſire,</l>
                  <l>Raviſh his ſinne-ſicke ſence; his ſoule inſpire</l>
                  <l>With ſacred extaſie; high apprehenſion,</l>
                  <l>Seraphicall love, divine affection.</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns gracious Actor makes this pretious uſe</l>
                  <l>Of his faire Part; ne'r turnes it to abuſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor wrongs the writer; but amaz'd with wonder,</l>
                  <l>As one ſhot through and through with holy thunder</l>
                  <l>At pious lines; whoſe powerfull Energie,</l>
                  <l>(In Noble ſpirits fruſtrates miſerie,)</l>
                  <l>Tames Pride, cooles luſt, makes the wiſe Actor ſee</l>
                  <l>His ſoule in danger; circl'd with ſinnes, that He,</l>
                  <l>In all meeke Humbleneſſe of ſoule prepares him,</l>
                  <l>Not raſhly hot (like ſome that goe to ſwimme,)</l>
                  <l>But takes a time to coole by meditation,</l>
                  <l>Ponders with ſweet celeſtiall affectation</l>
                  <l>On his ſoule-pleaſing Part, dares not venter</l>
                  <l>To tread Times <hi>Stage;</hi> nor unadvis'd to enter</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:102470:15"/>
                  <l>Till perfect in that part, whoſe excellence</l>
                  <l>Gaines grace, ſinnes pardon, <hi>Mercles Audience.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then like a bold and able Musketeire</l>
                  <l>Arm'd with a world of valour, trampling feare</l>
                  <l>Vnder his valiant foot, ſet's bravely on</l>
                  <l>The front of danger, where deſtruction.</l>
                  <l>In fiery flames, threatens to ſcourge his errour,</l>
                  <l>With never-failing death; yet ſcorning terrour</l>
                  <l>He in his good cauſe, ſtill oppoſing all,</l>
                  <l>Horrours and terrours what e're can befall,</l>
                  <l>Mounted on valours wings never retires,</l>
                  <l>Still he winnes ground; his ready nimble fires</l>
                  <l>Play thicke upon the foe, adde flame on flame,</l>
                  <l>Vndanted ſtands, to'th honour of his name.</l>
                  <l>And ne're forſakes the furie of the fight,</l>
                  <l>Till conqueſt Crownes him in his Countries right.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So fares</hi> it with <hi>Truth</hi>'s Actor, when his <hi>Part</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Enters him on the <hi>Stage a Pious heart.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then with clutch'd heav'd up hands above his head,</l>
                  <l>Eyes drown'd in Teares, and Armes divinely ſpread</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:102470:15"/>
                  <l>To meete with mercy, ſervently beginnes</l>
                  <l>So to bewaile the whirle-poole of his ſinnes,</l>
                  <l>That to gaine pardon, rid away all feares,</l>
                  <l>Sighes ſwimme in Sobs, deepe groanes in flouds of teares</l>
                  <l>Importunes heav'n, good <hi>Actions</hi> ne'rgives ore,</l>
                  <l>Till he hath quit the world, and clear'd ſinnes ſcore,</l>
                  <l>That like to <hi>Ariadne</hi> crown'd with <hi>ſtarrs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The ſoule in glory ſhines, all ill debarrs.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Admit</hi> at firſt, thou canſt not frame thy ſelfe</l>
                  <l>For Cares, and Croſſes, <hi>Luſt</hi> and worldly pelfe</l>
                  <l>To pray to God aright; yet ſtill endeavour,</l>
                  <l>Combate with linne; for <hi>victory</hi> perſevere:</l>
                  <l>What though to pray thou find'ſt thy ſelfe unapt,</l>
                  <l>Dull, heavie, ſad, eaſie to be intrapt?</l>
                  <l>Start from the Devill that enſnares thee ſo,</l>
                  <l>With ſloth's lewd <hi>lullaby</hi> for endleſſe woe.</l>
                  <l>Let me beſeech thee to be heavenly wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Rub drowſie dulneſſe from thy tender eyes,</l>
                  <l>Retire unto thy chamber, ſhut the doore,</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:102470:16"/>
                  <l>There wringing of thy hands fall downe, implore</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns ſacred aide, on thy dejected knees,</l>
                  <l>Pray to that glorious <hi>Majeſtie</hi> which ſees</l>
                  <l>The depth of darkeſt ſecrets; beate thy breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Till teares for ſinne ariſe ne'r give it reſt.</l>
                  <l>Strike, ſtrike the ſtonie ent'rance of thy heart,</l>
                  <l>Act to the life, the <hi>Publicars</hi> true part,</l>
                  <l>Knocke, and knocke hard; make <hi>l'ertues</hi> hammer felt</l>
                  <l>On thy hearts ſlinty Anvile; till it melt</l>
                  <l>To ſoft compaſſion; when that ſpring appeares,</l>
                  <l>Eyes turne to pearly drops, to flouds of teares,</l>
                  <l>Such ſtreaming pearles of pittie, being ſhed</l>
                  <l>For ſinne in thee; as ſhall when thou art dead,</l>
                  <l>Mount thy triumphing ſoule on Angells wings</l>
                  <l>To live for ever; Crown'd by the King of Kings:</l>
                  <l>Great is the power of fervent Prayer, that can</l>
                  <l>Conquer the All-Creator, raviſh man;</l>
                  <l>Fervent prayer, makes the crooked conſcience even;</l>
                  <l>Prayers, are thoſe <hi>ſcaling laders</hi> ſet to heav'n</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:102470:16"/>
                  <l>That lay long <hi>ſiege</hi> unto the throne of God,</l>
                  <l>Surround divinity, keepe in his Rod.</l>
                  <l>And never will depart, nor raiſe the ſiege,</l>
                  <l>Till they compell Natures <hi>Celeſtiall Liege</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To grant what they doe come for; faine would have,</l>
                  <l>To ſhield <hi>ſad ſoules</hi> from the infernall Grave.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:17"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:17"/>
               <head>THE WORLD.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VAine is this World, this Strumpet World that can</l>
                  <l>Yeild nothing conſtant; Love 'twixt man &amp; man,</l>
                  <l>Which next his Maker ſhould be moſt reſpected,</l>
                  <l>Is ſooneſt broke, and moſt of all neglected,</l>
                  <l>Miſſe-led by ev'ry vaine phantaſtick toy,</l>
                  <l>To forget God; bewitcht with carnall joy,</l>
                  <l>Bundles of Banbles, imbecillitie,</l>
                  <l>Biles of Apparell, Botch Nobilitie,</l>
                  <l>Lordſhip, Ladyſhips, Fool'ries, and Faſhions,</l>
                  <l>Luſt-panting Humours, ten thouſand paſſions.</l>
                  <l>Rich men, the more to blame, as this Age goes,</l>
                  <l>Debarre Houſe-keeping to maintaine gay Cloathes.</l>
                  <l>Arich Caroach, three hundred pound a Gowne,</l>
                  <l>Thirty pound a Smocke, or their wives will frowne,</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:102470:18"/>
                  <l>There is no living with them; they muſt ride,</l>
                  <l>Where, when, and how they lift in glitt'ring pride,</l>
                  <l>High flaſting burning Braverie, blind eyes,</l>
                  <l>Flint Hearts, dull Eares, deafe to the poore mans cries.</l>
                  <l>Such is the dullneſſe of mortalitie,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch the worlds cold Hoſpitalitte.</l>
                  <l>"Brave Cloathes, fall feeding, pride, eaſe, and laughter,</l>
                  <l>"Are peoples ſinnes, that breed a peoples ſlaughter.</l>
                  <l>"Times maw-wormes, muck-wormes, cancker-wormes of ſinne.</l>
                  <l>"Ruines our Peace without, our Peace within.</l>
                  <l>"Each duſtie Magiſtrate with Brib'rie fed,</l>
                  <l>"One robs the Living, another robs the dead,</l>
                  <l>"A third the Arch-theefe playes by cunning ſtealch,</l>
                  <l>"Knave Knights, by Patent rob the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"Ioyne with much, too much ill Injuſtice, he</l>
                  <l>"Sodomiticall letcher for a greedy Fee</l>
                  <l>"Dares licenſe luſt, glad if he may prevaile</l>
                  <l>"(Suck wealth from proſtitute Harlots,) never faile.</l>
                  <l>Mans mind, which moſt his maker ſhould reſpect,</l>
                  <l>(With feare and trembling, and that true reſpect</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:102470:18"/>
                  <l>Belongs to his high <hi>Majestie</hi>) the net</l>
                  <l>Of ſinne ſo ſnates, we worth-leſſe wormes forget</l>
                  <l>Gods thunder-darting Vengeance, glorious ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Still forget God, forget to contemplate</l>
                  <l>With raviſhing Love, true Love, pure heart, pure eyes,</l>
                  <l>That's the defect, makes hourely miſchiefs riſe,</l>
                  <l>"Ambitious Lords attir'd in Anticke ſhape,</l>
                  <l>"Joy in the waies of <hi>Lust, Murther,</hi> and <hi>rape.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"Ladies, with charmes, trickes, humours, that they have,</l>
                  <l>"Abuſe their Lords, diſpatch 'em to the grave.</l>
                  <l>"The jealous Husband, miſchievous in ill,</l>
                  <l>"Through vaine ſuſpect, his conſtant wife to kill.</l>
                  <l>"The careleſſe-Clergy-man in his degree</l>
                  <l>"Satan corrupts; makes for a goldenſee</l>
                  <l>"The greedy Lawyer, (fed by Clients ſtrife)</l>
                  <l>"Brib'd Angells take, for the the true Angell life.</l>
                  <l>Juſt Judge, the unjuſt'duſtie Magiſtrate,</l>
                  <l>Father the ſonne, the ſonne the Father hate;</l>
                  <l>Brother, the brother proſecute to death,</l>
                  <l>Quarrell for toyes; ſtop one anothers breath.</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:102470:19"/>
                  <l>The World do's hour'ly tempt fooles worldly wiſe,</l>
                  <l>The deceitfull Tradeſ-man that ſeemes preciſe,</l>
                  <l>And is an arrant Knave; to thinke the honie,</l>
                  <l>And only bleſſed life, ſtill to get monie,</l>
                  <l>Mockes at the poore mans vertue, and in pride,</l>
                  <l>Stiles him a vertuous Foole; thus Knaves deride</l>
                  <l>The poverty of men, which do's as ſarre</l>
                  <l>(In Heav'nly wealth) tranſcend them, as a ſtarre</l>
                  <l>The richeſt Gemme on Earth; But 'tis not ſo</l>
                  <l>With the World's wealthy worldlings; they ſay no,</l>
                  <l>Rich enough, honeſt enough; all they can</l>
                  <l>Aymes at the outward, not the inward man.</l>
                  <l>"Poverty made a ſcoſſe, a ſcorne, a winde,</l>
                  <l>"Gold ſmothers Vertue, blackeſt actions blinde.</l>
                  <l>"Gold got in Gods name, with an honeſt face,</l>
                  <l>"Comes flow; but in the Devills name apace.</l>
                  <l>Such is the Worlds condition, <hi>Good Mens</hi> thrall,</l>
                  <l>On Parth ther's no true comfort, none at all.</l>
                  <l>The honeſt minded Scholler ſhall no'r lack</l>
                  <l>"Sorrowes, nor want of meanes to breake his back.</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:102470:19"/>
                  <l>"The pittifull Souldier in his greateſt neede</l>
                  <l>"Ha's his throat cut; he ſhall be ſure to bleede.</l>
                  <l>"The faire Gameſter, for his milde ſquare play,</l>
                  <l>"Is ſooneſt cozen'd, ſure to loſe ev'ry day.</l>
                  <l>"The faithfull Lover oft is paid with hate,</l>
                  <l>"The more in Love, the more unfortunate,</l>
                  <l>Be rich or poore, in high or low eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Pth'mod'rate meane, or fully fortunate,</l>
                  <l>Vnſatiate mankind, ever diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Deſires to live, yet never lives content,</l>
                  <l>In ſcarcity of corne, for plenty cry,</l>
                  <l>In plenty, ſtraight forget God inſtantly.</l>
                  <l>Such is mans erring ſoule, which ought to know,</l>
                  <l>"Life's but a long ſad Pilgrimage of woe,</l>
                  <l>"An Arke of travell, ſhop of vanity,</l>
                  <l>"Store-houſe of triſtes, inhumanity.</l>
                  <l>"A field of ſtones, a path of thornie prickes,</l>
                  <l>"Meadow of Scorpions, Grove of Baſilickes.</l>
                  <l>The World's unquiet reſt is all Mans foe,</l>
                  <l>Dangers attend us where ſo'e're we goe.</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:102470:20"/>
                  <l>Miſchievous Deceits, Brawles, Quarrells; Fightings,</l>
                  <l>Falſe-hearted Neighbour-hood, baſe back-bitings.</l>
                  <l>Friendſhips, ſo faithleſſe ripe, full blowne with evill,</l>
                  <l>A friend to day, the next, for gaine proves Devill.</l>
                  <l>The World's condition right; 'tis ſlave to ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Beware of it; the world's a cunning ginne,</l>
                  <l>"Twill entrap ſoules; call then to God for grace,</l>
                  <l>Let griefe for worldly croſſesne'r take place,</l>
                  <l>Never let ſorrow runne into extreames</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe for ſinne; ſo ſhall Celeſtiall Beames</l>
                  <l>Glorifie thy ſoule; make it immortall,</l>
                  <l>Free it fromills what ever can befall</l>
                  <l>In this falſe promiſing world; this Maze of woe,</l>
                  <l>Where wretched worldlings know not where to goe</l>
                  <l>To winde them out; ſuch are the various waies</l>
                  <l>Of life-oppreſſing yeares, Moneths, Weekes and dayes.</l>
                  <l>As Proſe ill read, abide too much miſſuſing</l>
                  <l>Or vertuous verſe, when Rogues have the peruſing,</l>
                  <l>So fares it with the faire and flouriſhing line</l>
                  <l>Of that ſweet Heavenly ſtraine, Poeſie Divine,</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:102470:20"/>
                  <l>Baſely neglected, by the monſtre Crew,</l>
                  <l>"Of Puff-Paſt-Muddie-Mindes, that piſh, and mew,</l>
                  <l>"Make a wry Cloſe-ſtoole-face, a ſquint ey'd glance</l>
                  <l>"At Vertuous verſe, (whoſe ſad miſchance</l>
                  <l>"Is to goe unregarded) when the crime,</l>
                  <l>"Of a Laſcivious baſtard Ballad-rime,</l>
                  <l>"(If baudy enough) though ner'e ſo unfit,</l>
                  <l>"Winns favour, profit, and the praiſe of wit.</l>
                  <l>"Reade with delight, and much, too much requir'd,</l>
                  <l>"Coppies ſought after, greedily deſir'd,</l>
                  <l>"When perfect <hi>Poetrie,</hi> (<hi>Muſicke</hi> to the ſoule,</l>
                  <l>"Truths firme oppoſer, 'gainſt crymes filthy foule)</l>
                  <l>"If read, moſt read for faſhion, ſmall delight,</l>
                  <l>"No, comfort, no reſpect, but ſcornefull ſlight.</l>
                  <l>"And ſuch is Vertues Foe; the Worlds proud Minion,</l>
                  <l>"In whom ther's no true love, no perfect Vnion.</l>
                  <l>O Divine Poeſie I lament thy ſtate,</l>
                  <l>To ſee thy beauty diſproportionate,</l>
                  <l>So poorely in eſteeme, ther's few I ſee,</l>
                  <l>Or none at all, take true delight in thee.</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:102470:21"/>
                  <l>This wanton World, farre ſooner will approve,</l>
                  <l>Ioy in Pot-Poets louſie Ryming love,</l>
                  <l>Or want on <hi>Ovids</hi> ſtraine, to itch the eare,</l>
                  <l>And ſtirre the bloud to Luſt; rather then heare</l>
                  <l>The Sempeternall Aime of Noble verſe</l>
                  <l>Which points at Heav'n; and tells us of that ſierce</l>
                  <l>All-threatning Thunderer; he that deſcries</l>
                  <l>Our ſecret deeds; our blackeſt Actions ſpies,</l>
                  <l>At which; amaz'd my Muſe ſtands wrapt in wonder,</l>
                  <l>Beggs mercy, mercy, O thou God of Thunder,</l>
                  <l>Or we ſhall ſhipwrack all; All, too too blame,</l>
                  <l>Farre too unmindfull of Gods ſacred name,</l>
                  <l>His bleſſings day by day; his great mercy,</l>
                  <l>Long ſuffering, and excelling ſafety.</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould we wormes ſtand precious in Heavens ſight</l>
                  <l>And nor be damn'd to everlaſting-Night</l>
                  <l>For our foule-erring ſinnes; ſinnes that excell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ingratitude to Heav'n, picks open Hell.</l>
                  <l>Hell; that this inſtant Gapes to ſeize this world,</l>
                  <l>Which deſerves eu'ry moment to be hurld</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:102470:21"/>
                  <l>To endleſſe Flames; but for the Excellence</l>
                  <l>Of OVR FATHER'S wonderfull patience.</l>
                  <l>O for the Pen of pure perfection,</l>
                  <l>To Character mans imperfection,</l>
                  <l>Open the blind exceſſive ſinners Eyes,</l>
                  <l>(Force teares for ſinne) make him, himſelfe deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>Teare ope his eyes, that All-amaz'd with Horrour,</l>
                  <l>Trembling, he may behold his dreadfull Errour</l>
                  <l>Live; as in ſulphurous Flames, ſee his evill,</l>
                  <l>See the Grand Devill, and ceaſe to be a Devill.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Holla</hi> commanding Empreſſe of my Braine,</l>
                  <l>Whither thus ſtings my Muſe, divert thy ſtraine.</l>
                  <l>The Worlds a Racke, Times Tenter-hooke to catch</l>
                  <l>At mindes moſt honeſt, makes a man awretch,</l>
                  <l>Thouſands in want, finding no way to cure it,</l>
                  <l>Hazard the Gallowes, rather then endure it.</l>
                  <l>Mis'ry of Miſeri's, when Coyne growes ſcant,</l>
                  <l>Mans fortunes Foot-ball, ther's no wot to want,</l>
                  <l>It dulls brave witts, when nothing elſe can doe it;</l>
                  <l>Tames, &amp; makes deſp'rate, when Tyme brings men to it.</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:102470:22"/>
                  <l>Want makes a man turne ſlave, unto a ſlave,</l>
                  <l>Scof't, ſcorn'd, and flouted at by ev'ry knave,</l>
                  <l>By ev'ry ſilken ſodden-headed Foole,</l>
                  <l>That never felt Heav'ns rod, nor Mis'ries ſchoole.</l>
                  <l>Want breatheth miſcheifs never thought upon,</l>
                  <l>Makes too many dainty Dames turne wanton.</l>
                  <l>Want (like a Mad-man) makes men ſweare and dice,</l>
                  <l>Forget their God, turne Vertue into Vice.</l>
                  <l>Husband and wife, the ſiſter, and the Brother,</l>
                  <l>Compell'd through want, devoure one another.</l>
                  <l>Merchants, Lawyers, yea, ſome Divines will fall,</l>
                  <l>When want doth ſoundly gripe, 'twill trie 'em all.</l>
                  <l>And therefore (as an Antidote) be ſure,</l>
                  <l>Strive to pleaſe God firſt; that's the onely cure</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt Wolviſh want; then let thy preſent ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Thinke on ſome honeſt meanes; 'twill new create</l>
                  <l>Thy underſtanding; put thee on away</l>
                  <l>With rev'rent Soule, on bended knees each day</l>
                  <l>To ſerve thy God aright; ſo he from falling</l>
                  <l>Proves thy Protector; gives thee a Vertuous calling.</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:102470:22"/>
                  <l>Heav'n grant, the honeſt mind may never knowe</l>
                  <l>The fierce aſſaults of wants; that hell of woe,</l>
                  <l>Torture of minde, murd'rer of modeſtie,</l>
                  <l>High-way to Theft, Cut-throate of chaſtitie,</l>
                  <l>The key of whoredome, Bane of that true love,</l>
                  <l>Which many boaſt; but few did ever prove.</l>
                  <l>Many vow Love, for ever to be true,</l>
                  <l>Yet, when want comes, whores are not more untrue,</l>
                  <l>How ſweetly did that <hi>Sacred Pſalmiſt</hi> ſing,</l>
                  <l>And runne <hi>Times</hi> true Diviſion on the ſtring</l>
                  <l>Of Miſery, when he of God did crave</l>
                  <l>Nor want, nor too much wealth, leaſt in the Grave</l>
                  <l>Of damn'd <hi>Deſpaire,</hi> much want might hale him in,</l>
                  <l>And riches mount him to the higheſt ſinne;</l>
                  <l>Lackey his way to lewdneſſe, to miſtruſt</l>
                  <l>Gods mercies; and to practiſe waies unjuſt,</l>
                  <l>A holy feare, ſeiz'd on that Sacred King</l>
                  <l>To dread wants dangrous Dart, proud riches ſting.</l>
                  <l>May the good Man, ſtill thirſt for mercies Cup,</l>
                  <l>Clymbe <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſacred <hi>Ladder,</hi> and mount up</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:102470:23"/>
                  <l>Into a fiery Chariot, burning zeale,</l>
                  <l>Live a bright Angell, in Heav'ns common-weale,</l>
                  <l>Free from this world, whoſe pompe and bravery,</l>
                  <l>Is but a Land of Dirt, meere ſlavery.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mundus domus ampla malorum, Ac ſcelerum Patria eſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:23"/>
               <head>THE FLESH.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Fleſh unto the Soul's a bitter Pill,</l>
                  <l>Sweet gilded poyſon, Candide o're to kill,</l>
                  <l>Hurrid, Caroacht in Pride, with glitt'ring ſhowe</l>
                  <l>Of ſwelling pompe, whoſe ſweet effect, is woe,</l>
                  <l>Fleſhly delights begets much miſery,</l>
                  <l>Makes couples married unadviſedly,</l>
                  <l>Thinking Love tittle tattles, can feede their wiſhes,</l>
                  <l>Love ſoone growes cold, where there is empty diſhes.</l>
                  <l>Of all the ſinnes that are, when nothing can</l>
                  <l>Ruine the ſoule; the Fleſh prevailes with man.</l>
                  <l>Mans eyes no ſooner on devotion waite,</l>
                  <l>But in ſteps Carnall concupiſcence ſtraight,</l>
                  <l>Shee's at his Elbow ſtill, to itch him on,</l>
                  <l>Th'unhappie path to his confuſion.</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:102470:24"/>
                  <l>Chaſt Wives are Saints, women that wantonize,</l>
                  <l>Witches, all poyſon, hell is in their eyes,</l>
                  <l>In which, as in a wilderneſſe of woe,</l>
                  <l>In ſtriving to get out, on mad men goe,</l>
                  <l>Starke mad, paſt ſenſe, ſpight of all bookes &amp; Schooles</l>
                  <l>Ruine their Fortunes; prove the ſlaves to Fooles</l>
                  <l>For an alluring minutes trifling joy</l>
                  <l>Inſatiate Licoriſh longing, a meere toy,</l>
                  <l>The fleſh (falſe Traytor like) ſtrives to betray</l>
                  <l>The ſoule to Hell, as Heav'ns juſt caſt-away.</l>
                  <l>Fleſhly delight in Man, feares want of breath</l>
                  <l>More then his God; ſinne, or Eternall death.</l>
                  <l>When juſt Plagues come, then ſin-ſicke ſots can tremble,</l>
                  <l>Make knowne to all the world, how they diſſemble;</l>
                  <l>Pray with the Lip, (not heart) wreſt ſacred Text</l>
                  <l>To ſerve their owne ends firſt; and then Gods next,</l>
                  <l>Provide to live, in peſtilent Times beginne,</l>
                  <l>Take greater care to fly from death, then ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Ther's nothing in our Fleſh but wickedneſſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to live, and obſcene wantonneſſe.</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:102470:24"/>
                  <l>O vaine deſire of mortalls, can there be</l>
                  <l>In flight or Phyſick crue 'gainſt heav'ns decree?</l>
                  <l>No, no, ther's no eſcape; no way to this:</l>
                  <l>Mans good life onely, meets with mercies kiſſe.</l>
                  <l>We forget now that dreadfull diſmall chance,</l>
                  <l>The terrible Arrow of Gods vengeance,</l>
                  <l>When death buried farre more, then the earth could ſwallow,</l>
                  <l>And no man to the Grave his friend durſt follow.</l>
                  <l>O why ſhould Mortalls wiſh long life to live?</l>
                  <l>What comfort? what true joy do's this live give?</l>
                  <l>Ther's nothing, not one thought that do's us good,</l>
                  <l>But it is ſtrangl'd ſtraight, by fleſh and blood.</l>
                  <l>Holy Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> finding the fleſhrebell,</l>
                  <l>Deſir'd to be diſſolv'd, proud fleſh to quell:</l>
                  <l>And Sacred <hi>Symeon</hi> ſung 'gainſt ſinnes increaſe;</l>
                  <l>Lord let thy ſervant now depart in peace.</l>
                  <l>Shall ſuch ſoule ſweenting preparations be</l>
                  <l>Forgotten quite; O blind ſecuritie,</l>
                  <l>What is it, we behold in this vaine life?</l>
                  <l>But daily dangers, ſoule-bewitching ſtrife,</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:102470:25"/>
                  <l>The Fleſh is full of dagger; (never quiet)</l>
                  <l>'Mong fullfed diſhes, and Luxurious diet,</l>
                  <l>When my Soule-Erring Eyes, ſtaring behold</l>
                  <l>A dang'rous ſtrumpet, flame in glittering gold</l>
                  <l>(And murd'ring beauty; ſparkling from her Eye</l>
                  <l>Burning temptation;) then, me thinkes I ſpie</l>
                  <l>My moſt apparent miſchiefe, plainely ſee,</l>
                  <l>How I ne'r ſtrive to pleaſe my God, as ſhee</l>
                  <l>Strives to pleaſe men; ſuch is the flaming pride</l>
                  <l>Of the vaine fleſh, it hurts on ev'ry ſide.</l>
                  <l>Ther's nothing conſtant in us, if to day</l>
                  <l>Vertue we love, to morrow Vice obey.</l>
                  <l>What a notorious Coxcombe unto ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Luſt makes of Man, ſlave to a whores ſoft skinne.</l>
                  <l>What's a delicious Harlot? but a cheater,</l>
                  <l>A poyſon'd <hi>Marmalad Box,</hi> that rots the earer,</l>
                  <l>A Harlot, Man moſt fitly may compare</l>
                  <l>To Quickſilver; whoſe Mertall (like aſnare)</l>
                  <l>When er'e it meets with gold, does evermore</l>
                  <l>Mlingle it ſelfe; ſo commonly a whore.</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:102470:25"/>
                  <l>'Tis not the Man, but money ſhe reſpects,</l>
                  <l>And mingling with the one, ſhe both infects,</l>
                  <l>Drinks deepe in Taverns, Swaggers, Sweares, and raves,</l>
                  <l>Gets gold from fooles, to ſpend it upon knaves.</l>
                  <l>The cheife praiſe of a good wiſe do's not lie</l>
                  <l>In outward ſhew; but inward pietie:</l>
                  <l>If Vertue rules her bloud, ſhe merits love,</l>
                  <l>If not, I will aſſure thee ſhee will prove</l>
                  <l>Like a deceitfull glaſſe; where man may ſee,</l>
                  <l>Hee's meerly cheated in her; O miſerie,</l>
                  <l>Man makes lewd women proud with looking at,</l>
                  <l>And wondrous wanton to, beleeve that.</l>
                  <l>The onely cure, Luſt's raging flames to quench</l>
                  <l>Is <hi>Aqua Lachrymarum;</hi> that will ſtench</l>
                  <l>The wounds proud women ſo delight to make</l>
                  <l>On the poore ſoule of Man; make him to quake,</l>
                  <l>Afear'd to ſtand on that falſe rocke of Ice</l>
                  <l>Idleneſſe feeder of foule carnall Vice,</l>
                  <l>Nurſe of blacke thoughts, ſouth-Fogg, which rots the minde</l>
                  <l>Leapours the ſoule, and is the Northerne winde</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:102470:26"/>
                  <l>The cauſe of all ſinnes ſtormes; that dang'rous flood</l>
                  <l>Luſts ſurging Ocean ſwelling in Mans blood.</l>
                  <l>O Devill deſire of Luſt, me, me forſake,</l>
                  <l>I charge thee hence, by him that made hell quake,</l>
                  <l>By that Almighty One, in ſacred Trine,</l>
                  <l>All holy ſpells, and Charmes, Magick Divine;</l>
                  <l>By that ſweet Excellent Sacred Puritie</l>
                  <l>(Siſter of Angells) Virgin Chaſtity,</l>
                  <l>Fly from me all baſe thoughts, be juſt mine eyes,</l>
                  <l>And be your ſelves; hate wantons Witcheries.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Impendet periculum omnibus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:26"/>
               <head>THE IESVITE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOt like that Maſſe-Prieſt, he whoſe mouth is cram'd</l>
                  <l>With words that ſpeake all Proteſtants are damn'd.</l>
                  <l>Him nor his ſlocke, I dare not cenſure ſo,</l>
                  <l>Nor meane to write more then I juſtly know</l>
                  <l>To be moſt true; in which knowne Path I finde,</l>
                  <l>Counterfeit Catholiques, ſo groſſely blinde,</l>
                  <l>They dare outface Heav'ns <hi>Truth,</hi> forg'd lies maintaine</l>
                  <l>To Cloake the cunning <hi>Ieſuites</hi> ſubtile Braine,</l>
                  <l>He that do's Theefe-like waite for <hi>vertues</hi> fall,</l>
                  <l>Lives in perpetuall watch, to blow up all.</l>
                  <l>The Preſident, recorded ſtands for ever,</l>
                  <l>In this Realmes ſafety; which hell's Plot can never</l>
                  <l>Wipe from Rememb'rance; never ſhall the Evill</l>
                  <l>Of that cloſe <hi>Secretary,</hi> to the <hi>Devill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:102470:27"/>
                  <l>That <hi>Ieſuite Garnet,</hi> live forgot while I,</l>
                  <l>Have <hi>Pen,</hi> or <hi>Hand,</hi> to write his Tragedy,</l>
                  <l>(That <hi>Myne of Murther,</hi> Miſchiefes Maſter-vice,</l>
                  <l>Lodg'd in the Politicque skull of Avarice)</l>
                  <l>His deſp'rate Soule was ſuch, he durſt to ſwimme,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Vice,</hi> be rackt in ev'ry limme.</l>
                  <l>All tortures ſuffer, rather then reveale</l>
                  <l>The Treaſon, his Religion bids conceale.</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe thou <hi>Ghoſt</hi> of <hi>Garnet,</hi> this is true,</l>
                  <l>He that han'gd, drawne, and quarter'd, had his due.</l>
                  <l>To him was knowne, the powder pitchie Treaſon,</l>
                  <l>Never to be forgot, he knew the ſeaſon</l>
                  <l>When, where, and how, that ſuddaine bloudie blow,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(Black, Hell-bread, Thunder, flaming, overthrow,)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Should have beene given, knew the Times ſhort ſpace,</l>
                  <l>When no ſoule ſhould have time to pray for Grace,</l>
                  <l>Or cry, God helpe; The Treaſon was ſo foule,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Traitors</hi> would have damn'd both body and Soule</l>
                  <l>If in their power: and ev'ry ſoule i'th Ayre</l>
                  <l>Toſt up, ſent unprepar'd of heav'nly prayer,</l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:102470:27"/>
                  <l>With all their ſinnes; O horrid, horrid Act,</l>
                  <l>All this the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> knew; conceal'd the fact,</l>
                  <l>And rather then diſcloſe, leaſt warning give,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>King, Prince,</hi> and <hi>Nobles,</hi> not a ſoule ſhould liue,</l>
                  <l>Here was a Villaine; yet I've knowne in <hi>Spayne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Traitors</hi> death ſo moan'd, ſuch Credit gaine,</l>
                  <l>(Though here he dyde, for Treaſons juſt complaint)</l>
                  <l>There Monſter <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> make a Martyr'd Saint.</l>
                  <l>Miſchievous Maſſe-Prieſts to his meriting fame,</l>
                  <l>At the high Altar in a ſpacious frame,</l>
                  <l>Advance to him, as to a Saint moſt bleſt,</l>
                  <l>His Body-mangled Picture, thus expreſt: <hi>Garnets</hi> Picture.</l>
                  <l>Bare Head, white Beard, Lookes ſober, in his Gowne,</l>
                  <l>"Him over head, Angels with <hi>Laurell</hi> Crowne.</l>
                  <l>"About his Neck, a long large Haltertide,</l>
                  <l>"Hangs, (as befitting ſuch) downe the Left ſide.</l>
                  <l>"His Belly ript, bloud ſeeming open ſtraw,</l>
                  <l>"Holding in his righ hand, his pictur'd draw.</l>
                  <l>"Beneath his right ſide, flames a Heart in fire,</l>
                  <l>"Bove his left, Limmes quarter'd, Treaſons hire,</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:102470:28"/>
                  <l>"Preſented on a Tower; which Pictur'd ſtorie,</l>
                  <l>Straw-fainted ſet up to'th <hi>Arch-Traitors Glory,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Invites each eye, yea all the world to ſee</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ieſuites, Protectors</hi> of all Villany.</l>
                  <l>"Poys'ning of Princes, held as trifling things,</l>
                  <l>"With them, 'tis meritorious to kill Kings.</l>
                  <l>Can this Religion be, they thinke it pure,</l>
                  <l>But man ne'r knew Religion more impure,</l>
                  <l>Their Church, is but their <hi>Cloake,</hi> bad deeds to further,</l>
                  <l>The only ſanctuary for bloud and murther.</l>
                  <l>Plots, Practizes, helliſh abomination,</l>
                  <l>Pardons for Treaſon, holy approbation</l>
                  <l>Of that ill-Sainted wretch (his curſed fault)</l>
                  <l>That Father to <hi>Faux,</hi> the Divill i'th vault.</l>
                  <l>Such <hi>Iudas-Ieſuites</hi> ever Traitors prove</l>
                  <l>To King, and Prince; diſloyall in their love.</l>
                  <l>"Yet outward fawning ſeeme on bended knee</l>
                  <l>"Low as the earth; O true hypocriſie,</l>
                  <l>"Vnder the mild aſpect of Reverence,</l>
                  <l>"In duty, and ſubmiſſe obedience,</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:102470:28"/>
                  <l>"With Oylie Eloquence, beſt pleaſing Phraſe,</l>
                  <l>"Catching Orations, full of flatt'ring praiſe,</l>
                  <l>"When in the heart abides no ſpot of good,</l>
                  <l>"All treach'rous thoughts; all thirſting after bloud,</l>
                  <l>"The fall of Princes, changes, alteration,</l>
                  <l>"The Proteſtants Religion's deſolation,</l>
                  <l>"Such is the Ieſuites dive'liſh diſpoſition,</l>
                  <l>"The nature of the Beaſt, his true condition,</l>
                  <l>"He that can temporize, by booke maintaine</l>
                  <l>"To ſerve his ends; and glut his God-leſſe gaine.</l>
                  <l>"Be what he leaſt ſeemes, cold in devotion,</l>
                  <l>Envious, at one anothers Promotion,</l>
                  <l>"Not lowly minded, but proud Ambitious,</l>
                  <l>"In tongue a Saint, in heart a ſlave vicious.</l>
                  <l>"Preach divine patience, when himſelfe ſhall be,</l>
                  <l>"The waſpiſh Image of all Tyrannie.</l>
                  <l>"Spleenative, choll'ricke, and who ſo offends,</l>
                  <l>"Is ſo farre off from ever being friends,</l>
                  <l>All-bee't he ſeeme a Calme, yet if he live,</l>
                  <l>Hee'll be reveng'd, be ſure ne'r to forgive,</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:102470:29"/>
                  <l>Such is the Ieſuite, ſuch his double Face,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch his charitable ſigne of Grace.</l>
                  <l>He that dares awe his Countrey, King and State,</l>
                  <l>Smile, and yet be a villaine, all men hate,</l>
                  <l>Set Princes at debate, befoole the times,</l>
                  <l>Poyſon the world, with irreligious Crymes,</l>
                  <l>Swell Battles, Murthers, make whole Kingdomes ſhake,</l>
                  <l>Shed Innocent bloud, all for Religions ſake,</l>
                  <l>To defend Religion, what Religion's this,</l>
                  <l>To ſeeme devoute, and doe ſo much amiſſe?</l>
                  <l>"Colour Religion, with meere gullerie,</l>
                  <l>"Wreſt ſacred Text, to maintaine Roguerie,</l>
                  <l>"(As if Religion were a formall Law,</l>
                  <l>"Religion onely to keepe fooles in awe,)</l>
                  <l>Defend Controverſies; woe to thoſe dayes,</l>
                  <l>Woe to ſuch Serpent-ſnarling Church-Mens wayes,</l>
                  <l>"Sinne ne'r triumphes, ſtrikes a more fatall ſtroake,</l>
                  <l>"Then when 'tis cove'rd with Religions Cloake.</l>
                  <l>That Ieſuite, he, who ſpeakes divinely faire,</l>
                  <l>Yet hath a wicked life; I may compare</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:102470:29"/>
                  <l>To fire, ſtand off, doe not come too neare it,</l>
                  <l>You then may ſafely warme; neede not feare it.</l>
                  <l>But if thou unadviſedly preſume,</l>
                  <l>Approach too nigh, thee it will burne, conſume,</l>
                  <l>So the deceitfull Prieſt, come not neare him,</l>
                  <l>Shun his acquaintance, you neede not feare him.</l>
                  <l>Flie his diſſembling ſight, his blacke life ſpurne,</l>
                  <l>If lodg'd within your boſome, he will burne,</l>
                  <l>With ſhew of holineſſe burne and ſcorch,</l>
                  <l>Waſte thee, in thy Eſtate, like a ſpent Tortch.</l>
                  <l>Ther's not a Gentleman of meanes do's die,</l>
                  <l>But with his Heire, the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> preſently</l>
                  <l>Shares in his land; with ſhew of Reverence,</l>
                  <l>(Winning of Soules) covers concupiſcence.</l>
                  <l>Commits with all he like, any Mans wife,</l>
                  <l>Makes her beleeve, 'tis to preſerve his life.</l>
                  <l>Perſwading Letch'rie, with their Ghoſtly Father,</l>
                  <l>No ſinne, but a deede of charity rather.</l>
                  <l>Sad-ſickneſſe to prevent, to ſcowre the veines,</l>
                  <l>To mundifie, and for to purge the Reines.</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:102470:30"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ergo plena Charitatis;</hi> An Act</l>
                  <l>Of meere Commiſeration, ſuch a Fact,</l>
                  <l>As to denie it, (were a damned ſinne)</l>
                  <l>Pulls curſe on curſe, which hath for ever binne</l>
                  <l>Iuſtly inflicted; puniſhing all thoſe</l>
                  <l>Repugnant Natures, with the worſt of woes,</l>
                  <l>Diſpaire, aſſur'd confuſion, diſmall horrour,</l>
                  <l>Sudden deſtruction, Death, infernall terrour,</l>
                  <l>Hell, and the Devill; for that high offence</l>
                  <l>Of Stubborne refuſall, diſobedience,</l>
                  <l>A ſinne, impoſſible to be forgiv'n,</l>
                  <l>Such is the Ieſuites charge; of purpoſe giv'n,</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe his Luſt; makes that, a gainefull trade,</l>
                  <l>Lies with this Lady, and that Chamber-Maide.</l>
                  <l>Here gives a Pardon, there denounceth Curſes,</l>
                  <l>So betwixt both, ſure to picke all their Purſes.</l>
                  <l>The Nimble Slaves Church-knaverie can ſtrip,</l>
                  <l>And fetch your greateſt Lady o're the hip.</l>
                  <l>With a religious ſhow', put tricks upon her,</l>
                  <l>Rob the beleeving Foole, firſt of her honour,</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:102470:30"/>
                  <l>Then pardon Sinne; and then he may enthrall,</l>
                  <l>Rob her of Coyne, Plate, Iewels, Smocke and all,</l>
                  <l>Doe, and undoe, Her Charity's ſoone drawne</l>
                  <l>For baudie Ieſuites, her beſt Smocke to pawne,</l>
                  <l>Their thread of Doctrine'mong women ſpun,</l>
                  <l>Is to whore all, be ſhe the chaſteſt <hi>Nun,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If ſhe denie to yeeld, Murther and Rape,</l>
                  <l>Shall Wolfe-like ſeize that prey, there's no eſcape,</l>
                  <l>Such is the Murd'ring Minde of him we call,</l>
                  <l>Natures Monſter, <hi>Prieſt Ieſuiticall.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noli gloriari quod lingua bene dicis, Si vita male dicis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:31"/>
               <head>THE DEVILL.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SEarch all the <hi>Earth,</hi> you ev'ry where ſhall ſee</l>
                  <l>Satan moſt buſie; from the <hi>Church</hi> not free,</l>
                  <l>The very Pulpit haunts, and being vext,</l>
                  <l>Seekes how to put the Preacher from his Text.</l>
                  <l>Such as teach others, yet themſelves neglect,</l>
                  <l>And with ſinnes Caſſocke, hide their owne defect;</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Pew,</hi> to <hi>Pew,</hi> unſeene; <hi>Hell's Fiend</hi> do's creepe,</l>
                  <l>To dull the Hearers Eares, Ioggs ſome aſleepe,</l>
                  <l>Some to vaine prattle, others ſtill to prie,</l>
                  <l>With wanton lookes, for a bewitching Eye,</l>
                  <l>Some greedily imployes, to ſpie out faſhions,</l>
                  <l>To glut the humours of proud womens paſſions,</l>
                  <l>Makes muddie <hi>Mortalls,</hi> at each other looke,</l>
                  <l>More then on <hi>Heav'n,</hi> or Gods all Sacred Booke.</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:102470:32"/>
                  <l>And ſuch is <hi>Satans</hi> craft, continuall motion,</l>
                  <l>To draw mankind from <hi>heav'n,</hi> and all devotion.</l>
                  <l>Tempts ſome to <hi>Hate, Ambition,</hi> ſome to ſlide</l>
                  <l>The ſliprie ſleights of <hi>Pompe,</hi> unpai'd for pride.</l>
                  <l>Others to ſwimme the <hi>Sea,</hi> Luſt pleaſing vice</l>
                  <l>Some wet damnation, moſt men Avarice</l>
                  <l>Servants to <hi>Satan; Satan</hi> which do's ſtrive,</l>
                  <l>Man of all heav'nly ſolace to deprive.</l>
                  <l>God (for our ſinnes) no ſooner ang'ry growes,</l>
                  <l>But ſtraight the roaring, ſudden Devill throwes</l>
                  <l>His Pawes on us; and like himſelfe beginnes</l>
                  <l>(For numbers numberleſſe of deſperate ſinnes)</l>
                  <l>To ſeize the ſoule, made an eternall prey,</l>
                  <l>To burne in Hell; as Heav'ns juſt caſt away:</l>
                  <l>Such is the <hi>Fate</hi> of ſoules, enſnar'd within</l>
                  <l>Satans command; beware the Twigge of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt touch will take the Pris'ner; Helliſh guiles</l>
                  <l>Prove like the perilous paths of Crocodiles,</l>
                  <l>Who with their ſlimie tongues (lickt or'c) prepare</l>
                  <l>To murther <hi>Mortals,</hi> by a ſlip'rie ſnare.</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:102470:32"/>
                  <l>Man is a Tree, whoſe root, is certaine evill,</l>
                  <l>Bad deeds the Body, yeelding to the Devill.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Armes,</hi> ten proud aſpiring diſcontents,</l>
                  <l>Breakers of all the ten Commandements.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Branches</hi> are, our proneneſſe unto ill,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Leafes</hi> Pleaſure, the faire fruit <hi>ſinne,</hi> which ſtill</l>
                  <l>With ſweeteſt ſhow of ſweetneſſe tempts us on,</l>
                  <l>To feed and follow our deſtruction.</l>
                  <l>"There is feare above us, feare ſtill beneath us,</l>
                  <l>"Feare round about, and yet no feare within us:</l>
                  <l>Satan like <hi>Dalilah,</hi> ſuffers not men</l>
                  <l>For to ſee danger; is't not fitting then,</l>
                  <l>By holy violence, we ſeize the ſword</l>
                  <l>Of th'<hi>Omnipotents,</hi> Omnipotent word</l>
                  <l>To ſlaughter ſinne in us; O ſhall not we</l>
                  <l>(That profeſſe Sacred Chriſtianitie,)</l>
                  <l>Conquer our crymes; thinke on the life to come,</l>
                  <l>The riſing of the dead; the Day of Doome,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>dreadfull day;</hi> let us then never winke,</l>
                  <l>At our baſe follies; never forget to thinke:</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:102470:33"/>
                  <l>When this vaſt <hi>Orbe</hi> of <hi>Earth</hi> ſhall blaſing burne,</l>
                  <l>And all the world in Funerall flames ſhall mourne,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Heav'n</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> amazing muſt appeare</l>
                  <l>In two extremes; Ioy, and exceſſive feare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heav'n,</hi> in bright ſhining <hi>All-Eternall</hi> Light,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hell,</hi> in the Horrour of perpetuall Night.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heav'n</hi> ſhall triumph, <hi>Hell,</hi> tremble, <hi>Angells</hi> ſing,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gloria</hi> in <hi>Excelſis,</hi> to Heav'ns high King;</l>
                  <l>The King of Heav'n; Heav'n joyes perfect ſolace,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All-Raviſhing,</hi> glit'ring gliſt'ring <hi>Palace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pleaſures <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> immortall dwelling,</l>
                  <l>All-pure, excellent, paſt thought excelling.</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns Pavement, are the <hi>Starrs,</hi> in what exceſſe</l>
                  <l>Shines Heav'n, when ſtar-pav'd, with <hi>Starrs</hi> numberleſſe</l>
                  <l>No thought of want, which mads the thoughts of men,</l>
                  <l>But plenties fulneſſe, full abound in Heav'n.</l>
                  <l>"There, <hi>Virgin Chaſtity</hi> in life oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>"Glitters in Saint-like Glory, lives moſt bleſt.</l>
                  <l>"The poore <hi>Man</hi> toſt from wrong, to injurie,</l>
                  <l>"In <hi>Heav'n</hi> finds comfort, firme felicitie,</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:102470:33"/>
                  <l>"The wronged Widdow, injur'd fatherleſſe,</l>
                  <l>"Bright Heav'n relieves, gives all their woes redreſſe.</l>
                  <l>"He, that for ill do's good, <hi>Heav'n</hi> will requite,</l>
                  <l>"Crowne his faire ſoule with comforts infinite.</l>
                  <l>Is it not fit then, we our ſinnes bewaile?</l>
                  <l>Thinke ſtill on Heav'n? on Heav'n that ne'r did faile</l>
                  <l>The penitent ſoule, when (alas) diſtreſt,</l>
                  <l>Naked, forlorne, when moſt of all oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>Then ſends reliefe; miraculous reliefes,</l>
                  <l>Such is the love of Heav'n; Heav'n cures all griefes,</l>
                  <l>As for Tymes Wolfe-turn'd ill-affected great-ones,</l>
                  <l>Cloſe-fiſted to the poore, deafe to their groanes,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Villaines</hi> of this <hi>Age,</hi> that make profeſſion,</l>
                  <l>Of a pure life yet live by baſe oppreſſion,</l>
                  <l>Hell ſhall confound their ſoules, that Den of Horrour</l>
                  <l>(Circl'd with blacke affright, blew-burning terrour)</l>
                  <l>Shall boyle their ſoules, and bodies to th'black-ſweat</l>
                  <l>Of an infernall poyſon; and that eate</l>
                  <l>Still to renue new paines; plagues that excell,</l>
                  <l>Such are the never-dying paines of hell.</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:102470:34"/>
                  <l>There, painted <hi>Pride</hi> lives crown'd in flaming fire,</l>
                  <l>Tymes <hi>glorious ſtrumpet,</hi> whipt with burning wiere,</l>
                  <l>Fed is the Luſt-provoking Letcher there,</l>
                  <l>With ſcorching coales; ſuch as delight to ſweare,</l>
                  <l>Swallow the <hi>Drunkards</hi> ever ſcalding oyle,</l>
                  <l>There, <hi>Vſuters,</hi> in Pooles of ſulphure boyle,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Murther, Rape, Inceſt,</hi> endleſſe torments feele,</l>
                  <l>The Rack of vengeance, and the burning wheele</l>
                  <l>Whirl'd round in blew flames; ſoule-amazing feare,</l>
                  <l>"More thignes then tongue can tell, the damned beare.</l>
                  <l>In burning beds of ſteele, ſoules blazing fry,</l>
                  <l>Tortur'd with torments, ſuch as never dye;</l>
                  <l>Curſing the Time of their abus'd Creation,</l>
                  <l>Parents, Fate, ſinne, and their owne damnation.</l>
                  <l>Better, O better never to be borne,</l>
                  <l>Then with ſuch Terrour-ſtriking torments torne.</l>
                  <l>Which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, weepe wormes of Earth, repent,</l>
                  <l>Weepe, weepe for ſinne, ſoule-killing ſinnes prevent.</l>
                  <l>"Seeke heav'n, ſhun Hell, fly from the worlds intice,</l>
                  <l>"Heav'ns the reward of <hi>Vertue,</hi> Hell of Vice.</l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:102470:34"/>
                  <l>"Perfect repentance makes men bravely die</l>
                  <l>"That liv'd not ſo; fly then <hi>Hell's</hi> miſerie.</l>
                  <l>"Repent, or damne, for ſinne, weepe and weepe well,</l>
                  <l>"Soules that doe flout at teares, ſhall fry in hell.</l>
                  <l>"The Devill ſets his baits in ev'ry Angle,</l>
                  <l>"No Corner's free from him, ſoules to entangle.</l>
                  <l>"Therefore in <hi>Vertues Path,</hi> ſtrive to excell:</l>
                  <l>"Let firme faith ſtill repulſe the Fiend of hell.</l>
                  <l>Divines may preach elſe, till their heart-ſtrings burſt,</l>
                  <l>The height of ſinne will mount, live ſtill accurſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vbi peccatum, ibi Procella.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:35"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:35"/>
               <head>Mans Miſerie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MAns life is like a Watch, whoſe Time if ſtill</l>
                  <l>It Minnits right, diſtemper'd by no ill,</l>
                  <l>It is a rare Peece then; but oft we ſee,</l>
                  <l>It runnes too faſt; in <hi>Action</hi> tis too free.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes, by wilfull providence ſet backe,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes, by dull neglect it goes too ſlacke,</l>
                  <l>Beates like a dying panting pulſe ſo ſlow,</l>
                  <l>That by and by it ſtands; and then we know</l>
                  <l>Tis downe, ſome curious wheele is much amiſſe,</l>
                  <l>Or ſome ſprynge broke, whereby the whole frame is</l>
                  <l>So farre paſtrectifying, that it can</l>
                  <l>Never goe right; but like diſorder'd Man,</l>
                  <l>Miſ-ſpending pretious time in godleſſe riot,</l>
                  <l>Time barrs of <hi>Heav'n, Angells</hi> immortall dyet.</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:102470:36"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Youth</hi> is a hot, unbridled, willfull folly,</l>
                  <l>Picke me out one that's Vertuous, truly holy</l>
                  <l>In this abuſed life; and you ſhall finde,</l>
                  <l>Infinite thouſands of a <hi>Vicious</hi> minde.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Age</hi> Palſey-ſtrucke ready for deaths darke grave,</l>
                  <l>Inſenſible of ſinne, it all would have</l>
                  <l>That ſhew of profit brings; though ill got gaine,</l>
                  <l>And threatning heaven in thunder ſpeake, refraine</l>
                  <l>Bad precepts; t'will not do; Truth tells us ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Age proves Youth's ſcorne, through examples ill.</l>
                  <l>Vice leades the ſilver yeares to endleſſe blame,</l>
                  <l>Vaine unſtay'd youth to beggery, and ſhame.</l>
                  <l>'Tis Heav'ns juſt puniſhment; an ill lewd life,</l>
                  <l>In Young and old, meets with eternall ſtrife.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thinke</hi> then on thy <hi>Creatour</hi> wretched man,</l>
                  <l>Remember what thou art, thy life a ſpan,</l>
                  <l>A weake thinne thread, ſpun from the downy wooll</l>
                  <l>Of tender <hi>children,</hi> to the Aged skull.</l>
                  <l>From youths rich Scarlet die, Beauties full force,</l>
                  <l>To the ſilver Tinſell ſnow, of a cold Courſe.</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:102470:36"/>
                  <l>Man is an <hi>Actor,</hi> and the world the <hi>Stage,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where ſome doe laugh, ſome weepe, ſome ſing, ſome rage</l>
                  <l>All in their <hi>Parts,</hi> during the <hi>Stene</hi> of breath,</l>
                  <l>Act follies, ſcourg'd by the <hi>Tragodian</hi> death:</l>
                  <l>Such is the <hi>Fate</hi> of ſoules, enſnar'd within</l>
                  <l>Satans command; beware the twigg of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt touch will take thee <hi>Pris'ner;</hi> Helliſh guiles,</l>
                  <l>Prove like the perilous paths of Crocodiles,</l>
                  <l>That with a ſlimie Tongue lick't o're prepares</l>
                  <l>To murther Mortalls; ſuch is Satans ſnare.</l>
                  <l>O why ſhould Mortalls wiſh long life to live,</l>
                  <l>What comfort? what true joy do's this life give?</l>
                  <l>Ther's nothing, not one thought that do's us good,</l>
                  <l>But it is ſtrangl'd ſtraight by fleſh and blood.</l>
                  <l>The longer life, the more we ſinne, and fall</l>
                  <l>From bad to worſe, from worſe, to worſt of all.</l>
                  <l>"Life loving fortunes, how ye puffe men up,</l>
                  <l>"To hugg their follie, drinke damnations Cup!</l>
                  <l>O that men were farre wiſer, would but thinke,</l>
                  <l>How ſwell'd with pride, they deſperately wincke</l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:102470:37"/>
                  <l>At their owne venom <hi>Vices;</hi> and yet ſtorme</l>
                  <l>At others faults; good heav'n this ſinnereturne,</l>
                  <l>Or we ſhall periſh; praying for our foes</l>
                  <l>Is of ſmall uſe; this cauſes all our woes.</l>
                  <l>Rejoyce at no mans fall (with foule aſperſion)</l>
                  <l>Although thy foe; but pray for his converſion,</l>
                  <l>So piety wills; ſtill imitate the beſt,</l>
                  <l>Not worſt of men; he that lives well, dies bleſt.</l>
                  <l>Obſerve, what Holy Rritprompts thee to act,</l>
                  <l>"Pray for thy foes, 'tis a moſt pious fact,</l>
                  <l>If then thine enemie perſiſt in ire,</l>
                  <l>"Heav'n on his head in flames, heapes coales of fire:</l>
                  <l>The cauſe, that on our heads juſt vengance drawes,</l>
                  <l>Springs from our ſelves; we breake Gods ſacred Lawes,</l>
                  <l>Yet never minde it; complaints and daily cryes</l>
                  <l>Are much among us ſtill, but no weteyes</l>
                  <l>For crying ſinnes; daggers of diſcontent</l>
                  <l>Stab home, where careleſſe people ne'r repent.</l>
                  <l>Nothing more dang'rous, nor hath ever been,</l>
                  <l>Then to live ſtill, i'th' Lethargie of ſinne,</l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:102470:37"/>
                  <l>The clouded fight permits us not to Eie</l>
                  <l>Our owne foule faults; nor the Flint heart to ſpie</l>
                  <l>It's rockie ſubſtance; many have no ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>No feeling of their ſinnes large conſcience,</l>
                  <l>Remove the cauſe betimes; let thou, and I,</l>
                  <l>Ev'ry one ſtrive, offend not with thine eye.</l>
                  <l>"Fly from the tongues abuſe, thy hard hearts terrour,</l>
                  <l>"Or live ſinnes Slave, loſt in a miſt of errour.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:38"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:38"/>
               <head>Sinnes Jnfirmitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Sinne of <hi>Mans</hi> infirmitie is knowne</l>
                  <l>Beſt by the conſequence, (ſad ſorrowes groane.)</l>
                  <l>It leaves behind it ſuch a ſting within</l>
                  <l>The Soule; that miſerable <hi>Man</hi> for ſinne</l>
                  <l>(Snar'd with temptations in this worlds wide Hall)</l>
                  <l>Can never be at reſt; but grieve and fall</l>
                  <l>Out to the <hi>Death</hi> with his abhord condition,</l>
                  <l>The guilt of Conſcience; and the baſe fruition</l>
                  <l>Of his beſotted ſence; he takes no pleaſure</l>
                  <l>In the worlds wealth; weighing Gods deepe diſpleaſure</l>
                  <l>Still againſt ſinne; he never is at quiet,</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Home, abroad,</hi> in <hi>bed,</hi> or at his <hi>diet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There is no health in's fleſh, no reſt in's bones,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sinne</hi> ſtifles ſence, all mirth converts to moanes.</l>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:102470:39"/>
                  <l>Each comfort proves diſconſolate within</l>
                  <l>That ſoule, which really is griev'd for ſinne.</l>
                  <l>Deepe ſwelling ſighes, like breaking <hi>Seas</hi> diſcover</l>
                  <l>Heart breaking groanes; one griefe upon another.</l>
                  <l>Sinne like inceſſant ſtormes beats on the breaſt</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Mans</hi> afflicted ſoule, never at reſt,</l>
                  <l>'Till he has made his peace with Heav'n, by ſo und</l>
                  <l>And ſerious humble reconcilement drownd</l>
                  <l>In ſtreaming teares; ſuch teares, as beſt expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>For ſinnes infirme; a heart in bitterneſſe.</l>
                  <l>Learne thou this <hi>Leſson,</hi> thou whoſe clouded eyes,</l>
                  <l>Hides thee from ſight of thy infirmities,</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Pride,</hi> oppreſſion, <hi>luſt</hi>-provoking diet,</l>
                  <l>Naſtie defilements, drunken belching riot,</l>
                  <l>Which ſo beſweats, ſots, and beſpots the ſoule,</l>
                  <l>As renders it moſt loathſome, uggly foule</l>
                  <l>To the Eyes of the <hi>All-pure-God;</hi> He ſpies</l>
                  <l>All our baſe thoughts, each darke deed, all thoſe lies</l>
                  <l>The Divell blinds us with, to our abuſe;</l>
                  <l>Vnder the feign'd pretence of an excuſe;</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:39"/>
               <head>Sinnes Jmpudence.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SInne that was wont in privacy to lurke,</l>
                  <l>Not daring to be ſeene darke deeds to worke,</l>
                  <l>Walk't ſtill in feare; the mind was ne'r at reſt,</l>
                  <l>Like a poore Man in danger of Arreſt.</l>
                  <l>But now in <hi>Triumph</hi> like a Drab of State</l>
                  <l>Branded with impudence; dare walke and prate,</l>
                  <l>Doe deedes of open ſhame; yet never bluſh,</l>
                  <l>Shrinke, feare, nor feele <hi>Revenge</hi> more then a ruſh,</l>
                  <l>Shield us from ſinne, (great God) ſinne that at firſt</l>
                  <l>Poyſon'd the perfect Man; made all accurſt</l>
                  <l>That glorious Image; made him ſee his ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Poore, naked, neede, and loſſe of his good name.</l>
                  <l>What ever ſorrowes on weake man befall,</l>
                  <l>Publique, or private, ſinne is the cauſe of all.</l>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:102470:40"/>
                  <l>Sinne dulls the Soule, when Heav'n is out of ſight,</l>
                  <l>Mans out of <hi>Heart;</hi> all vertues looſe their light,</l>
                  <l>Like a beſieged <hi>Cittie,</hi> ſinne ſurrounds,</l>
                  <l>The medowes of the ſoule, ruines her grounds,</l>
                  <l>Windes like a ſubtile <hi>River</hi> bout the bancks,</l>
                  <l>So Eates into her ſides, as drown's the Ranks</l>
                  <l>Of Muddy-minded Mortalls weake defence,</l>
                  <l>Walls built on <hi>Wood-Piles,</hi> to ten confidence.</l>
                  <l>O the rare Mercy of Almighty God.</l>
                  <l>How it do's daily woe us from the Rod</l>
                  <l>Of his juſt vengeance; yet nor love, nor feare,</l>
                  <l>Not any thing that's good in us appeare.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Prodigall Gull,</hi> uncapable to know</l>
                  <l>The worth of wealth; farre ſooner will beſtow</l>
                  <l>Ten pound upon a Hawke, a Hound, a Whore,</l>
                  <l>Rather then give ten pence, to cloath the poore,</l>
                  <l>"The <hi>Worldly Churle,</hi> whoſe money is his ſlave,</l>
                  <l>"Goes to the Church heares Sermons, ſeemes to have</l>
                  <l>"Divine diſcourſe, <hi>Religion</hi> in his talke,</l>
                  <l>"Devotion, Pitty; yet in life do's walke</l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:102470:40"/>
                  <l>"A full diſſembler; <hi>Machivell</hi> and he,</l>
                  <l>"Remorſeleſſe monſters, dead in Charitle.</l>
                  <l>"Deafe to the poore man's-crie, his want of food,</l>
                  <l>"Vrge Scripture to him, that will doe no good.</l>
                  <l>"The ſpirits of miſcheife in their ſoules reply,</l>
                  <l>"They'l not be forc'd to ſuccour boggery.</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Ioſeph</hi> lie in Chaines, and <hi>Daniel</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>Shall they for thread-bare Charity undoe</l>
                  <l>Their full cramm'd baggs, abate the curious <hi>Pride</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Wife</hi> and <hi>Children;</hi> dimme glorious out<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lide,</l>
                  <l>High hopes; the Worlds applauſe, ſinne-ſick wiſhes,</l>
                  <l>Banquets by <hi>Torch-lights,</hi> and bloud ſtirring diſhes,</l>
                  <l>All, to relieve deſpiſed poverty?</l>
                  <l>Wrong their delights, to pitty penury?</l>
                  <l>No, no; they'l not be taught where, when, and how</l>
                  <l>To give their Almes; the Saint to whom they bow</l>
                  <l>Learnes no ſuch leſſon; he ſo ſlaves the braine</l>
                  <l>With the blacke Text; that for their hell-beed gaine,</l>
                  <l>Worſe then the <hi>Scythian Thiefe,</hi> or barbarous <hi>Turke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They'l cheate <hi>friend, Father;</hi> never doe good worke,</l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:102470:41"/>
                  <l>Vnleſſe to trumpet forth their Almes, much good,</l>
                  <l>When ther's no <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue</hi> in their venome bloud,</l>
                  <l>Yet to the World appeare the ſcourge of evill,</l>
                  <l>A very <hi>Saint</hi> in ſhow, in heart a Devill.</l>
                  <l>A foule diſſembling <hi>Fiend</hi> incarnate,</l>
                  <l>That ſeemes preciſe, thinking the gift of prate,</l>
                  <l>The pratling, pious ſeeming ſhew forſooth</l>
                  <l>Of a pure life, ſhould darken ſacred <hi>Truth.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Good God, divert their eyes from <hi>Hell</hi> below</l>
                  <l>To looke on Heav'n; force their blind eyes to know</l>
                  <l>Sinne for a while may with a <hi>Braſen</hi> face</l>
                  <l>Out-brave poore <hi>Vertue,</hi> flouriſh for a ſpace,</l>
                  <l>Feed hot, and high, ſwimme in the worlds delight,</l>
                  <l>As if <hi>Vice</hi> only, were <hi>beav'ns</hi> Favorite,</l>
                  <l>Befat in folly, curious ſcoffes, that dare</l>
                  <l>Mocke at the wrinckled lookes of honeſt care.</l>
                  <l>Scorne leane <hi>Ribb'd Art,</hi> all griefes which interlace</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Lines</hi> of <hi>ſorrow</hi> writ in <hi>Vertues</hi> face.</l>
                  <l>Sinne may doe this; rais'd on the loftie ſtile,</l>
                  <l>Of Prides preferment for a little while.</l>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:102470:41"/>
                  <l>But if time lend thee yeares for to obſerve,</l>
                  <l>You ſoone ſhall ſee proud ſinne, ready to ſterve,</l>
                  <l>Bluſhing for ſhame, and halting on a crutch</l>
                  <l>Spotted all o're with <hi>Biles;</hi> loathſome to touch:</l>
                  <l>"Sweett ſinnes ſoone fade, vaniſh like lightnings flaſh,</l>
                  <l>"Honors a <hi>Bubble,</hi> Riches deceitfull traſh</l>
                  <l>Circl'd with miſchiefes, glitt'ring wantonneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Dull ſelf-eſecured Eaſe, brittle greatneſſe:</l>
                  <l>Which like the ſerpent <hi>Dipſas</hi> quentchleſſe thirſt,</l>
                  <l>Lives never ſatisfied, untill it burſt.</l>
                  <l>"Much wealth, ſmall witt, and farre leſſe honeſty,</l>
                  <l>"Preferres the <hi>golden Aſse</hi> to dignity.</l>
                  <l>Be wiſe as <hi>Cato,</hi> juſt as <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nlius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Valiant as <hi>Scipio,</hi> Chaſt as <hi>Curius;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"Wiſedome in ragges is ſpurn'd at like a ruſh,</l>
                  <l>"Folly gaines Credit, crept but into Pluſh.</l>
                  <l>Be what thou wilt, wealth formes formality,</l>
                  <l>Though ſpung'd with never a one good quality.</l>
                  <l>Worldlings applaud the Rich, the poore deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>Speake never ſo well, ſo excellently wiſe,</l>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:102470:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102470:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:102470:43"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:102470:43"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:102470:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:102470:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:102470:45"/>
                  <l>Beſt knowledge muſt be dumbe; Wiſedomes beſt Note,</l>
                  <l>Yeelds but harſh <hi>Muſicke</hi> in a <hi>Thread-bare</hi> Coate.</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe Times poore <hi>Philoſophers</hi> report;</l>
                  <l>Who being in the <hi>Preſence</hi> at the Court,</l>
                  <l>Was for his ſimple weeds of ſlight regard</l>
                  <l>Rudely thruſt out by the grim-looking Guard;</l>
                  <l>But ſhifting cloathes, admitted to the Eye</l>
                  <l>Of State, the King, before whoſe Majeſtie,</l>
                  <l>He not the leaſt of Reverence would beare,</l>
                  <l>Save <hi>Cap</hi> and <hi>Knee,</hi> toth' cloathes himſelfe did weare,</l>
                  <l>Saying, I honour him that honours mee,</l>
                  <l>Theſe my gay <hi>Clouts,</hi> which brought me <hi>King</hi> to thee.</l>
                  <l>This to the ſinfull World, may Embleme out,</l>
                  <l>Mortalls vaine worſhipping the Golden Clout</l>
                  <l>Of him, or her, whoſe ſoules uncertaine ſtand</l>
                  <l>(Fixt i'th <hi>imperative moode</hi> of proud command)</l>
                  <l>Ioyes in no other Heaven, but admiration,</l>
                  <l>Till ſenceleſſe they forget their firſt Creation,</l>
                  <l>Honours vaine bubble, Riches deceitfull ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Which ne'r drops penny to the pining poore.</l>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:102470:45"/>
                  <l>Nor ever harbours thought of <hi>Charity</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Wretches,</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t ſterv'd with poverty.</l>
                  <l>While on the adverſe part; (Vertue denide)</l>
                  <l>Vice ſtill is hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g'd; the world's in love with pride.</l>
                  <l>O ſtonie hearted ſinne; on thee to thinke</l>
                  <l>Feare turnes my Paper black; makes pale my Inke.</l>
                  <l>Amazeth ſence, compells my palſey <hi>Pen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Trembling to write the Impiouſneſſe of <hi>Men,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe hate to pitty, muſt to terrour turne,</l>
                  <l>Where teares for ſinne are wanting, ſinne ſhall burne.</l>
                  <l>Tell me ye <hi>Toad-ſwolne</hi> flinty <hi>Pharaohs,</hi> tell?</l>
                  <l>Can temporall joyes, equall tho paines of Hell:</l>
                  <l>Treaſures, and pleaſures, thoſe quicke fading ſtreames,</l>
                  <l>To the poore ſleeping ſoule, are all but dreames.</l>
                  <l>The bodies beauty, momentary joy,</l>
                  <l>Which waking findes, Earths glory but a toy:</l>
                  <l>This for a Maximetake, ſhunne times lewd life,</l>
                  <l>Ceaſe from extreames in ſinne, ſoule-murth'ring ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Abhorre to Studdy ſtate with greater zeale</l>
                  <l>Then zeale to Heav'n or the ſoules Common-weale,</l>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:102470:46"/>
                  <l>Abhorre with ſolemne <hi>Oathes</hi> perjur'd to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>are</l>
                  <l>And racke the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> dreadleſſe of feare,</l>
                  <l>Wounding a freſh (with trembling feare I write)</l>
                  <l>Wonder of <hi>Angels,</hi> that great <hi>God</hi> of light,</l>
                  <l>His wounds with Oathes of wounds, fleſh, bloud and heart</l>
                  <l>(Horrour of darkeneſſe) O blaſpheming heart,</l>
                  <l>Too too much us'd, 'mong godleſſe ſoules, which ſtill</l>
                  <l>Infinite good pay, with infinite ill.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:46"/>
               <head>The Penitent Sinner.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LEt others boaſt their goodneſſe, for my part,</l>
                  <l>Wretch that I am, I have a ſinfull heart,</l>
                  <l>So ti'de and bound, fetter'd and chain'd within,</l>
                  <l>So ſtrong a priſon, ſuch a <hi>Maze</hi> of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>That 'tis as farre unlikely for me worme</l>
                  <l>Ere to winde out, as for to raiſe a ſtorme,</l>
                  <l>Or ſlacke a <hi>Tempeſt;</hi> works of wonder ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Farre from thereach of mortalls weake command.</l>
                  <l>None but the hand of God, his ſpeciall grace,</l>
                  <l>Can pull me forth the dungeon of diſgrace.</l>
                  <l>And ſhall I then, in impious waies uneven,</l>
                  <l>Offend ſo good a God; defend me Heav'n!</l>
                  <l>Ride thou my ſoule upon ſome winged cloud</l>
                  <l>To'th'Haven of heaven; fly to the ſacred ſhroud</l>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:102470:47"/>
                  <l>Of ſempeternall ſafety, fly the ſight</l>
                  <l>Of blaſing beautie; flaring Earths delight,</l>
                  <l>Malicious mindes, miſchievous mans invention,</l>
                  <l>Faire lookes, falſe hearts, ſtampt in a ſoule intention.</l>
                  <l>Take flight my <hi>Soule;</hi> fly from the diſmall Den</l>
                  <l>Of this darke Age; the impiouſneſſe of men,</l>
                  <l>Fly from the pond'rous plummets of blacke <hi>Vice</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which pulls to Hell; helpe <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Paradiſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I ſaint, I die, ſinne loades my ſoule with horrour,</l>
                  <l>The World, the fleſh and Divell, all with terrour</l>
                  <l>Hangs on my fetter'd limbes, Priſoner to care</l>
                  <l>I live ſterv'd, tortur'd, tempted to deſpaire.</l>
                  <l>What ſhall I doe, where, whither ſhall I fly?</l>
                  <l>Here, there, I know not where, lie downe and dye.</l>
                  <l>Vp ſoule to <hi>Heav'n,</hi> there get a glorious Crowne:</l>
                  <l>I am too weake, too vile, ſinne pulls me downe.</l>
                  <l>O my unworthyneſſe, my ſhame, my ſinne,</l>
                  <l>When ſhall I ſhake thee off? when when begin?</l>
                  <l>No? wil't not bee? can I not doe the good</l>
                  <l>I would? muſt I be rul'd by fleſh and blood?</l>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:102470:47"/>
                  <l>Weepe, weepe poore ſoule, diſſolve hard heart of flint,</l>
                  <l>Melt, melt thou ſtony Rock, teares never ſtint,</l>
                  <l>Drop Marble mount, drop to a <hi>Crimſon</hi> flood,</l>
                  <l>Sinke my ſinnes, in ſeas of penitent blood.</l>
                  <l>While others careleſſe of celeſtiall health,</l>
                  <l>Greedie like Hell, hunger for worldly wealth,</l>
                  <l>Preferment, pride, and vainely put their truſt</l>
                  <l>In the forbidden <hi>Pathes</hi> of tempting luſt,</l>
                  <l>In glaſſie glory, ſubtile <hi>Court</hi> behaviour</l>
                  <l>In valour, conqueſt and monarchall favour;</l>
                  <l>Whiles ſoules thus erre, O thou the Lord of light,</l>
                  <l>Make me <hi>Heavens Champion,</hi> vertues favorite.</l>
                  <l>Come folded Armes, and you ſad eyes, ſad heart,</l>
                  <l>Come ſoule oppreſt with ſorrow, play thy part.</l>
                  <l>Haſte to ſome gloomy Grave, there all alone</l>
                  <l>On the greene mantled earth ſigh, ſobbe and groane,</l>
                  <l>Spend precious time with ſacted thoughts that be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es</l>
                  <l>Heav'n in their eyes, true verie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eares.</l>
                  <l>Complaine I will to <hi>Fortune,</hi> not that who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Art</hi> and pale fac'd <hi>Wiſedome</hi> poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:102470:48"/>
                  <l>Il'e not complaine to her, but to that <hi>Ens,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Almighty <hi>Fortune</hi> in divineſt ſenſe.</l>
                  <l>Groveling on <hi>Earth</hi> for ſinne, I'le caſt forth groanes,</l>
                  <l>Sighes ſhall convert to <hi>Teares,</hi> teares into moanes,</l>
                  <l>Then will I ſtart from ground, my body raiſe,</l>
                  <l>Shoote ine eyes upward, againſt heav'n I'le gaze,</l>
                  <l>Thinke on my God, my God whoſe ſacred will</l>
                  <l>I have abus'd; my God moſt juſt to kill,</l>
                  <l>Damme ſoule and body; my rememb rance blot</l>
                  <l>Out of the booke of life; I that forgot</l>
                  <l>In midſt of all vaine joyes, in temp'rate health,</l>
                  <l>Soule-ſnaring Chamb'rings, laſcivious ſtealth,</l>
                  <l>All-ſeeing Heav'n, a <hi>God</hi> ſo greate, ſo good,</l>
                  <l>The death of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> my ſaviours blood,</l>
                  <l>Slave that I am, where ſhall I turne mine eye</l>
                  <l>Vnworthie to looke up? Heav'n heare my cry!</l>
                  <l>Heare me <hi>Eternall Eſſente,</hi> which hath made</l>
                  <l>My ſoule to pray; ſend me thy ſacred aide.</l>
                  <l>"On the bright Sun-beames of thy ſweet ſalvation,</l>
                  <l>"<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> draw up, the dew of my devotion.</l>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:102470:48"/>
                  <l>Mount ſoule upon the wings of Charity,</l>
                  <l>Helpe <hi>Heav'n,</hi> up heart, fly to Eternity.</l>
                  <l>Rowze like a towring <hi>Falkon</hi> in deſpight</l>
                  <l>Of Hell and furies, fly to the Makers ſight,</l>
                  <l>Come, come Lord Ieſus, O come thou and give</l>
                  <l>Helpe to my helpleſſeſoule; I that doe live</l>
                  <l>Like the diſtreſſed bird, trapt in a ſnare</l>
                  <l>Caught by a lime-twigg flying through the Aire;</l>
                  <l>In which diſtreſſe for comforts ſweet releife,</l>
                  <l>Poore Innocent, with wings adds woe to griefe,</l>
                  <l>So fares my ſoule ſtriving ſinnes ſnare to fly,</l>
                  <l>Trapt by deceit, lives ſnar'd in miſery.</l>
                  <l>My trembling conſcience tells me I have beene</l>
                  <l>A very fearefull finner, ſlave to finne,</l>
                  <l>Of all Men, moſt unworthy of Salvation</l>
                  <l>My ſinnes deſerve <hi>Heavn'ns</hi> wrath, <hi>hell</hi> and damnation,</l>
                  <l>Yet mercie, mercy Lord, mercy I crave,</l>
                  <l>Shield my ſad ſoule from the infernall grave,</l>
                  <l>"Strangle my growing ſinnes in their beginning,</l>
                  <l>"Demolliſh (Lord) in me cuſtome in ſinning.</l>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:102470:49"/>
                  <l>"Draw from mine eyes the vaine worlds vaine intice,</l>
                  <l>"And raviſh me with love of <hi>Paradice.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"Buſie my thoughts with vertue, make me trie</l>
                  <l>"To live by honeſt meanes, or let me die.</l>
                  <l>Pardon all idle prate, ſinnes rotten talke</l>
                  <l>Let not my ſteps treade that accurſed walke</l>
                  <l>Which leads to lewdneſſe; baſe delights in pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Deſire of Pompe, vaine glory, tottering treaſure,</l>
                  <l>Let not my wandring eyes flame in the fire</l>
                  <l>Of luſt-ſtung lookes, nor let the looſe deſire</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Beauties Bravery,</hi> burne out mine eyes</l>
                  <l>With ſenſeleſſe gazing; Lord make me to deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>All wanton waies, finnes of ill govern'd youth,</l>
                  <l>All wicked cuſtomes 'gainſt thy ſacred Truth.</l>
                  <l>Make me (my God) in hate to impure lives,</l>
                  <l>Kicke at that life, which life of heav'n deprives:</l>
                  <l>Deale not, Lord deale not with me as my merit</l>
                  <l>Truely deſerves; drive out that uggly ſpirit</l>
                  <l>Of all uncleanneſſe from my filthy fleſh,</l>
                  <l>My drooping ſoule with ſanctitie refreſh,</l>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:102470:49"/>
                  <l>Shrow'd me beneath thy ſacred Countenance,</l>
                  <l>Give me thy ſervant <hi>Davids</hi> repentance,</l>
                  <l>The Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> holy <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Bleſt <hi>Stephens</hi> Charity, chaſte <hi>Ioſephs</hi> life,</l>
                  <l>The Patience of <hi>Iob; Pauls</hi> purity,</l>
                  <l>And ſoule-afflicted <hi>Peters</hi> weeping Eye.</l>
                  <l>"With holy Teares, (Lord) make me to reject</l>
                  <l>"The Sinne, I impious ſinner moſt affect.</l>
                  <l>O thou the King of thoſe Eternall fires</l>
                  <l>That ſpangles <hi>Heav'n;</hi> good God grant my deſires,</l>
                  <l>Infuſe in me thy <hi>Grace,</hi> or I ſhall ſtray,</l>
                  <l>And ſo become a fearefull Caſt-away.</l>
                  <l>I, that am poore, weake, feeble, and too apt,</l>
                  <l>By the worlds whoriſh wales to be intrapt,</l>
                  <l>Beſeech thy pardon, forgive my coldneſſe</l>
                  <l>In ſerving thee, pardon that damned boldneſſe.</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Mercy</hi> every <hi>Evening</hi> which does keepe</l>
                  <l>Me, from day-dangers, death-reſembling ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>Be to my ſoule a <hi>Prayer</hi> booke to imprint</l>
                  <l>Teares in mine Eyes; griefe in my heart of flint;</l>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:102470:50"/>
                  <l>Be it ſo <hi>Mighty Maker</hi> unto mee,</l>
                  <l>To me and every one, make us to ſee</l>
                  <l>And ſhunne ſinnes cuſtome; with thy ſacred wings,</l>
                  <l>Guard us from dangers, bleſſed King of Kings,</l>
                  <l>Thou art my onely comfort in diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Foode, rayment, all my cure in heavineſſe,</l>
                  <l>My true <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> in unruly madneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Soule-raviſhing <hi>Muſicke</hi> in my deepeſt ſadneſſe,</l>
                  <l>When all the world forſakes me God is kind,</l>
                  <l>He comfort gives to my diſconſolate mind.</l>
                  <l>O thou the Lord of Thunder, Heav'n and Earth,</l>
                  <l>Mercifull maker, thou that didſt give me breath.</l>
                  <l>Thou that can'ſt muſter Angells in the Skie,</l>
                  <l>To ſafeguard ſoules from blacke impiety,</l>
                  <l>Thou that doſt feede, and cloath, and ſtill perſever</l>
                  <l>To give me health; be mercifull for ever.</l>
                  <l>"Lord teach me for to prize the world at naught,</l>
                  <l>"Vpon thy bleſſedneſſe be all my thought.</l>
                  <l>"Take from mine eyes, the vaine worlds vaine entice</l>
                  <l>"And rayiſhme with love of Paradiſe.</l>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:102470:50"/>
                  <l>"Bleſſe me each <hi>Morne,</hi> and bleſſe me ev'ry <hi>Ev'n,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"Bleſſe Wife and Children, bring us all to Heav'n</l>
                  <l>In thy good time; and during lifes ſhort ſpace,</l>
                  <l>Grant us Lord Ieſus thy abundant grace.</l>
                  <l>Graft thy Grace inardly in our hearts, that wee</l>
                  <l>Never like ſtraying ſheepe, ſtray Lord from thee.</l>
                  <l>Heare me <hi>Miraculous Majeſtie,</hi> and give</l>
                  <l>A period to my cares, let me not live</l>
                  <l>Fruſtrate of <hi>Honeſt meanes;</hi> O ſend redreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Imploy my <hi>Pen,</hi> keepe me from Idleneſſe,</l>
                  <l>From all ill Company, all waies unjuſt,</l>
                  <l>Sinne, Satan, and the Labyrinth of luſt.</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Ioſeph, Mighty Maker,</hi> make me fly</l>
                  <l>The tempting <hi>Bates</hi> of <hi>Beauties</hi> bravery.</l>
                  <l>Suffer me <hi>Worme unworthy,</hi> not in vaine</l>
                  <l>To call on thee; let me ſome ſolace gaine</l>
                  <l>Or kneele for ever; happie man were I</l>
                  <l>To kneele, and pray, and at my Prayers die.</l>
                  <l>To live for ever; ever more to ſing</l>
                  <l>Glory to thee O God; Heavens glorious King.</l>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:102470:51"/>
                  <l>O you, that ſtand on <hi>Pinacles</hi> of ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Let not the <hi>World</hi> deceive you, leſt too late,</l>
                  <l>From off your ſlipprie height you come in thrall,</l>
                  <l>To paſh your ſelves in pecces paſt recall!</l>
                  <l>Sell not faire <hi>Lordſhips</hi> to keepe <hi>Ladiſhips,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor ſucke damnation from a <hi>Strumpets</hi> lips,</l>
                  <l>Touch not thoſe ſpells of <hi>Sparta,</hi> let 'em rot,</l>
                  <l>When Vertue lives in man, luſt is forgot,</l>
                  <l>One onely Iemme, that's all the ſtore I have,</l>
                  <l>Great of that little, nothing, which ſhall crave</l>
                  <l>Of Heav'ns great <hi>Ens,</hi> not for my ſelfe alone,</l>
                  <l>But for thee <hi>Reader;</hi> thee, and every one</l>
                  <l>Rareneſſe of rare example, and withall</l>
                  <l>An everlaſting skie of Grace to fall</l>
                  <l>Vpon our Warre on Earth, deſiring Heav'n,</l>
                  <l>For waies on Earth are crooked, all unev'n.</l>
                  <l>O Heav'nly <hi>Father,</hi> glorious Diety,</l>
                  <l>Pardon, O Pardon my impiety,</l>
                  <l>I, that have imperfections on my head,</l>
                  <l>Paſt Starres in number; or thoſe ſands that ſpread</l>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:102470:51"/>
                  <l>The Vaſt Seas bottome; ſhall not I confeſſe,</l>
                  <l>How oft 'gainſt God, I deſp'rately tranſgreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Put off Repentance ſtill from day to day,</l>
                  <l>Abuſe his mighty <hi>Patience,</hi> ſtill delay</l>
                  <l>His dread <hi>Command;</hi> and like a ſenceleſſe ſot,</l>
                  <l>Vnmindfull of his mercies; minde them not,</l>
                  <l>No ſooner doe I finde a good thought take me;</l>
                  <l>But from that vertue fleſh and bloud doe ſhake me.</l>
                  <l>Forgive me, O forgive me thou that art</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns univerſall ſearcher, cure my heart,</l>
                  <l>At my dull follies Ile no longer winke,</l>
                  <l>Sorrow ſhall be my <hi>Pen,</hi> ſad teares my <hi>Incke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Miſery my <hi>Paper,</hi> whereon I'le write</l>
                  <l>The ſorrowes of my ſoule, my <hi>youthes</hi> delight,</l>
                  <l>My pathes of pleaſure, <hi>Prodigall</hi> expences,</l>
                  <l>My Scarlet Crimes, and all my blacke offences:</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Booke,</hi> I'le <hi>dedicate</hi> unto my heart,</l>
                  <l>My heart, chiefe <hi>Actor,</hi> in ſinnes <hi>Tragicke</hi> part.</l>
                  <l>My heart, <hi>unprincely,</hi> Revelling within</l>
                  <l>My body, that <hi>Banquetting</hi> houſe of ſinne;</l>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:102470:52"/>
                  <l>There, Chain'd to 'th <hi>Magicke Muſicke</hi> of free will,</l>
                  <l>Riots in poyſon'd pleaſure, lewdly ill.</l>
                  <l>All that belongs to th'body, ev'ry part,</l>
                  <l>(My ſoule alone excepted) ſerves my heart,</l>
                  <l>Beſt pleas'd; and beſt at eaſe, with pleaſures bane,</l>
                  <l>Moſt glad, to be moſt bad; and in that vaine</l>
                  <l>Traitor to <hi>Truth;</hi> each limbe a Mortall foe,</l>
                  <l>To worke my univerſall overthrow.</l>
                  <l>O falſe, falſe heart, falſe to thy deareſt freind,</l>
                  <l>Wound me no more; for pittle make an end,</l>
                  <l>I pitty thy blacke life; nor can forbeare,</l>
                  <l>For thee, to ſhed many a bleeding teare.</l>
                  <l>Thou art my foe: and yet to ſee thee feed,</l>
                  <l>Fat for <hi>Hells Shambles,</hi> my poore ſoule dosbleed;</l>
                  <l>Bleeds inward, indiſcern'd of any eye,</l>
                  <l>Except my <hi>God,</hi> and my owne miſery.</l>
                  <l>What ſhall I doe? faine would I ſhunne the ſinne</l>
                  <l>My frailty moſt delights to wander in:</l>
                  <l>And yet I cannot; when I ſtrive 'gainſt vice</l>
                  <l>To ſtand moſt firme, I'me tript up in a trice.</l>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:102470:52"/>
                  <l>"O What a mis'ry 'tis to have a minde</l>
                  <l>"For to be truely honeſt; well inclinde,</l>
                  <l>"And not to be ſufferd; ſuch is the ſtate,</l>
                  <l>"Of my ſad bleeding ſoule unfortunate.</l>
                  <l>"Field honour's but a Vapour; the ſound breſt,</l>
                  <l>"Puts on <hi>Church-Armour Faith,</hi> and ſleights the reſt.</l>
                  <l>"In Love to Vertue and true godly feare,</l>
                  <l>"Dwells Honour; not in <hi>Dart, Bowe, Sling</hi> or <hi>Speare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not in vaine Beauty, ſtrength, the pride of Wit,</l>
                  <l>Preſuming Riches, Learning, Valour, Credit,</l>
                  <l>High Birth, Nobility, nor gravitie,</l>
                  <l>Humanity, nor yet Virginity,</l>
                  <l>But in the humbleſoule whom holy ſtorie,</l>
                  <l>Speaks to maintaine God, and the Goſpels glory;</l>
                  <l>The King and Kingdomes ſafety; Churches peace,</l>
                  <l>The Virgins right, Widdowes and fatherleſſe;</l>
                  <l>Theſe are the noble ſteps that ever waite,</l>
                  <l>On Vertues Court; 'tis the true Prop of ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Save me, O ſave me thou Eternall terrour,</l>
                  <l>To damned ſoules, I doe confeſſe each errour,</l>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:102470:53"/>
                  <l>The many thouſand ſinnes, unſeene, unfelt,</l>
                  <l>Which long, too long, in my hard heart have dwelt,</l>
                  <l>To thee, to thee thou everlaſting being,</l>
                  <l>Of an Eternall <hi>Majestie;</hi> all ſeeing,</l>
                  <l>With Penitent heart, I come, I call, I cry,</l>
                  <l>Pittie me wretch, helpe thou all viewing eye.</l>
                  <l>My armes are ſpread, come ſempeternall Eſſence,</l>
                  <l>Raviſh my ſoule; come bleſſed Penitence</l>
                  <l>Give me thouſand ſtabbs, my ſoule has neede,</l>
                  <l>Of many thouſand teares; then let it bleede!</l>
                  <l>Pierce, pierce my ſtubborne heart, make that the Inne</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Grace,</hi> which yet, is but the houſe of ſinne;</l>
                  <l>Looke downe ſoule ſaving ſacred God of Truth,</l>
                  <l>Forgive th'infinite follies of my youth,</l>
                  <l>Shield me Divinity from Sathans ginnes,</l>
                  <l>Lord lay not to my charge my Parents ſinnes:</l>
                  <l>Glory of goodneſſe in thy mercy, heare me,</l>
                  <l>Let hate, <hi>Revenge,</hi> nor <hi>Envie</hi> ne're come neare me,</l>
                  <l>Let neither <hi>Pride,</hi> nor hope of <hi>gaine</hi> deceive me,</l>
                  <l>Nor pleaſure, nor the want of meanes bereave me</l>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:102470:53"/>
                  <l>Of ſence; leſt ſenceleſſe wholy I deſpaire</l>
                  <l>And ſo become the wretched child of Care.</l>
                  <l>O ſacred ſaviour; give me grace to fly</l>
                  <l>Delight in ſinne; I beg it earneſtly,</l>
                  <l>In all my prayers enable me to be</l>
                  <l>(Bleſſed Lord Ieſus) pleaſting unto thee.</l>
                  <l>Make me to doe thy will Lord; make me grow</l>
                  <l>Great in thy love, thou that doſt truely know,</l>
                  <l>Of all <hi>Earths bleſſings</hi> unto mortalls giv'n,</l>
                  <l>My ſole deſire on <hi>Earth,</hi> is <hi>Grace</hi> from Heav'n,</l>
                  <l>Grace to be good; grace to avoide hels ginnes,</l>
                  <l>And grace to grieve, for nothing but my ſinnes,</l>
                  <l>So ſhall thy mercy, ne'r forgetfull ſtand,</l>
                  <l>While I have <hi>Tongue,</hi> a <hi>Pen,</hi> a <hi>head,</hi> a <hi>hand.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:54"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:54"/>
               <head>The Soules Sea fight,</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>EMp'rour of Angells; O thou King of Starrs,</l>
                  <l>Man's perfect ſolace 'gainſt ſinnes bloudy warres,</l>
                  <l>When I behold with contemplations Eye</l>
                  <l>The ſilver ſpangles of the glorious skie;</l>
                  <l>Me thinks in that Blew-paper-booke of Heay a</l>
                  <l>I ſee the waies of Mortalls all Vnev'n,</l>
                  <l>The wretched ſoule of Man in ev'ry place,</l>
                  <l>Lives Locally in hell, Wanting thy grace,</l>
                  <l>Temptation on temptation paſt controule,</l>
                  <l>Alures the body to betray the ſoule;</l>
                  <l>Hells <hi>Blacke-Prince Troopes</hi> of ſpiries ev'ry day,</l>
                  <l>Invades Mans Sinne-ſeidg-Soule, <hi>Furies</hi> diſplay</l>
                  <l>Infernall <hi>Banners,</hi> while the <hi>Drum</hi> of death</l>
                  <l>Beates a dead <hi>March,</hi> and e're I can take breath.</l>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:102470:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:102470:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:102470:56"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:102470:56"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102470:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102470:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:102470:58"/>
                  <l>Sounds ſhrill Alarums, hot aſſaults beginne</l>
                  <l>The ſoules fierce <hi>fight;</hi> muffl'd in cloudy ſinne,</l>
                  <l>I live beſet; Millions of ſpirits round</l>
                  <l>Shoot at my ſoule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſtand on no firme ground</l>
                  <l>But tread on Earth, as on a Ball of ice.</l>
                  <l>I cannot ſtand, nor ſtirre for ſliprie vice.</l>
                  <l>My Soul's a ſhip toſt on the mountaine ſeas,</l>
                  <l>Of this vaſt world; ſhe never lives at eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>Sailes</hi> are <hi>ſighes,</hi> her <hi>Anchor</hi> deepe deſpaire,</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>Compaſse</hi> errour, her ſad <hi>Pilot</hi> care.</l>
                  <l>Farre off from ſafetyes ſhore, floates on the waves</l>
                  <l>Of fearefull billowes, Soule-devouting graves,</l>
                  <l>Rough, bluſtring ſtubborne ſtormes, yeeld no reliefe</l>
                  <l>On ev'ry <hi>ſhrowd,</hi> each <hi>Tackling</hi> hangs a griefe,</l>
                  <l>Death like a darke cloud, beſets every place,</l>
                  <l>Here <hi>Rockes</hi> of <hi>ruine,</hi> there <hi>Pyrates</hi> lie in chaſe,</l>
                  <l>In ev'ry corner miſcheifes hour'ly lurke,</l>
                  <l>Pride fights againſt us like a furious Turke.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lust</hi> like a <hi>Trech'rous Spaniard,</hi> murd'ring <hi>French,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Like an infected poyſons loathſome ſtench,</l>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:102470:58"/>
                  <l>Gluttonie like a <hi>Germane;</hi> drunkenneſſe</l>
                  <l>Like a <hi>Dutch-dun-ker-ker;</hi> whoſe impiouſneſſe</l>
                  <l>Stiles him the Maſter Gunner to give fire</l>
                  <l>To all Sinnes blacke Artillery, hells Ire,</l>
                  <l>Infernall Chaine-ſhort, All Soule murd'ring ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>To ſnke mans weather-beaten ſhip of life.</l>
                  <l>Which to gaine grace; no ſooner weighes Anchor,</l>
                  <l>Sets faile for ſafety, but ſtraight Sinnes canker</l>
                  <l>The devouring Devill, <hi>Pyrate</hi> for Hell,</l>
                  <l>Chaſing flyes after; and with blacke <hi>Arts</hi> ſpell</l>
                  <l>Commands to ſtay; ſometimes with beautions formes,</l>
                  <l>With ſongs of <hi>Syrens</hi> ſometimes; ſometimes ſtormes,</l>
                  <l>Such pitchy <hi>Tempeſts,</hi> to benight the way,</l>
                  <l>As if the <hi>horrour</hi> of the Latter day;</l>
                  <l>Frighted the world, ſo ſtops the ſoule from bliffe,</l>
                  <l>Shoots through and through her; ſo ſhe ſteares amiſſe.</l>
                  <l>Then as in <hi>bloudy Sea-fights</hi> men may ſee,</l>
                  <l>Times ſacrifice to valour, no man free</l>
                  <l>From deſperate danger; every one maintaines</l>
                  <l>The terrour of the fight (though with their braines</l>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:102470:59"/>
                  <l>"Daſht in each others face) vitall breath</l>
                  <l>"Loſt in a <hi>Fighting flame;</hi> bloud and death</l>
                  <l>"Ballets, and <hi>Batteries,</hi> covers the <hi>ſhip</hi> all ore</l>
                  <l>"Her diſmall <hi>Decks</hi> with horror, purple gore,</l>
                  <l>And ſcatter'd limbes; O the ſad ſhreeke the cries,</l>
                  <l>Here ſinckes a <hi>Ship,</hi> and there another fries</l>
                  <l>In fiery flames; ſome to ſcape preſent harme</l>
                  <l>Mount the <hi>Maine-Top,</hi> ſome hang on the <hi>Yard-Arme,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Till the pitcht <hi>Maſt</hi> becomes a blazing Torch,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe up flying flame, when it beginnes to ſcortch,</l>
                  <l>Downe, downe the poore <hi>Soules</hi> drop, who (life to ſave)</l>
                  <l>Vnwilling, willingly make the Sea their Grave,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>deepes</hi> their <hi>Tombes;</hi> ſo the ſoules Pinnace</l>
                  <l>In her ſpirituall fight, ſinne dos deface,</l>
                  <l>Murders our beſt of thoughts; like raging ſeas,</l>
                  <l>Windes, Stormes, &amp; Tempeſts, drive us where they pleaſe</l>
                  <l>The poore afflicted ſoule, Satan ſo blinds</l>
                  <l>It knowes not where ſhe is; by whizing winds</l>
                  <l>Now-toſt, toth' top, of all the Azure skie,</l>
                  <l>Now tumbling as to <hi>Hell</hi> with frighted Bye,</l>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:102470:59"/>
                  <l>Her <hi>Flag</hi> of ſinnes deſiance Tempeſts rent,</l>
                  <l>Her ſayles torne all to raggs; her maine maſt ſpent</l>
                  <l>All out of order, toſſing too, and fro,</l>
                  <l>The ſoule diſtreſt, knowes not not which way to goe.</l>
                  <l>With gentle calme; checke Sathans blacke ſtorme Lord,</l>
                  <l>We ſhipwracke elſe; Devills will come abord</l>
                  <l>Burne with hells Wildfire; flame, ruine, raze,</l>
                  <l>Blot our ſoules hope, helpe miniſter of grace.</l>
                  <l>Safetie's in Heav'n; in this uncertaine life,</l>
                  <l>Nothing but Hell-bred Quickſands, warre and ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Soule killing vapours, worldly vanites,</l>
                  <l>Thicke clouds of Vice perpetuall miſeries!</l>
                  <l>There is a <hi>Voyage</hi> to the holy land,</l>
                  <l>In which the <hi>Truth</hi> our bleſſed <hi>Card</hi> muſt ſtand</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> our <hi>Pilote</hi> to Direct</l>
                  <l>The Steerage of our <hi>Courſe</hi> from ſinnes neglect</l>
                  <l>To th'<hi>Haven</hi> of <hi>Heav'n;</hi> that happie Port of reſt</l>
                  <l>Salvation's guard, true Cape of comfort bleſt,</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Heav'ns</hi> bright <hi>Majestie</hi> our Saviour ſweet,</l>
                  <l>Sits with the hand of mercy for to greet</l>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:102470:60"/>
                  <l>And waft us to him; O may all that ſtray</l>
                  <l>Sayling along the <hi>Coaſt</hi> of ſorrow pray,</l>
                  <l>Pray unto him; he'le guide their wand'ring Barke</l>
                  <l>Tempeſt-toſt hontely in the dreadfull darke.</l>
                  <l>If thou be <hi>Sea-ſick,</hi> call upon him, and he</l>
                  <l>Shall ſoone, with healths ſweet ſolace comfort thee,</l>
                  <l>Rebuke the raging winds, Times blackeſt ſtormes,</l>
                  <l>And to a <hi>Calme,</hi> skie-ſwelling ſeas reforme.</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Rocks, Gulfes, Sands,</hi> nor ſeas-cloud-kiſſing waves</l>
                  <l>Sinnes dreadfull <hi>Sea-fights,</hi> nor the deſperate braves</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Pyrates,</hi> none ſhall hurt; let then thy care</l>
                  <l>See thy weake <hi>Veſſell</hi> rigg'd, well <hi>Mann'd</hi> with prayer,</l>
                  <l>And then <hi>Launch</hi> forth, hoiſt ſailes, and when you ſpie</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Cape</hi> of good hope, keepe it in thine eye.</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Holy thoughts deatht-breatning ſtormers</hi> ore'come,</l>
                  <l>That whatſoever chance there ſhall become,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>veſſell</hi> of thy body, being foule,</l>
                  <l>Make ſure to ſave the <hi>Paſſenger</hi> thy ſoule.</l>
                  <l>He valiant, onely vertuous is that can</l>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:102470:60"/>
                  <l>Subdue his ſinnes, He's the true Noble man.</l>
                  <l>Ther's perfect valour, he true glory winnes,</l>
                  <l>Hee's the true ſouldier that ſubdues his ſinnes,</l>
                  <l>Breaks through the Pikes of ſinne, all Fiends that are</l>
                  <l>In Hell, or divells ruling in the ayre,</l>
                  <l>Forceing his way to Heav'n deſpight all charmes,</l>
                  <l>Enchantments, dead ſleepes, all ſoule-ſlaying harmes,</l>
                  <l>Wreſtling like <hi>Iacob</hi> conſtant in his ſight,</l>
                  <l>Mindfull of his Majeſticke-Makers ſight,</l>
                  <l>To ſuch, belongs the Everlaſting Crowne</l>
                  <l>Of Sempeternall <hi>glory,</hi> true renowne.</l>
                  <l>Which to prepare thee for; ceaſe to neglect</l>
                  <l>Th'<hi>Almighties</hi> ſacred <hi>ſervice,</hi> let reſpect,</l>
                  <l>Feare and true reverence to his pretious word,</l>
                  <l>Be to thy Soule Truths Helmet, ſhield and ſword,</l>
                  <l>Fit to ſubdue the Fiend, all fiery Darts,</l>
                  <l>Furies and fiends, Heav'n arme thy noble parts,</l>
                  <l>Soule, Body, Heart, and all ſtrive to fulfill</l>
                  <l>(The Majeſtie of Heav'n) his divine will.</l>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:102470:61"/>
                  <l>And like the cunning curious Architect,</l>
                  <l>Earneſt ſome goodly building to erect,</l>
                  <l>(Breaking his ſteepe) wholy imployes his mind</l>
                  <l>On the drawne modell, which when he dos find</l>
                  <l>Exact; his eye dwells ever then upon it,</l>
                  <l>And his affection never driven from it.</l>
                  <l>So when to thought we call our Saviours bloud,</l>
                  <l>(That ſempeternall <hi>Platforme</hi> of all good)</l>
                  <l>Shed for our ſinnes; let it for ever dwell</l>
                  <l>In the <hi>Idaea</hi> of our minds, ſo Hell</l>
                  <l>Sterne <hi>Death,</hi> nor deadly deſp'rate diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Can barre the heav'nly heart from's true content!</l>
                  <l>"Gods Vengeance againſt ſinne, his true diſlike</l>
                  <l>Me thinkes ſhould move us to repent, and ſtrike</l>
                  <l>A terrour to our ſoules, force us to ſee</l>
                  <l>Man's outward danger, inward miſerie.</l>
                  <l>Which like an unreſiſted roaring Tide</l>
                  <l>Runnes through our veines, apts the baſe bloud to pride</l>
                  <l>To all the ſinnes that are, or ever were,</l>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:102470:61"/>
                  <l>O horid ill, have we not cauſe to feare,</l>
                  <l>To quake, and tremble, when our dull dead eyes</l>
                  <l>(Drunke with the poyſon'd dreggs of ſinne) ne'r ſpies</l>
                  <l>The miſcheivous perills, and the blacke affright;</l>
                  <l>That hourely wait on the ſpirituall fight;</l>
                  <l>Fiends live at <hi>Sea,</hi> and <hi>Furies</hi> on the land,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gluttony</hi> for a <hi>Corporall</hi> dos ſtand;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Avarice</hi> a <hi>Pioner, Sloth</hi> you'l ſpie,</l>
                  <l>An idle <hi>Gentleman</hi> of a Companie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wraths</hi> the <hi>Serjeant, Envie</hi> the Colours gaine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Luſt</hi> the <hi>Lievtenant</hi> is; <hi>Pride</hi> the Captaine.</l>
                  <l>Theſe in the hearts of ev'ry one takes place,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Cowardly Soules</hi> ſhuns the bleſt meanes of grace.</l>
                  <l>Let us for ever then, deſiſt from evill,</l>
                  <l>Wiſedome commands us to deſie the Devill.</l>
                  <l>To combate with our ſinnes oppoſe temptation,</l>
                  <l>Fight againſt <hi>Hell,</hi> the <hi>Devill</hi> and damnation.</l>
                  <l>This for a <hi>Caveat</hi> take, ſtrive to live well,</l>
                  <l>Ingratitude to God, findes flames in Hell.</l>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:102470:62"/>
                  <l>While grace is offer'd then, watch, faſt, and pray,</l>
                  <l>Ther's no prevention in the latter day.</l>
                  <l>None lives ſecure, that to his Vice lives friend,</l>
                  <l>A Vicious life, oft makes a Vicious end.</l>
                  <l>Strengthen me my Creator, make me fight,</l>
                  <l>Thy holy battell, let not the worlds delight</l>
                  <l>Diſſwade my ſoule; ſweet Ieſus for thy merit</l>
                  <l>Enable me, rowze my dejected ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>Vncharme Hells charme; O ſacred God untie</l>
                  <l>My fetter'd ſoule; let me not ever lie</l>
                  <l>Lull'd in the lazie lan of deadly ſinne,</l>
                  <l>This Minute Sacred Saviour, now beginue</l>
                  <l>To give releaſe; and as thou didſt provide,</l>
                  <l>Army of <hi>Angells</hi> for <hi>Eliahs</hi> guide,</l>
                  <l>Who (to ſecure him girt with Enemies)</l>
                  <l>Mounted his ſoule from worldly vanities,</l>
                  <l>So Heav'nly <hi>Day-ſtar,</hi> bleſſed <hi>Jeſus</hi> end</l>
                  <l>This my deſigne; thy holy <hi>Angell</hi> ſend</l>
                  <l>To be my guide, my guard, my ſacred ſpell</l>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:102470:62"/>
                  <l>'Gainſt all Enchantments, Witchcraft, Death and Hell.</l>
                  <l>So ſhall my <hi>Anthem</hi> ev'ry <hi>Morning</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>Glory of <hi>Heav'n</hi> pitty, O pitty me.</l>
                  <l>Pitty me Wretch, moſt wretched, vilely baſe</l>
                  <l>Wanting thy ſacred aide, ſpirituall grace.</l>
                  <l>The onely Cure ſinnes raging flames to quentch,</l>
                  <l>Is <hi>Aqua Lacrymarum;</hi> that will ſtench</l>
                  <l>The wounds proud pomper'd Dames delight to make</l>
                  <l>On the poore ſoule of man, make him to quake;</l>
                  <l>Afeard to ſtand on that falſe <hi>Rocke</hi> of Ice</l>
                  <l>Idleneſſe, feeder of foule <hi>Carnall</hi> Vice.</l>
                  <l>Blacke errours cloud, <hi>South Fog</hi> which rotts the mind,</l>
                  <l>Leapours the ſoule, and is that <hi>Northerne</hi> winde</l>
                  <l>The cauſe of all ſinnes ſtormes, 'tis dangers floud,</l>
                  <l>Sinnes-ſurging Ocean, ſwelling in mans bloud.</l>
                  <l>O Soule alluring ſinne, me, me forſake,</l>
                  <l>I charge thee hence, by him that made Hell quake,</l>
                  <l>By that <hi>Almighty One,</hi> in ſacred <hi>Trine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All holy ſpells and charmes <hi>Magicke</hi> divine,</l>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:102470:63"/>
                  <l>Siſter of <hi>Angells Virgins Chaſtitie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By that <hi>Sovle ſaving ſacred</hi> puritie,</l>
                  <l>Fly from me all baſe thoughts; be juſt mine eyes,</l>
                  <l>And be your ſelves, hate wantons witcheries.</l>
                  <l>The bleſſing of th' <hi>Almighty,</hi> Lord of Hoaſt,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Sonne,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Preſerve, be with me, now and for ever when,</l>
                  <l>My ſoule is moſt diſtreſt <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:63"/>
               <head>The Virgins Honour.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, As a Child, that of it ſelfe can doe</l>
                  <l>Nothing, to ſheild <hi>Virginity</hi> from woe,</l>
                  <l>Proſtrate on bended <hi>Knees</hi> with teares I fall</l>
                  <l>Before thee <hi>Lord;</hi> O heare, on thee I call.</l>
                  <l>Pittie me wretch, I that am in the prime</l>
                  <l>Heate of my youth; and the moſt dang'rons tyme</l>
                  <l>Of all my life; beſeech thy heavenly aide,</l>
                  <l>All holy helpes; Lord pitty me weake Maide.</l>
                  <l>Leſt like the filly fly about the Flame,</l>
                  <l>I ſcortch to Cinders; burne out my good name.</l>
                  <l>Quench, quench the flames of all lewd carnall Motions,</l>
                  <l>Inordinate deſires, all looſe affections.</l>
                  <l>Never let my ſoule be led away good Lord</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Wanton Company,</hi> that no good afford.</l>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:102470:64"/>
                  <l>Waking or ſleeping; O thou King of Kings,</l>
                  <l>Let the ſafe pearefull ſhaddow of thy wings</l>
                  <l>Be my <hi>Eternall ſafetie,</hi> leſt the mines</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Golden Snares,</hi> alter my chaſt deſignes.</l>
                  <l>By day and night, <hi>Lord let thy</hi> gracious beames,</l>
                  <l>Diſperſe all wandring thoughts, all idle dreames!</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> is a more pretious Iewell</l>
                  <l>Then I can keepe; let me not then be cruell</l>
                  <l>To my owne ſoule; but, by the more that I,</l>
                  <l>In the great danger of <hi>Temptation</hi> lie,</l>
                  <l>So much the greater, let thy grace preſerve</l>
                  <l>My <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin Honour;</hi> and though I deſerve</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Vengeance,</hi> indignation, and no favour,</l>
                  <l>Yet for thy Mercies ſake, moſt ſacred Saviour,</l>
                  <l>Be thou my Advocate; Lord make me free,</l>
                  <l>To ſue in <hi>ferma pauperis</hi> under thee.</l>
                  <l>Angelize thou my ſoule, to ſhunne the Tract</l>
                  <l>Of obſcene ſpeech; lew'd thought, and uncleane act.</l>
                  <l>To thee for ever make me reconcil'd,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Body,</hi> and <hi>Soule,</hi> chaſt, holy, undefil'd.</l>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:102470:64"/>
                  <l>And through the operation of thy grace,</l>
                  <l>To ſpit defiance in <hi>ſinnes</hi> uggly face.</l>
                  <l>"Pleaſures are poyſons to this ſoule of mine,</l>
                  <l>"Ther's no true joy on Earth, but what's divine.</l>
                  <l>What ſhall I doe? helpe Prince of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I cannot ſtand, nor ſtirre for ſlip'ry <hi>Vice.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Quicken me Lord, enable me to pray:</l>
                  <l>Humble my Minde, my <hi>Parents</hi> to obey</l>
                  <l>In all their juſt commands; and at all times,</l>
                  <l>Patient to beare reproofes, confeſſe my crimes.</l>
                  <l>Ne're let me (Lord) be ſo depriv'd of grace,</l>
                  <l>To ſcoffe (like ſome) their Parents to their face.</l>
                  <l>Make me in ſtead of ſtubborne waies to grieve 'em,</l>
                  <l>(At their moſt need) ſtill able to relieve 'em.</l>
                  <l>Increaſe good Heav'n, the number of their dayes;</l>
                  <l>To ſpeake thy glory, and to ſing thy prayſe.</l>
                  <l>And if thy will e're call me to the ſtate</l>
                  <l>Of honorable wedlocke; let my <hi>Mate</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be ſuch a one (good God) with whom I may</l>
                  <l>Serve thee in peace; and never goe aſtray.</l>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:102470:65"/>
                  <l>Ne're let contention, nurs'd 'twixt <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Wife,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Diſturbe the <hi>Quiet</hi> of my married <hi>life.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Married</hi> or <hi>Single,</hi> let me ever be,</l>
                  <l>Fitted with <hi>Prudence,</hi> pleaſing unto thee.</l>
                  <l>Make me to ſhunne (great God) ſins dang'rous ſhelfe,</l>
                  <l>That I, apoore Tree, barren in my ſelfe</l>
                  <l>May Bud; and beare ſuch fruits of Faith as may,</l>
                  <l>My ſoule emparadice at the <hi>Judgement</hi> day.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:65"/>
               <head>The Single and Marrid Life.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SOme ſay, the ſingle life, is ſingle care,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſinne ſtill <hi>Slaves</hi> it under <hi>Sathans</hi> ſnare,</l>
                  <l>Soule-burning <hi>Beauties-brav'ry,</hi> witching folly,</l>
                  <l>Which mads th'intemprate Braine breeds melancholly,</l>
                  <l>Delight in dangrous Dice, Drabs, drinke, and Riot,</l>
                  <l>Sinne Theife-like robs, the ſingle life of quiet</l>
                  <l>Hinders the happie Soule from being wed'</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Vertues faire, Chast, Honeſt, Humble bed.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O what a ſacred ſweetneſſe had it beene,</l>
                  <l>Had our firſt <hi>Parents</hi> purity ſhunn'd ſinne.</l>
                  <l>Marriage, that Rich immaculate <hi>Robe</hi> of honour,</l>
                  <l>Hadne're beene tempted then to baſe diſhonour;</l>
                  <l>Luſt, that do's hour'ly ſlave the ſingle life,</l>
                  <l>And ſhunnes the ſweets of Wedlock, through baſe ſtrife.</l>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:102470:66"/>
                  <l>Had ne're beene thought on then; all had gone well,</l>
                  <l>Soules ne're had cauſe to feare ſinne, death nor hell.</l>
                  <l>Mariage was made for Man, ('tis a true Text)</l>
                  <l>For <hi>honour,</hi> not diſhonour, to be vext</l>
                  <l>With deadly ſtrife; adultr'ate fornication,</l>
                  <l>Vnruly <hi>Luſt,</hi> ſinne-cauſing-ſeparation</l>
                  <l>(Hell to the Bed that's chaſt) turning the eaſe</l>
                  <l>Of wholſome <hi>Marriage,</hi> into a diſeaſe.</l>
                  <l>Wedlocks great weighty worke, craves ſound advice,</l>
                  <l>Begg'd at the hands of Heav'n; leſt cheating Vice,</l>
                  <l>Puts tricks on faire beleeving honeſty,</l>
                  <l>To cloake Biggebellies prurient renery.</l>
                  <l>Marriage requires a ſolemne Meditation,</l>
                  <l>Trembling reſolve, no ſudaine affectation</l>
                  <l>Vnask't of Heavn'n; the mari'd life muſt be,</l>
                  <l>Vnforc'd, Religious, faithfull, chaſt and free,</l>
                  <l>Elſe like <hi>Jehorams</hi> Match twill prove a curſe,</l>
                  <l>Bad the beginning, but the end farre worſe.</l>
                  <l>Learne wiſedome by this Truth, be zealous,</l>
                  <l>Vſe holy <hi>Iobs</hi> preſervative; be Jealous,</l>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:102470:66"/>
                  <l>Thou that art <hi>Married</hi> over all thy waies,</l>
                  <l>Beauties alurement <hi>Natur's</hi> ill ſpent dayes,</l>
                  <l>Thy trouble about wealth, greife<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> long and large,</l>
                  <l>Care ſtill to get, <hi>Childrens</hi> continuall charge,</l>
                  <l>Loſſes by <hi>Servants,</hi> ſinnes infirmity</l>
                  <l>Vnquietneſſe of <hi>Neighbours;</hi> all do cry,</l>
                  <l>And cry alow; the married life to be,</l>
                  <l>Man's ent'rance into ſad calamity.</l>
                  <l>The Married life, I fitly may compare</l>
                  <l>To Heav'n or Hell, unto the Earth, or Ayre,</l>
                  <l>'Tis Heav'n where harmeleſſe <hi>Turtle Mates</hi> agree,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Diſmall Hell</hi> where <hi>Couples</hi> faithleſſe be,</l>
                  <l>Sweet like the dainty wholſome Ayre to ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>Where Man and Wife content, ſhunne rude offence.</l>
                  <l>But where deepe diſcord rules, and proud diſdaine,</l>
                  <l>There, like the gaping <hi>Tongue-tide Eath</hi> for Raine</l>
                  <l>(Sun-burnt with ſordid Actions, deeds unjuſt)</l>
                  <l>They partch to Cinders, fall away to duſt:</l>
                  <l>Tis ſinnes juſt payment, whoſe reward is death,</l>
                  <l>The miſery of life, and ſcourge of breath.</l>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:102470:67"/>
                  <l>"Wiſedome directs the married life to be,</l>
                  <l>"The peacefull <hi>Embleme</hi> of true Vnitie.</l>
                  <l>"Heav'n gives a bleſſing; makes that love divine</l>
                  <l>"Where <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Wife</hi> content, draw in a Line:</l>
                  <l>"A <hi>Wife,</hi> obeying of her Husbands will,</l>
                  <l>"Ha's the rule over him, deſerves no ill!</l>
                  <l>Love, is a <hi>worthy Wife,</hi> Times precious <hi>woman,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Luſt a perfidious <hi>Harlot,</hi> true to no man.</l>
                  <l>"There is no joy on Earth that can tranſcend,</l>
                  <l>"A <hi>Husband</hi> and a <hi>Wife,</hi> kind to the end.</l>
                  <l>"The <hi>carefull Husband's</hi> honeſt gaines no doubt,</l>
                  <l>"Makes the <hi>Good-wife,</hi> an honeſt layer out.</l>
                  <l>"A Vertuous Wife (free from all lewd expence)</l>
                  <l>"Is the Husbands joy, his Tower of defence;</l>
                  <l>"Thus ſpeakes the Text, diſcretion in a Wife</l>
                  <l>"Make's fatt the Husbands bones, delights his life.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:67"/>
               <head>Teares Triumph.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHat's Honour, Beauty, and the damaske skinne,</l>
                  <l>But Dirty droſſe, ballanc'd with teares for ſinne,</l>
                  <l>One trickling teare for ſinne, gaines greater pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Then a whole <hi>Ocean</hi> of terreſtriall treaſure.</l>
                  <l>"Many can weepe, to counterfeits 'tis given,</l>
                  <l>"But to weepe truely, is the gift of Heav'n.</l>
                  <l>Mirrour of <hi>Truth,</hi> give me the ſacred Raies</l>
                  <l>Of divine knowledge, ſo to ſpend my dayes</l>
                  <l>In ſighes, teares, prayers, that my poore ſoule may,</l>
                  <l>Mount to thy glory, at my latter day.</l>
                  <l>"Happy the man, whoſe teares adorne the place</l>
                  <l>"Where he do's pray, that's the true ſigne of grace.</l>
                  <l>"Teares joyn'd with <hi>Prayers,</hi> are triumphant Twinnes,</l>
                  <l>"Soft waxe, hot Iron, to disburthen ſinnes.</l>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:102470:68"/>
                  <l>"Mingle thy Prayers with teares; teares ſoules refreſh,</l>
                  <l>"Kills all the wanton <hi>Motions</hi> of the fleſh,</l>
                  <l>"Teares humble <hi>Pride,</hi> makes chaſt inſatiate luſt,</l>
                  <l>"<hi>Malice</hi> to Mercy turnes, turnes time unjuſt</l>
                  <l>"Detracting <hi>Envie</hi> into Noble pittie,</l>
                  <l>"Dull <hi>Drunkards</hi> to be temp'rate; heavenly wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</l>
                  <l>"Converts baſe <hi>Avarice</hi> from the abuſe,</l>
                  <l>"Of godleſſe gaine, to charitable uſe,</l>
                  <l>"Teares, Phiſicks <hi>Gluttony</hi> to live content</l>
                  <l>"With meane courſe fare; makes mortalls penitent.</l>
                  <l>"Teares lengthens <hi>yeares;</hi> to Man's laſt day teares give,</l>
                  <l>"Sufficient meanes conentedly to live,</l>
                  <l>God that beheld King <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s teares,</l>
                  <l>Prolong'd his dayes; added full fifteene yeares.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Peter,</hi> that thrice denide his ſacred Lord,</l>
                  <l>Teares gain'd his pardon without ſpeaking word:</l>
                  <l>"O bleſſed <hi>Teares;</hi> teares that for ſinne ariſe,</l>
                  <l>"Are glorious <hi>Pearles</hi> ith' <hi>Petitidaers</hi> eyes.</l>
                  <l>Weepe for thy ſinnes poore ſoule; 'tis Heav'ns advire,</l>
                  <l>Teares <hi>Orient E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arles</hi> purchaſe Paradice.</l>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:102470:68"/>
                  <l>Shall ſuch Soule-pleading Pearles then I pray</l>
                  <l>Be flung to Swine? 'mong ſwine be caſt away?</l>
                  <l>Reſolve me thou whoſe conſcience never felt</l>
                  <l>A teare for ſinne; O let thy ſoule but melt</l>
                  <l>To penitent Pearles; then, then let it tell</l>
                  <l>The infinite difference, 'twixt Heav'n and Hel.</l>
                  <l>With, and without thoſe raviſhing teares; the one</l>
                  <l>Feeles joy, free pardon; but the other none!</l>
                  <l>Vnpittied plagnes attend the ſcorneful eye</l>
                  <l>Ne're wet for ſinne; that's endleſſe miſery.</l>
                  <l>When on the adverſe part, where ſoules bewaile</l>
                  <l>Their wretched frailty, God do's never faile</l>
                  <l>To ſend releife; frees them from all annoy,</l>
                  <l>"Who ſowes in teares ſhall reape eternall joy.</l>
                  <l>Teares winnes the ſoule to God; (raiſes it up</l>
                  <l>From Earth to Heav'n) drinkes deepe of mercies Cup,</l>
                  <l>Applies health's Plaiſter to the firme ſicke pulſe,</l>
                  <l>"Teares with God, never ſuffer'd a repulſe,</l>
                  <l>Wee never weepe, never devoutly cry,</l>
                  <l>Ne're drop a teare for finne, but God ſtands by.</l>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:102470:69"/>
                  <l>Puts all our <hi>Teares</hi> into his <hi>Bottle;</hi> looke</l>
                  <l>What ſaies the <hi>Pſalmiſt?</hi> are they not in thy booke?</l>
                  <l>Thou tell'ſt my wand'rings (Lord) put thou my teares</l>
                  <l>Into thy bottle; fruſtrate ſinfull feares.</l>
                  <l>"Teares trembles Hell, pacifies Mortall ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>"Blotts all our ſinnes out of the booke of life,</l>
                  <l>Ile' cry, ſaies <hi>David,</hi> to the King of Kings,</l>
                  <l>Prevailing teares with God, performe all things,</l>
                  <l>God of the <hi>Spirits</hi> of all <hi>Fleſh</hi> that can,</l>
                  <l>Rectifie ſoules; looke on me wretched man,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Holy Paul</hi> ne'r ceaſed for three yeares,</l>
                  <l>Night and day conſtantly to warne with teares</l>
                  <l>The Elders of <hi>Miletum,</hi> (them to free</l>
                  <l>From Sathans ſubtile temptings) ſo leeme,</l>
                  <l>Night and day (Lord) forever, never ceaſe</l>
                  <l>With teares, to warne, my warring fleſh to peace.</l>
                  <l>"True teares winne <hi>Heaven,</hi> all impious thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule</l>
                  <l>"Teares ſubdue Sinnes; make white the ſpotted ſoule,</l>
                  <l>"Perfumes the <hi>Body,</hi> mortifies leud ſence,</l>
                  <l>"Calmes <hi>ſtormie cares,</hi> and prove the quinteſſence</l>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:102470:69"/>
                  <l>"To all our quiet; no anguiſh, no contention</l>
                  <l>"Troubles true teares; want is ne'r thought upon</l>
                  <l>"Nor the worlds wide woe; where a bleſſed teare</l>
                  <l>"Is ſhed for ſinne, it frights away all feare,</l>
                  <l>"Gently allayes Earths tempeſt's that ariſe</l>
                  <l>"Through times deceitfull riches; beauties Eyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lachryma nunquam patitur repulſam.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="concrete_poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:70"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:70"/>
               <head>Mercies Miracle.</head>
               <p>C<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>HR<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>IST'S Setting forth from's Celeſtiall PALACE, Lodg'd in the <hi>Virgins</hi> Wombe; From that bleſt PLACE, To th'<hi>Manger</hi> went; from <hi>Marger</hi> to the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> From <hi>Croſſe</hi> departed (with his deare Blouds loſſe) Vnto the SEIVLCHER; there made all ev'n, And ſo return'd, Gloriouſly Home to HEAV'N. To HEAV'N, from whence LORD let thy SACRED FIRE, GLISTER upon my SOVLE, whoſe ſole Deſire Begges MERCIE for my Sinnes, makes knowne to THEE, THOV that haſt RAVISHT ALL, haſt Raviſht Me.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVOnder, of <hi>Angells,</hi> O thou <hi>Flaming Glory,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Mercies Miracle,</hi> thy Sacred ſtory</l>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:102470:71"/>
                  <l>Shewes thy ne'r-failing Love; it is thy love.</l>
                  <l>(Thou Lambe of God, celeſtiall Turtle-Dove,)</l>
                  <l>Thy over liberall love that does reſtraine</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sodomes</hi> juſt <hi>Plague,</hi> which thou mightſt juſtly raine</l>
                  <l>In <hi>blew flames, ſtormes</hi> of <hi>fire</hi> to conſume,</l>
                  <l>Burne up this ſinfull world, and ſcortch the plume</l>
                  <l>Of mortalls Pride; ſoules wilfully miſled,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pamper'd</hi> with <hi>Chin-deepe Luſt,</hi> fullneſſe of bread.</l>
                  <l>"Man is to <hi>Man</hi> a <hi>Monster-hearted ſtone,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"With <hi>God</hi> thet's mercy, but with <hi>Man</hi> ther's none.</l>
                  <l>God is the worlds miraculous <hi>Creater</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Holy, juſt, mercifull, <hi>Man's</hi> glorious <hi>Maker.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>God into hell, for Pride, the Divells hurld,</l>
                  <l>Gods Iuſtice drown'd, <hi>Gods</hi> mercy ſav'd the world,</l>
                  <l>God is all Eye, he brings to open light,</l>
                  <l>The darkeſt deeds and ſecrets of the night,</l>
                  <l>Man's <hi>bell-bread plots</hi> againſt the Innocent,</l>
                  <l>God ſtill contrives to'th <hi>Authors</hi> puniſhment.</l>
                  <l>God is all goodneſſe, Greatneſſe, deare delight,</l>
                  <l>His anger ſhort, his mercy infinite.</l>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:102470:71"/>
                  <l>Reade th'<hi>Everlaſting Bible,</hi> there you'l finde</l>
                  <l>His all abundant Excellence inclin'd</l>
                  <l>To chide, then ſmile, long ſuffering, but ſure,</l>
                  <l>Firſt he beginnes to ſtrike, and then to cure,</l>
                  <l>Drownes the rudd world for impious ſinne; and then</l>
                  <l>(Never to execute the like agen)</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Raine-bowe</hi> ſends, as a moſt ſacred ſigne</l>
                  <l>Of his ne'r failing mercy, love divine!</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Mercy,</hi> thy rich thought appeares to me,</l>
                  <l>Tymes <hi>golden ſpurre,</hi> to quicken and make free</l>
                  <l>Dull ſtupid ſpirits from their <hi>Iade-like</hi> pace,</l>
                  <l>Swiftly to runne Vertues celeſtiall race:</l>
                  <l>Haſte ſoule to <hi>heav'n,</hi> and thinke when thou doſt faint,</l>
                  <l>A ſtately <hi>Pace</hi> too ſolemne for a <hi>Saint.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Plough through the duſty wayes, the dirt and mire</l>
                  <l>Of fouleſt ſinnes, temptations fierceſt fire</l>
                  <l>For Mercies ſake; <hi>Mercy</hi> makes bleſt the braine,</l>
                  <l>Curbs ſinnes delight with contemplations Reine.</l>
                  <l>Mercies ſweet thought, ſtands the ſoules ſacred ſpell,</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt all the <hi>Thorry Paſſages</hi> of hell.</l>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:102470:72"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt, the ſecond put to death,</l>
                  <l>The ſecond dying, gave us all new birth.</l>
                  <l>The Tree of good and bad, and Apple gay,</l>
                  <l>Brought to the world, to caſt us all away.</l>
                  <l>Yet the ſad <hi>Tree</hi> of <hi>ſhame</hi> bare fruit to ſave,</l>
                  <l>All that beleev'd from the infernall grave.</l>
                  <l>And as our <hi>Parents</hi> firſt notorious <hi>Vice,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whipt them from out the joyes of <hi>Paradice,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So from mans crooked ſinfull waies unev'n</l>
                  <l>Chriſt <hi>entertaines</hi> us, readily to heaven.</l>
                  <l>Thinke what a raviſhing Act of love was there</l>
                  <l>Figur'd toth' life; thinke thinke, O Bleſſed, Deare,</l>
                  <l>Soule-ſaving <hi>Saviour,</hi> ſacred <hi>Purity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Raviſh my ſoule to tell thy <hi>Charity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou ſempeternall raviſhing Roſe-bud,</l>
                  <l>Who for our ſinner was ſixe times dide in bloud,</l>
                  <l>Text in ſuch <hi>Tragick letters</hi> as did ſhow</l>
                  <l>Men turn'd to Monſters; the great debt we owe</l>
                  <l>To his victorious ſufferings, that is</l>
                  <l>Mirrour of <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> man's only bliſſe.</l>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:102470:72"/>
                  <l>Did the forgetfull wretch conſider when</l>
                  <l>Hell haſt's him on, to ſome hot ſinne, and then</l>
                  <l>Finds no way left to his deſire free,</l>
                  <l>But by a narrow lane where he muſt ſee,</l>
                  <l>That never enough to be lamented loſſe,</l>
                  <l>Chriſt Ieſus Tenterd on the bloudy Croſſe,</l>
                  <l>God on the <hi>Racke</hi> for our ſpirituall food</l>
                  <l>His limbs all o're, a Charactor of blood,</l>
                  <l>All wounded, and <hi>now</hi> bleeding, crying out,</l>
                  <l>O thou that bearſt', the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſtampe about</l>
                  <l>Thy fleſh and blood; behold my bloud braine,</l>
                  <l>Was ever griefe like mine? ſicke ſoule refraine,</l>
                  <l>Reade in my wounded ſide thy backe returne,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſordid ſinnes repulſe; let thy ſoule mourne</l>
                  <l>In ſhowers of ſorrow; and to hells diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Reade ſinnes diſlike in my <hi>ſtorme beaten fate.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Vnboſome <hi>Vice;</hi> taſt from thy ſoule ſinnes evill,</l>
                  <l>And with my <hi>Scriptum eſt,</hi> ſilence the divell.</l>
                  <l>Can careleſſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> beare the thought of this</l>
                  <l>Mercies <hi>Memento,</hi> in their mindes amiſſe?</l>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:102470:73"/>
                  <l>No ſure; no helliſh <hi>heart</hi> ſo prone to ſinne,</l>
                  <l>But the rich thought of ſuch rare love muſt winne</l>
                  <l>Mans ſoule to God; and with right admiration,</l>
                  <l>(Fixt ſirme and often on our <hi>Saviours</hi> paſſion)</l>
                  <l>Force him to hate the ſinne he lik't ſo well,</l>
                  <l>And with a loathing kick, ſend it to hell.</l>
                  <l>Mercie's <hi>rememb'rance</hi> like a <hi>Curious Lute,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Renders moſt excellent <hi>Maſicke,</hi> heavenly fruite,</l>
                  <l>Points out the weary ſoule the way to Grace;</l>
                  <l>And ſpurs us on to the <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> race.</l>
                  <l>Invites the penitent minde o're clogg'd with care,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Heavenly extaſie ſpirituall</hi> fare.</l>
                  <l>Mercifull God, turne thou man's vaine deſire</l>
                  <l>To feare and trembling; let a zealous fire</l>
                  <l>Flame in the ſoules of men, let each proud eye,</l>
                  <l>Humbl'd with teares, admire thy Majeſtie,</l>
                  <l>Backward, and forward looke, calling to mind,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe multitudes of <hi>Mercies</hi> mortall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> find,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Day, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ght, Tyme, Tyde,</hi> miraculouſly given,</l>
                  <l>By thy <hi>All-ſacred</hi> hand, Great God of heav'n.</l>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:102470:73"/>
                  <l>As the young Bird then, that do's never ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>Op'ning the <hi>Mouth,</hi> untill the Damme releaſe</l>
                  <l>And cures the want it ſuffers; ſo ſhould wee</l>
                  <l>With vnlockt lipps, ſtill pray, that God would free</l>
                  <l>Our ſoules from ſinne, O 'tis a bleſſed taske,</l>
                  <l>God ne'r leaves giving, 'till we leave to aske.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dei miſericordia, plenitudo eſt virtutum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="concrete_poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:74"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:74"/>
               <head>FAITH.</head>
               <p>Nail'd to the Croſſe, there Chriſt, loſt ſoules to winne, Suffer'd the world's huge pond'rous weight of ſinne, Inſulting <hi>Foes</hi> reproach, mocks, ſcoffings, ſcorne, His ſinewes to bee Rackt, his Body torne; A <hi>kiſſe</hi> betray'd him, and a perjur'd lie, Was the reward for all his Puritie. Heav'ns wrath, Hells rage, on <hi>Chriſt</hi> all tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments fell, To ſave our Soules, from thoſe blew flames in Hell. Chriſt's whole life was a Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp; Croſſe, Active and Paſſive, and his deare Blouds loſſe, The Tragick part; the bloudy Sceane which none But He himſelfe muſt Act, and act alone: Chriſt's Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Death And Devills force did quell, He tooke the great Leviathan of hell With the Hook of his Croſſe, made him his ſlave, Captiv'd the DEVILL, and ſubdu'd the Grave.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:75"/>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:102470:75"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>FAith makes unſeene things ſeene, <hi>Faiths</hi> ſacred eye</l>
                  <l>Vn-viſore <hi>Prides</hi> painted hypocriſie,</l>
                  <l>A reſolute <hi>Faith</hi> forc'd <hi>Abram</hi> to conſent</l>
                  <l>To butcher his beloved; to content</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Mighty Maker:</hi> Faith has ever beene,</l>
                  <l>The perfect Evidence, of things unſeene.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacob</hi> by Faith obtain'd his full deſire,</l>
                  <l>Faith ſtopt the <hi>Lyons Mouthes;</hi> Faith quenches fire,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Enoch</hi> by <hi>Faith</hi> from ſence of vitall breath,</l>
                  <l>Tranſlated was, that he ſhould ne'r ſee death.</l>
                  <l>Faith made <hi>Eliah</hi> to call downe from heaven</l>
                  <l>Conſuming flames, to burne accurſed men!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſraels</hi> great <hi>Captaine</hi> by his <hi>Faith</hi> did part</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Egypts Red-Sea,</hi> went through with joyfull heart.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioſua</hi> by Faith, on <hi>Gibeon</hi> did command</l>
                  <l>The golden <hi>Taper</hi> of the <hi>Sunne</hi> to ſtand</l>
                  <l>Still; while he fought the <hi>Battell</hi> of the Lord,</l>
                  <l>Faith comes by hearing the All-mighties word.</l>
                  <l>Women receiv'd their dead rais'd up to life,</l>
                  <l>Faith conquer'd Kingomes, and ſubdues all ſtrife.</l>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:102470:76"/>
                  <l>Like a ſafe winde, which to the Sea-man ſings,</l>
                  <l>Comfort in midſt of all ſad cares, <hi>Faith</hi> bringt,</l>
                  <l>And breathes into our ſoules, Truths gentle gaile</l>
                  <l>(Salvations ſweet reliefe,) to fill the ſaile</l>
                  <l>Of Man's <hi>ſtorme-beaten veſſell;</hi> keepes it ev'n,</l>
                  <l>So ſends it home in peace to th' land of heav'n.</l>
                  <l>Faith cloathes the <hi>Soule</hi> in a divine attire,</l>
                  <l>To paſſe untoucht, through <hi>Famine, ſword,</hi> and <hi>fire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His body feeles no paine by fire, or ſword,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>Faith,</hi> is in the boſome of the Lord.</l>
                  <l>Faith is Saint <hi>Peeters</hi> walking on the water,</l>
                  <l>Hope lent him helpe, and <hi>Love</hi> was his ſupporter.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fides, Signum Chriſtianorum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="concrete_poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:76"/>
               <head>HOPE.</head>
               <p>Hope followes Faith; when Man is moſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, Ready for hell, Hope to the Soule gives reſt. Hope in the Lord, be ſtrong the Pſalmiſt ſaith, Hope ſtrengthens, comforts and confirms thy faith. Hope is Faiths daughter, Heav'ns holy Handmaid ſtill, To over-rule unruly deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p'rate will From doing damned violence, which may, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the ſoules Eternall caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away. In midſt of helliſh croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſtormes &amp; ſtrife, Hope muſt our Pilot be to a good life Our Anchor, Cable: give it then free ſcope, The ſweet's of Grace, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by hope: O my dull ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, rowze thee, fit not ſtill pond'ring on thy poore Meanes, though it be ill, be thankfull; thanke thy God, and bee not hurl'd To damn'd deſpaire, by th'malice of the world. Good luck may goe away, but good hope yet, Will never leave us, if we leave not it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:77"/>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:102470:77"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>ARe we ſo blind, ſo ſotted by the Devill</l>
                  <l>To receive good at Gods hands; and not evill</l>
                  <l>With equall thankes? have we for ſinne deſerv'd</l>
                  <l>Leaſt good, no? rather worthy to be ſterv'd.</l>
                  <l>Want threats revenge; men's ſtates muſt needs decline,</l>
                  <l>When men againſt the will of heav'n repine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hope</hi> cleares <hi>Night-ſtormes,</hi> calmes the <hi>tempeſtuous</hi> day'</l>
                  <l>Afflicted, or not afflicted, let us pray,</l>
                  <l>Deſpaire not, nor repine; let <hi>Vertues</hi> ſcope</l>
                  <l>In midſt of ſorrowes, pearch thy ſoule on Hope.</l>
                  <l>Dare Man deſpaire to live the life of <hi>Caine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And die the death of <hi>Iudas;</hi> merit paine,</l>
                  <l>The Damned feele in hell? good heav'n defend</l>
                  <l>Diſquietted ſoules from ſuch a dreadfull end.</l>
                  <l>We all are ſav'd by <hi>Hope;</hi> if in true ſence</l>
                  <l>We hope for Heav'ns Eternall Excellence:</l>
                  <l>Hope's like the <hi>Fiſher-man's Corke,</hi> deſpaire the lead,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe pond'rous weight no ſooner being ſpread,</l>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:102470:78"/>
                  <l>But it beginnes to ſinke; ſo man in ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Did not hope lift him up ſtill by the Chinne.</l>
                  <l>Yet neither Faith, nor Hope can eneſubfiſt,</l>
                  <l>Wanting ſweete Charity; ſhe is the liſt</l>
                  <l>That comprehends, and is the life of grace,</l>
                  <l>Love pittles ſtill the poore, ſeekes the Lords Face,</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spes mea Chriſto.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="concrete_poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:78"/>
               <head>CHARITIE.</head>
               <p>Charitie and Pride, both feede the poore, in the Den. Charitie to praiſe God, Pride to get praiſe of men: True <hi>Charitie</hi> in midſt of dangers winnes Safety: ſhee covers multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of ſins. Love is the Chaine of Grace, love without ſpot, which ties all <hi>Vertues,</hi> in Loves true-love knot, Three thouſand Soules, the heav'nly weeper gain'd conſtant till death, by <hi>Charity</hi> obtain'd: Not words, but good works, muſt man's Faith approve, Charitie, ever is the life of love, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence Houſe-keeper, rich &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, No Grimfac'd grumbling giver ſlothfull: Deale li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally thine Almes, chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Aimeſ-giving, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Mens ſtates, decreaſes no man's li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:79"/>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:102470:79"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>TRue Love ne'r <hi>Envies</hi> this, nor that Man's good,</l>
                  <l>The low deſcent, nor High-borne Noble blood,</l>
                  <l>Ne're makes hot boaſt of giving, never braggs,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſeeks revenge by <hi>Hell-affected</hi> Raggs,</l>
                  <l>Surpaſſing this, or that proud neighbours ſtate,</l>
                  <l>(Cauſes of miſcheife, malice, and much hate,)</l>
                  <l>But is all excellent ſweetneſſe, noble pitty.</l>
                  <l>Faire <hi>Honours</hi> ſoule, cloath'd in humility!</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Eye</hi> on Earth ſheads for his ſinne a teare?</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Eare</hi> delights <hi>Heav'ns Holy Word</hi> to heare?</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Tongue</hi> triumphs to ſpeake in Almighti's praiſe?</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Heart</hi> affected ſtands to holy waies?</l>
                  <l>Wer't not for <hi>Charity;</hi> ſhe is the Queene,</l>
                  <l>In whom all <hi>Graces</hi> of the ſoule are ſeene!</l>
                  <l>Propheſies ſhall faile, Tongues ceaſe, &amp; knowledge vaniſh</l>
                  <l>But Charity never; ſhe from ſoules can baniſh</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lust, Averices</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> with all the Rabble</l>
                  <l>Of ſinnes, which make <hi>Men</hi> truely miſerable!</l>
                  <l>"O, when we want the gift of Charitie</l>
                  <l>"We all are ſubject to impletie.</l>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:102470:80"/>
                  <l>"The Devill laies his ſtumbling blocks within</l>
                  <l>"Our waies of wickedneſſe, our daies of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>"Lures us to ſtrumpets, ſuch as <hi>Sampſon</hi> tride,</l>
                  <l>"To mighty <hi>Nabuchadnezers</hi> ſwolne pride,</l>
                  <l>"Like <hi>Acban,</hi> and <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bezi,</hi> daily He,</l>
                  <l>"Tempes Man, to covetuous Idolatrie;</l>
                  <l>Snares ſoules to <hi>Envie</hi> like accurſed <hi>Caine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Herods</hi> Selfe-love, <hi>Nabals</hi> churliſhvaine</l>
                  <l>Sinne heapt on ſinne, all thoſe blacke ſoules to ſtifle,</l>
                  <l>That thinke Adult'rie ſweet, true love a trifle,</l>
                  <l>If rich, Heav'n wills us from our plenteons ſtore,</l>
                  <l>To yeeld <hi>Truths</hi> cherefull ſuccour to the poore,</l>
                  <l>And that by ſundry <hi>Statutes</hi> God commands,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the forfeiture of life and Lands,</l>
                  <l>Confirming ſtill, the poore man to have part</l>
                  <l>In the Rich man's Eſtate; if any heart</l>
                  <l>Dares doubt this <hi>Truth;</hi> the Scripture muſt denie,</l>
                  <l>"None but an <hi>ATheiſt</hi> wrongs that pietie!</l>
                  <l>What a large extre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me folly 'tis to ſee</l>
                  <l>Man (like the <hi>Wolfe</hi> for prey) how earneſtly,</l>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:102470:80"/>
                  <l>He hunts for meanes; as if the onely honie,</l>
                  <l>Of ſoule and body did conſiſt in monle,</l>
                  <l>Meate, drinke, and cloathes; Men ſicke, ſtill pray for health,</l>
                  <l>Readie to be undone, for paltry wealth,</l>
                  <l>Freedome and ſafety, and with ſhameleſſe faces,</l>
                  <l>Forget to begg of <hi>God</hi> ſpirituall Graces.</l>
                  <l>Many men, pray but he the glory winnes,</l>
                  <l>That prayes to be disburthen'd of his ſinnes,</l>
                  <l>And viewes the poore Mans labour with the eye.</l>
                  <l>Of ſweetreliefe; ther's noble Chatitie!</l>
                  <l>The heart of ſuch a man may ſometimes ſhrinke</l>
                  <l>Vnder temptations weight, but never finke.</l>
                  <l>"God makes man here Lord ſteward of that ſtore</l>
                  <l>"He deales ſo chearefully among the poore,</l>
                  <l>"Gives him the Grace to thinke, when to his fight</l>
                  <l>Apoore wretch comes to begge of him a mite,</l>
                  <l>He might have beene that begger, his eſtate</l>
                  <l>Transferr'd on him, and begging at his gate,</l>
                  <l>Or in the ſtreete in Ragges, oppreſt with griefe</l>
                  <l>Glad to beſeech him for ſome poore reliefe:</l>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:102470:81"/>
                  <l>Wealth's the worlds Witch, deſir'd of moſt, all know it,</l>
                  <l>Yet I have read, wiſe <hi>Codrus</hi> a poore <hi>Poet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And his Wife <hi>Procula,</hi> they knew it was</l>
                  <l>Farre greater happineſſe, their dayes to paſſo</l>
                  <l>After long <hi>life</hi> unto aquiet end,</l>
                  <l>Then change their pooreneſſe, proudly to aſcend</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Ninus Throne;</hi> be wonder'd at and ſeene</l>
                  <l>T'out ſhine <hi>Semyramis;</hi> wealths wicked Queene.</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Heathens</hi> learne us <hi>Chriſtians</hi> what to doe,</l>
                  <l>Greedy deſire of wealth, workes endleſſe woe!</l>
                  <l>As wiſe <hi>Vlyſses</hi> ſerv'd his <hi>Syren</hi> Witches,</l>
                  <l>Paſſe-by the worlds pelfe; ſeeke celeſtiall Riches,</l>
                  <l>"Be rich or poore, unleſſe a beaſt thou be,</l>
                  <l>"Seeke Heav'nly wealth, or ne're looke heav'n to ſee.</l>
                  <l>Man backward goes, takes all the care he can,</l>
                  <l>Not to be godly firſt, but a rich man,</l>
                  <l>Takes care for health, long life, Phyſicks the blood</l>
                  <l>But laſt of all, leaſt care, to become good.</l>
                  <l>Cleane oppoſite to the faire rule of <hi>Truth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Truth inſtructs crooked <hi>Age,</hi> and ſtiffe-neckt youth.</l>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:102470:81"/>
                  <l>Firſt to ſeeke Godlineſſe, Riches and health</l>
                  <l>Will follow next; godlineſſe is great wealth.</l>
                  <l>What though the world frowne, muſt we ſtraight repine,</l>
                  <l>Has not Heav'n ſent us reaſon to deſine</l>
                  <l>Twixt good and evill? ought not thou and I,</l>
                  <l>Ev'ry one ſtrive to live contentedly</l>
                  <l>With our eſtates? certaine it ſhould be ſo,</l>
                  <l>Did not <hi>ſinne</hi> blind us, did we but truly know,</l>
                  <l>That which the world ſo ſcoffes at, <hi>Poverty</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>God onely ſends to trie our honeſtie,</l>
                  <l>Or diſhoneſtie; poverty is ſent</l>
                  <l>"For Vertues triall; Vices puniſhment:</l>
                  <l>He that in peace enjoyes the quiet calmes</l>
                  <l>Of flouriſhing plenty; yet gives no Almes,</l>
                  <l>But like <hi>inſatiate Hell</hi> greedy of more,</l>
                  <l>Belies his wealthy ſtate to rob the poore</l>
                  <l>Of their juſt Intreſt; diſabling himſelfe</l>
                  <l>(Baſe miſer like) to ſave his dirty pelfe,</l>
                  <l>Such falſhood, cries for flaming vengeance ſtill</l>
                  <l>To perſecute a Wretch ſo vile, ſo ill.</l>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:102470:82"/>
                  <l>'Tis not the <hi>Rich,</hi> not <hi>Poore</hi> can pleade excuſe,</l>
                  <l>Where want of <hi>Charity</hi> ſpeakes Man's abuſe.</l>
                  <l>Doſt thou want <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>es to give, <hi>Truth</hi> is thy friend,</l>
                  <l>Truth at all times inſtructs thee to extend</l>
                  <l>'Thy Almes in lib'rall manner; not to pine</l>
                  <l>In parting with thy pence, for love divine.</l>
                  <l>Admitt thou art unable to disburſe</l>
                  <l>Leaſt pecce of Coine, yet let thy emptypurſe,</l>
                  <l>Be full expreſt in a Compaſſionate groane,</l>
                  <l>A ſigh, a prayer for him that makes his moane,</l>
                  <l>And in the Holy Name of the moſt High,</l>
                  <l>Beggs ſome reliefe to ſuccour penurie.</l>
                  <l>God ever ſtands, more on the givers mind,</l>
                  <l>Then the gift given; if God but truely find</l>
                  <l>A cup of water, (in his ſacred name)</l>
                  <l>Given to the poore, God gratifies the ſame.</l>
                  <l>"The Widdowes <hi>Mite,</hi> one <hi>Farthing</hi> pleaſed more</l>
                  <l>"The Lord of Heav'n, then all the <hi>Rich Man's</hi> ſtore,</l>
                  <l>"There is no <hi>Vertue Conſtant</hi> without love,</l>
                  <l>"Nor no love perfect but from <hi>Heav'ns</hi> above.</l>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:102470:82"/>
                  <l>Witneſſe <hi>Truths</hi> ſacred <hi>Text; Heav'ns</hi> love to <hi>Man</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Amply expreſt in the poore <hi>Publican.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His humble Eyes, ſighes, cries, and bruiſed breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Forc'd ope the <hi>Gates</hi> of <hi>Mercy,</hi> gave him reſt.</l>
                  <l>With Spittle, Clay, leaſt word that did proceed</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Mercies</hi> never failing <hi>Maſter</hi> freed</l>
                  <l>The Blind, the Lame, the Sicke, the Dead from grave,</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns <hi>All-Commanding, Maker</hi> all can ſave;</l>
                  <l>O let us then in holy love betake us</l>
                  <l>To Chriſtian Charity; Now good God make us</l>
                  <l>Gratiouſly willing, for thy owne ſweet ſake</l>
                  <l>(That ſuffer'd on the Croſſe; made hell to quake)</l>
                  <l>Faſhion our wills to thine; Lord, make us know</l>
                  <l>It is our <hi>ſinnes,</hi> our <hi>ſinnes</hi> makes God our <hi>Foe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vbi Charitas non eſt Caritas.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="concrete_poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:83"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:83"/>
               <head>VERTVES PYRAMID.</head>
               <p>B<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſt Bleſt, O Bleſt, Be that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, Three Sacred Perſons GOD in Vnitie, WHOSE glorious Raviſhing Reſurrection, Reſtor'd us (loſt) to Grace, Oh PERFCTION! Purifie thou my Soule, my Heart, my Minde: Snatch me from Earth, to Heav'n make me inclin'd, Wholly to Thee, (All worldly Pompe deſpiſing) Fixe my THOVGHTS ever, On thy Bleſſed RISING: Give MEE A Sempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, To Thy All-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious high Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. I that am clog'd with ſin, and wretchedneſſe, (Deſp'rate thoughts hunting after Worldli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;) Thy bleſt Protection crave, cleare the great ſcore, Of all my foule miſdeeds, that I no more ſo great a ſinner proove; Lord let my ſtrife, Againſt my ſinnes, Raiſe mee from Death to life. And from the Foote of uggly ſinnes diſgrace, Mount, mount, my SOVLE, to th'Pyramid of GRACE.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:84"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:84"/>
               <head>Chaſtitie and Luſt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LEwd ſpeech ſtrikes bluſhes in a <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgins</hi> face,</l>
                  <l>Chaſtity is ever the <hi>Zeale</hi> of grace,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>taffe</hi> of <hi>Devotion, Enemy</hi> to Luſt,</l>
                  <l>In death true comfort; the <hi>Marke</hi> of the <hi>Juſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Siſter</hi> of <hi>Angells,</hi> and the <hi>Virgin Tie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which cleaves to God, gaines ſweete Eternity.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Luſt</hi> with all her paint, Curles, purles, &amp; pride</l>
                  <l>(Swelling in pompe) is but a naſtie Hide</l>
                  <l>A moſt infectious foe; foe to the <hi>Purſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Foe to the <hi>Perſon,</hi> and which makes it worſe,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Conſcience corroſive,</hi> confounding witt,</l>
                  <l>The minds <hi>Canker,</hi> ſoules burning <hi>Feaver</hi> fitt.</l>
                  <l>Mong all enticemcuts, pleaſures quaſſing Boule,</l>
                  <l>All the ſharpe <hi>combats</hi> of a <hi>Christian</hi> ſoule,</l>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:102470:85"/>
                  <l>None feircer then the warrs of a Chaſt mind;</l>
                  <l>Ther's a continuall <hi>Fight;</hi> which good Men find</l>
                  <l>Never ſubdu'd without wet eies, true care,</l>
                  <l>In praying; Why? the victory is rare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chaſtities</hi> ſtill, in danger 'mong delights,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Truth</hi> in much talke; Souldiers in fierce ſights.</l>
                  <l>The walls of <hi>Chaſtity</hi> once batter'd downe,</l>
                  <l>Maides looſe their <hi>Honour,</hi> Vertues rich renowne.</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Luſt,</hi> what's thy delight? thy full fruition</l>
                  <l>Of Pleaſure; but the Path way to Perdiiton,</l>
                  <l>Seandall, diſhonour, foule reproach and ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Will blaſt thy being, blot out thy good name.</l>
                  <l>"O happie is that Man, happie the Maide</l>
                  <l>"That's Chaſt; cleare conſciences are ne'r afraid</l>
                  <l>Of Iudgement, Death, and hell; no ſad affright,</l>
                  <l>Tortures the mind that's chaſt; ther's true delight.</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe the two-fold feare that do's belong</l>
                  <l>To Chaſtity and Luſt; feare to doe wrong</l>
                  <l>And grieve her Husband, is the chaſt wiſes part,</l>
                  <l>She feares her ſlack of Love; leſt he depart,</l>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:102470:85"/>
                  <l>Gives no croſſe words, no angry lookes nor ſowre,</l>
                  <l>Nor do's ſhe ſeeme to lumpe, to powte, to lowre.</l>
                  <l>She feares t'offend her husband, ſhunnes all ſtrife</l>
                  <l>Togaine his Preſence; which ſhe loves 'bove life.</l>
                  <l>But the lewd Harlot, when her Mate's from home,</l>
                  <l>Feare makes her wiſh, that he might never come.</l>
                  <l>Leſt his approach unlook't for terrifie,</l>
                  <l>And catch her in her baſe Adultery.</l>
                  <l>Shee's fill'd with feare, doubts, ſtarts leaſt creeke o'th doore,</l>
                  <l>O 'tis a dreadfull ſinne to be a Whore.</l>
                  <l>Beauty in the Face, and Luſt within the heart</l>
                  <l>Kills Soule and Body, ruines ev'ry part:</l>
                  <l>Strike me Eternall Eſſence with the dart</l>
                  <l>Of Saint-like Chaſtitie; give me a heart</l>
                  <l>Of fleſh; ſo chaſtly pleaſing, that poore I</l>
                  <l>May live in Chaſtity; a chaſt ſoule die.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:86"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:86"/>
               <head>Midnights-Meditation.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHen I contemplate Heav'n, and take no care</l>
                  <l>For worldly vanities; then my ſoule how farre,</l>
                  <l>How amorouſly faire thou art; deſtroying ſinnes,</l>
                  <l>"<hi>Man's</hi> a rich <hi>Monarch;</hi> then true joy beginnes,</l>
                  <l>Never till then; never did any fight</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt ſinne, but gain'd unſpeakeable delight.</l>
                  <l>This, when I thinke upon, and practiſe too,</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns in my eye, want nor the worſt of woe</l>
                  <l>Diſtracts my ſenſes; but when I roote my mind</l>
                  <l>On this rude world, Vertue is ſoone ſtrooke blind,</l>
                  <l>Witt, reaſon, all my ſenſes are confounded,</l>
                  <l>Devills aſſault my fleſh, my ſoule is wounded.</l>
                  <l>Save me, O ſave me Lord, thy worthleſſe Creature;</l>
                  <l>Pittie the weakeneſſe of my Mortall nature,</l>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:102470:87"/>
                  <l>Forgive all forfeitures my ſinnes have made,</l>
                  <l>Vowes, Promiſes, proteſtations never paid.</l>
                  <l>I promis'd ſtill to mend, to turne mine eyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>From ſinfull wales; yet Heav'n knowes all were lies.</l>
                  <l>Shame to my ſoule; how dare I then looke up,</l>
                  <l>Expect leaſt ſolace from ſweete Mercies Cup?</l>
                  <l>O I am angry, vext to th' very heart,</l>
                  <l>I act not thy will Lord, but mine owne part.</l>
                  <l>A ſinfull Tragicke Part which will deface</l>
                  <l>My ſoule; helpe Heav'n; ſend thy reſtraining Grace,</l>
                  <l>One Drop of <hi>Grace Celeſtiall</hi> can refreſh</l>
                  <l>A fainting ſoule; cleanſe Lord my corrupt fleſh,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vn-ſtorme ſinnes ſulphurous</hi> ſtorme; I burne I fry,</l>
                  <l>Like the impatient <hi>Fiſh,</hi> which violently</l>
                  <l>(Scorch't to the quick) it's raging heate to tame,</l>
                  <l>Leaps from the Pan, into the burning flame.</l>
                  <l>Such is the flaming Torture I endure,</l>
                  <l>Scorcht for my ſinnes; where ſhall I fly for cure.</l>
                  <l>"<hi>Want</hi> is a <hi>Mis'rie,</hi> much Wealth a trouble,</l>
                  <l>"<hi>Honour</hi> a <hi>burthen;</hi> Beautie but a <hi>bubble.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:102470:87"/>
                  <l>"<hi>Pleaſure</hi> a <hi>ſhadow, advancement dangerous <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"<hi>Friendſhip</hi> a <hi>falſe Winde,</hi> and diſgrace odious.</l>
                  <l>This world of ſinne <hi>circles</hi> my braine with ſnares;</l>
                  <l>A <hi>thouſand</hi> diſtractions, <hi>Millions</hi> of cares,</l>
                  <l>Beates on the <hi>Anvile</hi> of my poore weake head,</l>
                  <l>(To ruine ſenſe) to ſtrike all good thoughts dead;</l>
                  <l>Oft muſing on the <hi>Worlds Witch</hi>-pleaſing pelfe,</l>
                  <l>I thus beginne to argue with my ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Why might not I be <hi>Rich?</hi> ruſh, God do's ſee,</l>
                  <l>This meane eſtate of mine fitter for me.</l>
                  <l>Then I collect my <hi>Spirits,</hi> praiſe that God</l>
                  <l>Which keepes me ſtill unſcourg'd; reſtraines the Rod</l>
                  <l>Of his juſt <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>engeance,</hi> that might juſtly fall</l>
                  <l>On me, and mine; in Iuſtice ruine all:</l>
                  <l>"Had I the <hi>Worlds</hi> poſſeſſion in my hand,</l>
                  <l>All <hi>Potentates</hi> on <hi>Earth</hi> at my command,</l>
                  <l>What then? I then; ſubject to all entices,</l>
                  <l>Might fill my <hi>little-world,</hi> with <hi>World</hi> of <hi>Vices.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is enough I live, and 'tis too much</l>
                  <l>That I am fed, or cloathed, if I grutch.</l>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:102470:88"/>
                  <l>My daies of ſinne encreaſe, wax worſe and worſe,</l>
                  <l>Whither? O whither ſhall I direct my courſe?</l>
                  <l>Downe, downe foule fleſh, (great God) my ſelfe I blame,</l>
                  <l>I aske thy pardon, asking in his name</l>
                  <l>That is my <hi>Life,</hi> the <hi>Light,</hi> the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Truth;</hi> faire <hi>Truth</hi> which do's afford</l>
                  <l>Mercy to all; onely preſcribes this taske,</l>
                  <l>That whatſoever <hi>Mortall ſoules</hi> do aske</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Father</hi> in his <hi>Name</hi> it ſhall be done,</l>
                  <l>To glorifie the Father, in the Sonne.</l>
                  <l>O infinite ſweetneſſe; O Immortall love,</l>
                  <l>Thou God the Father, that doſt rule above</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Higheſt Heav'ns;</hi> Thee in the bleſſed Name</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, (Theanthropos)</hi> that came</l>
                  <l>To ſave beleeving ſoules, I aske, implore,</l>
                  <l>Pardon, O pardon; out with ſinnes rotten core</l>
                  <l>Rooted too neare my heart; whiſper thy feare</l>
                  <l>Into my ſoule; let me not onely heare</l>
                  <l>Thy ſacred word, but (in the practicke part)</l>
                  <l>Make perfect uſe of it; nere let me ſtart</l>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:102470:88"/>
                  <l>From thee my God; let ſad Teares from mine eyes,</l>
                  <l>And ſighes from my heart expreſſe my grievancies.</l>
                  <l>Though I fall foule and fearefully each day,</l>
                  <l>Lord let me not fall finally away.</l>
                  <l>And I if needs muſt fall, let my fall be,</l>
                  <l>From death to life, from ſinne to ſanctity.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amor Dei, amorem Deo parit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:89"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:89"/>
               <head>The Divine Dreame.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVOrme that I am; O how ſhall I begin</l>
                  <l>To praiſe that God, that in my ſleepe 'gainſt ſin</l>
                  <l>Gave divine warning; ſent truths ſacred ſcrole</l>
                  <l>Which to and fro, hovring i'th' Ayre, did role</l>
                  <l>This way, and that; at laſt, as if Heav'ns will</l>
                  <l>Had ſo decreed; the waving ſcrole ſtood ſtill,</l>
                  <l>(Much like the <hi>golden Taper</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>At the command of <hi>Man;</hi> the ſonne Nun)</l>
                  <l>In which me thouht I read, and read it ore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Peccair no majs;</hi> that is, ſinne no more</l>
                  <l>Written in Spaniſh; this ſeeming ſight ſo ſtrange,</l>
                  <l>Workt in my dreaming ſpirit ſuch a change</l>
                  <l>That ſtartling from my drowſie ſleepe I cride</l>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:102470:90"/>
                  <l>To heav'n; thus inſtantly with <hi>Teares</hi> repli'd</l>
                  <l>O ſacred Saviour, humbly I implore,</l>
                  <l>Give me the ſpirit of <hi>Grace</hi> to ſinne no more.</l>
                  <l>For I am blind; ſinne <hi>clouds</hi> my <hi>ſence</hi> of ſeeing</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>good,</hi> my <hi>ill;</hi> I'me <hi>Natures</hi> brittle being,</l>
                  <l>Vext to the ſoule; ſo infinitely oppreſt</l>
                  <l>With ſighes and groanes, they cannot be expreſt.</l>
                  <l>What ſhall I doe? great Natures miracle,</l>
                  <l>Thou onely <hi>wiſe God, Heav'ns</hi> firme <hi>Oracle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Faſhion me to thy will; tip out with the core</l>
                  <l>Of ſinne in me; that I may ſinne no more.</l>
                  <l>Say to my ſoule, leſt I in ſoule deſpaire,</l>
                  <l>"Thy grace ſufficient is; Cure Lord my care.</l>
                  <l>"Speake but the word (at the <hi>Centurion</hi> ſaid)</l>
                  <l>"Thy ſervant ſhall he heal'd; Lord be my aid.</l>
                  <l>"No <hi>Rod</hi> ſo ſharpe, nor no <hi>diſcaſe</hi> ſo ſore,</l>
                  <l>"But thy good <hi>Grace</hi> can cure, to ſinne no more.</l>
                  <l>Thou Lord by holy Text confirm'd doſt ſay,</l>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:102470:90"/>
                  <l>I am the Lord that heales; I <hi>Ropeca:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"Thou God the true Phiſitian art that can,</l>
                  <l>"Be mine, Lord be ſo; pitty me weake man.</l>
                  <l>God my <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> and his <hi>Grace</hi> the <hi>Phyſicke</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I muſt not, will not, cannot be <hi>ſin-ſicke.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nomo loeditur niſi a ſeipſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:91"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:91"/>
               <head>THE DIVINE ECCHO, BETWEENE THE GOOD ANGELL, Man in deſpaire, And the DEVILL.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>DEath to my <hi>Soule,</hi> how long muſt I in vaine</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns comfort crave? yet endleſſely remaine.</l>
                  <l>Fetter'd in ſinne? breake <hi>Heart,</hi> give death free ſcope</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And</hi> muſt I then deſpaire? is there no hope?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Angell</speaker>
                  <p>Hope.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>What Soule affected ſpirit to mine Eare</l>
                  <l>Eccho's ſome ſweet releife? can hope come neare</l>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:102470:92"/>
                  <l>Sinnes <hi>ſhackl'd Slave</hi> from whom all <hi>Verues</hi> gon?</l>
                  <l>What's to be Hop'd for? when all hopes are done?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Angell.</speaker>
                  <p>Pardon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>How; <hi>Pardon,</hi> can <hi>Pardon</hi> raiſe a wretch</l>
                  <l>Times reprobate like me? I that can fetch</l>
                  <l>Nor ſigh, nor teare, ſinnes furie to abate,</l>
                  <l>Can <hi>Heav'n</hi> free ſuch a <hi>Soule?</hi> ſo deſolate?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>Too late.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>Too late indeede; my <hi>Sinnes ſicke ſtonie</hi> heart,</l>
                  <l>Traytor to <hi>Truth; Acts</hi> the <hi>Tragedian's</hi> Part</l>
                  <l>Of ill ſo well; I know not what to doe,</l>
                  <l>Frights, terrours, broken ſleepes, all ſpeake my woe,</l>
                  <l>Yet <hi>Holy Writ</hi> tells me, 'tis better ever,</l>
                  <l>Late to repent, then to repent me never.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:102470:92"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>Never.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>O my horrour (never) thou deadly accent,</l>
                  <l>Art thou from Heav'n or Hells curs'd dungeon ſent</l>
                  <l>Muſt my deſpairing thoughts for ever bend</l>
                  <l>To Helliſh Actions? ſhall I ne'r amend?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Angell.</speaker>
                  <p>Amend.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>Amend I cannot, guifts of <hi>Grace</hi> I lacke</l>
                  <l>Like him that weares <hi>Heav'ns Livery</hi> on's backe</l>
                  <l>Hells favour in his boſom; wretched I</l>
                  <l>Will <hi>Fate</hi> afford no preſent remedie!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>Die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſoule muſt then miſcarrie and be damb'c.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>Be damb'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:102470:93"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>Is that the onely ſolace, all the pitty</l>
                  <l>Sterne <hi>Fate</hi> affords poore Man in miſery?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>I.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>Was my <hi>Creation</hi> in the <hi>Wombe</hi> of woe</l>
                  <l>Ordain'd for <hi>Hell?</hi> no otherwiſe then ſo</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>So.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>Die then I muſt; and will, appoint me where.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>Here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>So quicke: O true <hi>Phyſition,</hi> for to die</l>
                  <l>I hold it beſt; and to linke ſuddenly.</l>
                  <l>Here in this Deſart then, where no eye ſees,</l>
                  <l>Expreſſe the meanes to die among theſe Trees.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:102470:93"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Trees.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>If mong theſe <hi>Trees</hi> appoint to me an <hi>Altar?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>An <hi>Halter.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>To be hang'd is baſe, better to drowne my ſelfe,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>Do, drowne thy ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>No no, I will not die ſo like a <hi>Rat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Cicken,</hi> or a <hi>Mouſe,</hi> a <hi>Dog,</hi> a <hi>Cat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But like the deſp'rate <hi>Stateſman</hi> I will be</l>
                  <l>Made nothing by a <hi>Dramme;</hi> poyſon to me</l>
                  <l>Is pretious balme; I will die by poyſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill</speaker>
                  <l>I, poyſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:102470:94"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis the true death, beſt Cure 'gainſt diſcontent</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Noble-Mans</hi> conſumption; my intent</l>
                  <l>Huggs the conceit; And yet my ſoule to ſlay</l>
                  <l>By touch or taſt, is no true Roman way</l>
                  <l>Canſt thou not change thy word?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy ſword.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall my <hi>Sword</hi> then ſet free from all the ſtrife</l>
                  <l>Of Worldly woes? this mockery of life:</l>
                  <l>Can my ſword ſoone quit me from out this ſtraight?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
                  <l>Straight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>I tifle time; come forth thou maine ſole good,</l>
                  <l>Thou cure to all my cares; ſweete <hi>ſword</hi> in blood</l>
                  <l>I'le drowne thy friendly <hi>Blade;</hi> tis the beſt Part</l>
                  <l>Thou ere canſt <hi>Act,</hi> to cleave thy Maſters heart.</l>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:102470:94"/>
                  <l>Fly ſoule to <hi>Ayre, Flame, Duſt,</hi> I know not where,</l>
                  <l>Earth, ſerve thou me for <hi>Coffin</hi> and for <hi>Beere,</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Angell.</speaker>
                  <p>Forbeare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>Who bids forbeare? what Potent power commands</l>
                  <l>My ſoule to live? my ſword and trembling hand</l>
                  <l>To ſtop their bloudy courſe? is it in Fate</l>
                  <l>To alter Mans intent before too late,</l>
                  <l>Turning ſwift miſchiefe to that ſudden ſtay</l>
                  <l>Whom death but ev'n now would make her Prey?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Angell.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray, unto whom? my <hi>ſoule</hi> is in a miſt,</l>
                  <l>See ſee, me thinkes the <hi>Everlaſting</hi> Fiſt</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Heav'n</hi> is ſtretcht, waving the <hi>Crowne</hi> of grace</l>
                  <l>Over my <hi>Curſed</hi> head, <hi>Soule,</hi> ſinfull Face,</l>
                  <l>Ayme accurſt; I doe deſerve the Rod</l>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:102470:95"/>
                  <l>Of <hi>Vengeance,</hi> rather then to pray to God</l>
                  <l>For the leaſt drop of <hi>Mercy:</hi> No I muſt</l>
                  <l>Not dare to pray to him, for he is juſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Angell.</speaker>
                  <p>Juſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>And by his <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> my impietie</l>
                  <l>Merits <hi>Eternall endleſſe</hi> miſerie,</l>
                  <l>Sinnes juſt reward; O teach me yet the way</l>
                  <l>Thou <hi>Divine Eccho;</hi> to what place to pray,</l>
                  <l>From whence implored mercy may be giv'n,</l>
                  <l>To cleare my ſinnes great ſcore, and make all ev'n.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Angell.</speaker>
                  <p>Heav'n.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>What words will beſt he fit, and not betray me,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Angell.</speaker>
                  <p>Aye-mee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>Deſpaire deteines me backe, commands me ſay</l>
                  <l>I have no <hi>Will;</hi> no <hi>Minde,</hi> no <hi>heart</hi> to pray</l>
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:102470:95"/>
                  <l>What ſhall I doe? my ſoule is in a <hi>Feaver</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in that word deſpaire I ſhall end ever.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Angell</speaker>
                  <p>Endeavour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>O ſacred ſweetneſſe, true <hi>Caeleſtiall</hi> witt,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſumme of ſweetnes ſtampt in ſacred writ,</l>
                  <l>Endeavour, yes, ſinnes ſtrife is the beſt play,</l>
                  <l>My ſoule can <hi>Act;</hi> God <hi>give, heav'n</hi> I obey.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Angell.</speaker>
                  <p>Obey.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cum humi limus, cur non humilimus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:96"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:96"/>
               <head>Deaths Maſqueing Night.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AS mighty Kings in glorious <hi>Maſques</hi> delight,</l>
                  <l>Death, <hi>(Times Grand-Maſquer)</hi> had his maſqueing Night.</l>
                  <l>In evr'y <hi>Pallace,</hi> ev'ry <hi>Nooke</hi> Death ranges</l>
                  <l>Death takes his root from ſinne, Hee's full of changes.</l>
                  <l>With ſolemne <hi>Pace</hi> unſeene, <hi>Death</hi> dos advance</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Sable ſhaft,</hi> to lead the <hi>World</hi> a dance.</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Courts,</hi> though <hi>Armyes,</hi> the <hi>worlds wide Hall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Controul'd of none, Death is the end of all.</l>
                  <l>Wher's then the Mighty Monarch? wher's the glory</l>
                  <l>Of all his <hi>Court? State, Maſques, joyes</hi> tradſitory?</l>
                  <l>Beauties bright <hi>Earth-Bred-Star?</hi> whoſe ſparkling eye</l>
                  <l>Shoots quivers of <hi>Love-ſhafts</hi> at <hi>Rich</hi> Majeſtie.</l>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:102470:97"/>
                  <l>Death ſhall deface, and in the bed of night,</l>
                  <l>Yeild farre more cauſe of terrour, then delight.</l>
                  <l>Wher's then the, wanton glance that ſeem'd to skip</l>
                  <l>From this <hi>Great Lord?</hi> to that <hi>Great Ladyes</hi> Lap?</l>
                  <l>The <hi>nymble, Sprightly, Cap'ring, Courtier</hi> then</l>
                  <l>Forgotten lies; there is no dancing when</l>
                  <l>Devouring Death, ſtabs with his ſable ſhaft,</l>
                  <l>Vaine is the power of <hi>Art;</hi> all mundane craft.</l>
                  <l>The deepe Phyſitians skill, flatt'ring diſcourſe</l>
                  <l>Of health; Death ſoone, turnes to a diſmall courſe.</l>
                  <l>Wher's then? the mighty Madams fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reing Pride?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oyles, Powders, Paintings?</hi> all are laid aſide.</l>
                  <l>Gold glittring <hi>Glory, Cloath</hi> of <hi>Silver ſilke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Forgetfull Feaſts, their ſinfull <hi>Baths</hi> of Milke</l>
                  <l>(When many a poore ſoule ſterves, wanting the food)</l>
                  <l>Of their ſupurfluous out-ſide) pamper'd blood</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gurles, Purles, Purfumes,</hi> Court complements, viſites,</l>
                  <l>Hot-ſtirring <hi>Diſhes,</hi> ſoule bewitching Minuts,</l>
                  <l>All <hi>Pompe</hi> on <hi>Earth,</hi> ambitious mad deſires,</l>
                  <l>Revells and <hi>Luſt-burnt Midnights</hi> unchaſt fires.</l>
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:102470:97"/>
                  <l>All are huſht then; Beggers and Kings, all muſt,</l>
                  <l>Take a poore lodging in a bed of duſt.</l>
                  <l>Death is a dreadfull Antimaſque, 'twill fright</l>
                  <l>The worlds Grand Maſquer in his full delight!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Figures</hi> and <hi>Footings,</hi> practiz'd to intrance</l>
                  <l>Spectators <hi>Eyes,</hi> Deaths interpoſing <hi>Dance,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Diſſolves to darkeneſſe, in a moments ſpace</l>
                  <l>Ruines proud <hi>Pompe;</hi> makes pale th'aluing Face</l>
                  <l>Sparkling in <hi>Beanty;</hi> deads the hot deſire</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Naked Breſts;</hi> Death tames Luſts raging fire,</l>
                  <l>Wounds without dread or dalliance; Death will ſtrike,</l>
                  <l>Sou'raignes and ſubjects, all are to him alike.</l>
                  <l>To Rich and Poore thoſe that doe ill, or well,</l>
                  <l>Death is the <hi>Path,</hi> either to <hi>Heav'n,</hi> or Hell.</l>
                  <l>Deaths dread appearance evermore makes glad</l>
                  <l>The good; but proves a terrour to the bad.</l>
                  <l>Disjoynts the ableſt limbs; Death trembles Pride,</l>
                  <l>Extincts <hi>State-Glories</hi> will not be denide</l>
                  <l>Death is an <hi>Archer,</hi> Man the <hi>Marke</hi> to ſhoot at</l>
                  <l>Fly where thou wilt, <hi>Eaſt, Weſt,</hi> this way, or that,</l>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:102470:98"/>
                  <l>Death followes like a <hi>ſhaddow,</hi> ſhoot he will,</l>
                  <l>Drawes ſure and home; Death never failes to kill</l>
                  <l>And yet, none truely mindes it; though we know</l>
                  <l>Time ſhall decay, we cannot feede nor goe</l>
                  <l>Nor promiſe life a Minute, men paſſe to bed,</l>
                  <l>But ignorant are to riſe, alive or dead.</l>
                  <l>Death by a thouſand accidents do's meet</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Health, Wealth,</hi> and Beauty, ſtabs 'em in the ſtreet.</l>
                  <l>He that leaſt dreames of death, ſome falling Tyle</l>
                  <l>Timber, or Stone, doth ſuddenly beguile</l>
                  <l>Him of his life, yea oft, when Man refraines</l>
                  <l>And ſeekes to ſhunne it, daſhes out his braines,</l>
                  <l>This learnes us <hi>Mortalls,</hi> during vitall breath,</l>
                  <l>With humble <hi>ſoule</hi> to meditate on Death.</l>
                  <l>The thought of Death aright, prevents the evill</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Hells Night</hi> Theife, &amp; the worlds Noone-day Devill</l>
                  <l>Death's deepe remembr'ance rightly underſtood</l>
                  <l>Strikes dead delights, lures the lewd mind to good.</l>
                  <l>Wafts the <hi>ſinne weary ſoule</hi> to thinke upon</l>
                  <l>Her ill paſt life, preſent affliction.</l>
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:102470:98"/>
                  <l>O <hi>ſinne-ſicke-ſinfull Man,</hi> feare to doe ill</l>
                  <l>Tremble proud <hi>Heart,</hi> croſſe not thy Makers will,</l>
                  <l>Thinke on thy end; thinke on the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Doome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The paines of Hell; <hi>Deaths-Maſqueing Night</hi> wil come</l>
                  <l>Not in the Pompe of Princely merriment,</l>
                  <l>But the dread fall of ſoules impenitent,</l>
                  <l>Ingratefull <hi>Soules</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> ſoules that dare ſit</l>
                  <l>I'th ſcorners ſeate truſting to wicked wit</l>
                  <l>More then their Makers wiſedome; their conceit</l>
                  <l>Aimes not at Heav'n, but to be worldly great.</l>
                  <l>Pride is their <hi>zeale,</hi> theie Prayers forgetfulneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Charity <hi>Contempt,</hi> their <hi>Vivtue</hi> wantonneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Plump high fed <hi>Pamper'd Fleſh</hi> on whom muſt waite</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Page, Pander, Paraſite,</hi> preparation, ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Gold glitt'ring glory, coſt, curious diet,</l>
                  <l>Inſatiate pleaſure, and vaineglorious Riot.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are the ſinnes that merit endleſſe ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Hells ever burning, never dying flame.</l>
                  <l>Which to prevent, (Great God) let hate to vice</l>
                  <l>Diſſolve ſinnes <hi>Cloud,</hi> Becho to Paradice.</l>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:102470:99"/>
                  <l>Our Saviours ſweetneſſe, let us never more,</l>
                  <l>Lie downe to our diſhonour like a whore.</l>
                  <l>Dead to good Counſell; never let darke deedes</l>
                  <l>Defile the ſoule; let's roote up all the ſeeds</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Pride, Luſt, Envie, Hatred,</hi> and in place,</l>
                  <l>Plant Wiſedome, meeke Humility and Grace,</l>
                  <l>Abhorre to ſtudy State with greater zeale</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>zeale</hi> to <hi>Heav'n,</hi> or the ſoules-common-weale.</l>
                  <l>True <hi>Penitence</hi> gaines <hi>Heav'n,</hi> throwes ſinners downe,</l>
                  <l>To raiſe them up, to an Immortall Crowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cogita de fine infinito, ut vives in infinitum.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:102470:99"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
